<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?>
<cwn>
<cwn_head>
  <cwn_date>2003.10.28</cwn_date>
  <cwn_prev>2003.10.21</cwn_prev>
  <cwn_next>2003.11.04</cwn_next>
  <cwn_date_text>21 to 28 October, 2003</cwn_date_text>
</cwn_head>
<cwn_body>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Question about linking C++ and OCAML</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Dan Koppel asked and Kamil Shakirov answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I'm new to OCAML.  I have written C++ code which needs to call a
&gt; OCAML subroutine (written by somebody else).  I'm using a Windows
&gt; XP/Pentium 4 system and have the Microsoft Visual C++ compiler.  I
&gt; was wondering if anybody has experience doing this and could kindly
&gt; give me some instructions on how to accomplish this.

You may use the ODLL tool from the http://tech.motion-twin.com/

``ODLL is creating a Win32 DLL from an OCaml library, and
automatically generating the C stubs needed to interface the OCaml
code and the C code and the .H interface. Simply run ODLL with you
CMA/CMXA and one or several CMI interfaces and ODLL will do the job
for you.''

I hope it helps you.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>ocamlgsl release</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Olivier Andrieu announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
This is to announce the release of ocamlgsl version 0.3.0 .

ocamlgsl is a set of bindings for GSL, the GNU Scientific Library
http://sources.redhat.com/gsl/ . GSL is "a collection of routines for
numerical computing" : this includes RNGs, special functions, FFT,
linear algebra, numerical integration, etc.

What's new:
 - support for the latest GSL (version 1.4)
 - bugfixes
 - compiles with MSVC (contributed by Lexifi)

available here :
http://oandrieu.nerim.net/ocaml/gsl/
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Enhanced Ocaml Documentation Version 3.07</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Hendrik Tews announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I would like to announce the

                 The Enhanced Ocaml Documentation
                          Version 3.07
   available via http://wwwtcs.inf.tu-dresden.de/~tews/htmlman-3.07


The enhanced documentation contains the original html version of
the ocaml reference manual with the following changes:

- Changes (wrt version 3.06) are tagged with icons and color

- meta symbols of the grammar are "hot" and refer to their
  definition.

- additional appendix containing just the grammar rules


Browsing through the Enhanced Ocaml Documentation you will
discover the following changes that have not been announced in
http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200309/msg00313.html :

- character literals can be given hexadecimal line '\x40'
- matching or-patterns is now guaranteed left-to-right
- OCAMLRUNPARAM can be given in hexadicimal
- new ocamllex argument -ml (use an ocaml engine) and -o (output file)
- parametrized ocamllex lexers
- in ocamllex one can choose between "shortest match" and "longest match" rule
- 4 new options for ocamldoc/texinfo: -info-entry, -info-section,
  -noheader, and -notrailer
- new function Buffer.add_substitute
- new printf conversion %! (flush)
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>IBM funding for OCaml on Eclipse?</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Greg K said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Anyone want to do something with OCaml on Eclipse?

IBM has a million dollars in grants for teaching and research efforts done
with their extensible open source IDE. (I currently use it for Java work -
its very good, reminds me of Smalltalk dev environments.) It's designed to
be extensible to support other languages (currently has a strong working
C++ extension, and many other languages coming along).

Any OCaml proposals should probably include some work to allow Java and
OCaml runtimes to inter-operate.

Proposals are due by November 7th.

http://www-3.ibm.com/software/info/university/products/eclipse/eig.html
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>perl4caml 0.3.6 and mod_caml 1.0.0</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Richard Jones announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce two new free software products from Merjis Ltd.:

 * perl4caml 0.3.6  - use Perl code and libraries within Objective CAML   
 * mod_caml 1.0.0   - OCaml bindings for the Apache API (and much more!)  

(I'm combining these two announcements into one to reduce list bandwidth)

More information about perl4caml here:

        http://www.merjis.com/developers/perl4caml/

More information about mod_caml is available here:

        http://savannah.nongnu.org/files/?group=modcaml
        http://www.merjis.com/developers/mod_caml/

In addition, if you install both perl4caml and mod_caml at the same
time, then you can use any Perl DBD (database driver) with the
mod_caml DBI database layer. Perl DBDs are available for a wide
variety of databases.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>partial eval question</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Ben Kavanagh asked and Damien Pous answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Say I have a function such as pow defined as
&gt;
&gt; let pow n x =
&gt;     let rec pow_iter (n1, x1, p1) =
&gt;         if (n1 = 0) then p1
&gt;         else if (n1 mod 2 = 0)
&gt;                then pow_iter(n1/2, x1*x1, p1)
&gt;              else pow_iter(n1-1, x1, p1*x1)
&gt;     in pow_iter(n, x, 1);;
&gt;
&gt; and I say
&gt;
&gt; let pow2 = pow 2
&gt;
&gt; Are there any ML implementations that would automatically perform
&gt; partial evaluation to create pow2 instead of using closures, possibly
&gt; unfolding the pow_iter call? Would Caml ever have this capability?

Multi-Stage Programming is your friend...
http://www.cs.rice.edu/~taha/MSP/

There are two ML implementations :
Ocaml : MetaOCaml http://www.cs.rice.edu/~taha/MetaOCaml/
SML : MetaML http://www.cse.ogi.edu/PacSoft/projects/metaml/


let rec pow n = .&lt;
        .~(match n with
                | 1 -&gt; .&lt; fun x -&gt; x &gt;.
                | n -&gt; .&lt; fun x -&gt; x * .~(pow (n-1)) x&gt;.
        )
&gt;.

(pow 3) get reduced into .&lt;fun x -&gt; x*x*x&gt;.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Dmitry Lomov added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
May I also humbly draw your attention to Dynamic Caml:
http://oops.tercom.ru/dml

:)
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Ocamlodbc</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Alex Baretta asked and Erik Arneson answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I'm working on interfacing a piece of Ocaml code with an Oracle
&gt; dbms. I noticed that Ocamlodbc does support Oracle, and I've been able
&gt; to build both the unixodbc and the ocamlodbc/oraclecfo libraries. I'd
&gt; like to know what C client libraries/ODBC drivers i need for Oracle to
&gt; work with ocamlodbc.

You will need the Oracle client installation and an ODBC driver.  As
far as I know there are no stable freely-available Oracle ODBC drivers
for UnixODBC, but there are a few commercial drivers that look pretty
nice.

&gt; Also, does anyone know if there is a "native" client library for
&gt; Oracle à la libpq de PostgreSQL?   

Search the Caml Humps for the OCaml OCI library.  There is one out
there.  I have used it with success.  Here's the URL:

                   http://oci8ml.sourceforge.net/

Good luck!
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Sebastien Ferre added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I recently implemented an access to Oracle for OCaml.
I just use the free C library libsqlora8, which provides
an easy interface to Oracle, and wrap it in a OCaml module.
The interface is simple, and probably limited, but I think
it is suitable to most uses.

The C library is available at http://www.poitschke.de/libsqlora8/ .
I can give you the wrapping code (a C file + a ML file), if you wish.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
</cwn_body>
</cwn>
