<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?>
<cwn>
<cwn_head>
  <cwn_date>2004.06.08</cwn_date>
  <cwn_prev>2004.06.01</cwn_prev>
  <cwn_next>2004.06.22</cwn_next>
  <cwn_date_text>01 to 08 June, 2004</cwn_date_text>
</cwn_head>
<cwn_body>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Library parsing S-expressions?</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Yamagata Yoriyuki asked and Bruno Verlyck answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Does anyone know a library converting S-expressions to AST?
&gt; Preferably, it would allow 8-bit characters in symbol names,
&gt; because I want to parse the file using Japanese symbol names.

There&apos;s something like this in Cash, a sort of Scheme reader, in fact.
Files sexp.ml*, atomo.mll, schlex.ml*.  Anything that&apos;s not something
else (number, string) is a symbol, with 8-bit chars if any.  The
lexical syntax is inspired by Scheme, but the source is small and
should be easy to modify.

Bruno.
http://pauillac.inria.fr/cash/
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>ocamljitrun - new release (for new method send)</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Basile Starynkevitch announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I just adapted ocamljitrun - see
http://cristal.inria.fr/~starynke/ocamljit.html to the new cached
sending method protocol (as in Ocaml CVS and probably future release)
   
The cached method send [ie the new GETPUBMET bytecode operation] uses
a cache (in the bytecode), and calls runtime routine (in byterun/obj.c
- functions caml_get_public_method and caml_cache_public_method) only
for cache misses. The cache test and retrieval is inlined (inlining
the dichotomical search is not worthwhile, it would expand the
GETPUBMET bytecode into about a hundred bytes of machine code...).

Ocamljitrun still don&apos;t run on PowerPC because of a pending GNU
lightning book (which is worked on by lightning authors).
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Calling all Seattle Caml riders</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Jeff Henrikson said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Brandon Van Every and I would like to organize the first ever Seattle Ocaml SIG.  Any Seattle Caml   
riders please reply.  We would like to know you are out there, even if you don&apos;t want to meet us     
offline.                                                                                             
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>CFP:  MetaOCaml Workshop</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Walid Taha announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
 URL:  http://www.metaocaml.org/workshop04/

 Submission deadline: July 1, 2004
 Notification of acceptance: August 31, 2004
 Camera ready: October 20, 2004

 A half-day tutorial will also be given the day before (see URL).

------------------------------------------------------------------

                        MetaOCaml Workshop

      GPCE&apos;04 Workshop (Vancouver, Canada, October 25th, 2004)


MetaOCaml is a multi-stage extension of the widely used functional
programming language OCaml. It provides a generic core for expressing
macros, staging, and partial evaluation. The workshop is a forum for
discussing experience with using MetaOCaml as well as possible future
developments for the language. The scope of the workshop includes all
aspects of the design, semantics, theory, application, and implementation
of MetaOCaml. The workshop welcomes reports on

  - novel applications (especially interpreters),
  - extensions (macros, new language constructs, offshoring translations),
  - implementation techniques (compilation, RTCG), support (debugging,
    profiling),
  - educational use,
  - basic theory (staging annotations, static typing, static analysis,
    environment classifiers, etc).

Each submission will be reviewed by at least three members of the
Program Committee (PC). The PC will work to provide detailed and
constructive comments to the authors. The workshop will only have informal
proceedings, and is intended to be close in spirit to the Haskell, ML, and
Scheme workshops.

Based on author requests and PC decisions, authors will be given either 25
minute or 15 minute slots to present their ideas, and both will be
followed by 15 minutes of questions and discussion. At the end of the
workshop, one hour will be allocated to an open discussion to review the
outcomes of the meeting, and to discuss future challenges and directions
for MetaOCaml.

For uniformity, authors are encouraged to use the latest ACM SIGS
conference style file (option 1). We also request that submissions be
limited to 12 pages in this style. Registration for the workshop is part
of registering for GPCE&apos;04. The event is co-located with OOPSLA&apos;04, which
already provides housing and transportation information.

Program Committee

 * Zine El-Abidine Benaissa, Intel   * Kedar Swadi, Rice U.
 * Cristiano Calcagno, Imperial C.   * Walid Taha, Rice U. (Chair)
 * Rowan Davies, U. W. Australia     * Todd Veldhuizen, Chalmers U.
 * Ralf Hinze, U. Bonn               * Stephanie Weirich, U. Penn
 * Robert Glück, DIKU &amp; Waseda U.    * Hongwei Xi, Boston U.
 * Oleg Kiselyov, FNMOC
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
</cwn_body>
</cwn>
