<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?>
<cwn>
<cwn_head>
  <cwn_date>2004.06.22</cwn_date>
  <cwn_prev>2004.06.08</cwn_prev>
  <cwn_next>2004.06.29</cwn_next>
  <cwn_date_text>08 to 22 June, 2004</cwn_date_text>
  <cwn_extra_head>Sorry for not sending the CWN last week, I was abroad with no internet access.
</cwn_extra_head>
</cwn_head>
<cwn_body>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>MLGame library</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Lukasz Lew announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I&apos;m please to announce MLGame library 0.112, available here:
http://mlgame.sourceforge.net/

MLGame is a library designed to help developers create 2d games by
providing a high level interface for graphics, network, etc.

Features

    * Sprites with collision (per pixel or per rect)
    * Contexts (parts of screen may display parts of world)
    * Network (high level protocol with callbacks)
    * Console and Menu (based on a parser with variables, aliases, ...)
    * Binding keys to game actions

---

Some time ago we stopped developing it.
Now it seems that some more work is needed.
If You are ready to continue our work, contact us.

Regards,
Cezary Kaliszyk       cek@students.mimuw.edu.pl
Lukasz Lew          l.lew@students.mimuw.edu.pl
Dominik sidorek d.sidorek@students.mimuw.edu.pl
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>More or bignums/ints</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>John Hughes said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I&apos;ve read the May interchange in CWN that started with the question

&gt; I have made a web search to understand which kind of support for                                   
&gt; bignums is available for OCaml...                                                                  

and found it interesting. I&apos;ll be teaching a few weeks of ML as part
of a first-year course at Brown University, and we&apos;ve used SML in
previous years. SML/NJ works OK, but we&apos;d like a debugger, so I&apos;ve
looked at OCaml as a possible alternative. I was a little depressed
to find (by trial and error) that &quot;int&quot; doesn&apos;t mean &quot;integer&quot; but
rather &quot;element of Z/nZ for some very large n, represented with
integer notation, including negative signs.&quot;
    
I think I can live with this if only there&apos;s some way to write
something like this (pseudo-ML/Java):

fun fact(0) = 1
  | fact(n) = try {                                                                                  
                 n * fact(n-1)
              }
              catch (IntegerOverflow e) ...


What I don&apos;t think I can bear is to use the sorts of &quot;bignum&quot;-like
libraries that make me write things like

 y = x bigadd big-unit

to mean

 y = x + 1

because our students will actually be writing some code that has
a good deal of arithmetic in it.

---

So the questions are

1. Is there a way to catch overflow exceptions within an entire
   computation?
2. Is there a way to tell OCaml that ints really are either
   (a) bignums or
   (b) overflow-protected ints (as in SML/NJ, for instance)

Perhaps the implicit third question is

3. Is there a reasonable debugger for some dialect of ML that has
what I might call &quot;protected integers&quot;?

Thanks very much in advance.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; 1. Is there a way to catch overflow exceptions within an entire
&gt;    computation?

Not that I know of.

&gt; 2. Is there a way to tell OCaml that ints really are either
&gt;    (a) bignums or
&gt;    (b) overflow-protected ints (as in SML/NJ, for instance)

No. Old Caml had (a), but this is more than 10 years ago.
Note however that you may redefine operators if you want to:

exception Int_overflow

let (+) a b =
  let c = Pervasives.(+) a b in
  if a &lt; 0 &amp;&amp; b &lt; 0 &amp;&amp; c &gt;= 0 || a &gt; 0 &amp;&amp; b &gt; 0 &amp;&amp; c &lt;= 0
  then raise Int_overflow;
  c

This is going to be pretty slow, but if this is for beginners this
shouldn&apos;t matter too much.
And it won&apos;t change the behaviour of other operations in the library,
but you don&apos;t want to: they may depend on the rollover behaviour.

&gt; Perhaps the implicit third question is
&gt;
&gt; 3. Is there a reasonable debugger for some dialect of ML that has
&gt; what I might call &quot;protected integers&quot;?

I don&apos;t know, but it should be possible to hack ocamlrun to check for
overflows. Combined with C primitives, you could also set whether an
exception should be raise or not.
A bit more painful than the above approach, but this should run
faster.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Brian Hurt answered as well</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I was a little depressed
&gt; to find (by trial and error) that &quot;int&quot; doesn&apos;t mean &quot;integer&quot; but
&gt; rather &quot;element of Z/nZ for some very large n, represented with
&gt; integer notation, including negative signs.&quot;

Yep.  Generally mod 2^n for some n.  This is because this is what the
hardware supplies for fast integer arithemetic.  &quot;Fixing&quot; this, so that
ints are real (mathematical) integers entails a *huge* performance cost,
for very little gain.

&gt;
&gt; I think I can live with this if only there&apos;s some way to write
&gt; something like this (pseudo-ML/Java):
&gt;
&gt; fun fact(0) = 1
&gt;   | fact(n) = try {
&gt;                  n * fact(n-1)
&gt;               }
&gt;               catch (IntegerOverflow e) ...
&gt;

There are two problems with this: 1) most CPUs don&apos;t support throwing
exceptions on integer overflows, because 2) the CPU throwing an exception
is incredibly expensive (two complete pipeline drains (the same cost as a
mispredicted branch), and two task switches (into and back out of the
OS)).

You might be able to modify the ocaml compiler to add overflow checking
code.  Most CPUs have a &quot;jump on overflow&quot; instruction.  But currently, an
integer add takes at most 2 instructions (the second instruction to deal
with the tag bit), and often only one.  This change would cause an add
instruction to take at least two, maybe three, instructons- for a
signifigant performance hit (this is assuming that the throwing the
exception code is factored out).

How big of a performance hit, I don&apos;t know.  I note that on the Great
Language Shootout page, SML/NJ has a much lower performance score than
Ocaml or MLton.

Note that the numeric people have exactly the same problem, and are more
likely to hit it than your average code.

&gt;
&gt; What I don&apos;t think I can bear is to use the sorts of &quot;bignum&quot;-like
&gt; libraries that make me write things like
&gt;
&gt;  y = x bigadd big-unit
&gt;
&gt; to mean
&gt;
&gt;  y = x + 1
&gt;
&gt; because our students will actually be writing some code that has
&gt; a good deal of arithmetic in it.

Define new operators.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Xavier Leroy answered as well</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; 1. Is there a way to catch overflow exceptions within an entire
&gt;    computation?
&gt; 2. Is there a way to tell OCaml that ints really are either
&gt;    (a) bignums or
&gt;    (b) overflow-protected ints (as in SML/NJ, for instance)

Solution (a) is problematic because of literals.  It&apos;s easy to
redefine the infix `+&apos; operator to mean &quot;bignum addition&quot;, and
similarly for other arithmetic operators, but OCaml has no syntax for
bignum literals, e.g. to get the bignum 123 one needs to type
Int 123 or num_of_string &quot;123&quot;.  A Camlp4 syntax extension could
possibly do the job, however.

Solution (b) is much easier, provided you don&apos;t care much for
performance (probably true for an intro course).  Stick the following
definitions in, say, CS101.ml

  exception Overflow

  let ( + ) a b =
    let c = a + b in
    if (a lxor b) lor (a lxor (lnot c)) &lt; 0 then c else raise Overflow

  let ( - ) a b =
    let c = a - b in
    if (a lxor (lnot b)) lor (b lxor c) &lt; 0 then c else raise Overflow

  let ( * ) a b =
    let c = a * b in
    if Int64.of_int c = Int64.mul (Int64.of_int a) (Int64.of_int b)
    then c else raise Overflow

  let ( / ) a b =
    if a = min_int &amp;&amp; b = -1 then raise Overflow else a / b

[Note that the definition of ( * ) above assumes a 32-bit processor.
 Something even less efficient is required to work both on 32- and 64-bit
 architectures.]

Compile this source to CS101.cmo and make sure that the module CS101 is
linked and opened in the students&apos; code.  For instance, with the
interactive toplevel loop, make them stick

   #load &quot;/path/to/CS101.cmo&quot;;;
   #directory &quot;/path/to&quot;;;
   open CS101;;

in $HOME/.ocamlinit, and voila, every time they start ocaml, they get
overflow-protected integers.

Don&apos;t even think of modifying the OCaml bytecode interpreter so that
the arithmetic operations of the abstract machine perform overflow
detection: some code in the standard library and the compilers rely on
modulo arithmetic.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Manos Renieris added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I think you also need

    let ( ~- ) x = if x &lt;&gt; min_int then -x else raise Overflow

(~- is unary minus, commonly typed in as &quot;-&quot;)

You still get
    -1073741824=1073741824
being true if you type in the exact literals. I think fixing this
requires tweaking the parser.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>troubles with polymorphic variant in class</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>François-Xavier Houard asked</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I&apos;m working on an ocaml GUI library -more information about it later, on
the list ;)

I&apos;m now working on an introspecting side of this GUI library; in a GUI,
every composant can have some child, and have a father.
The choice I&apos;v made is to have a class for every type of composant, and
an object for every composant, for example, I have a window class, a
frame class (inheriting window), a button class, a panel class, etc.

So, as every composant can have different type of father, every object
is parametrized by the type of his father, for example, a button in a
panel in a window is, for the moment, typed as
window panel button
as the button class looks like that:
class [&apos;a] button (father:&apos;a)
.....
and the panel too,etc

I find it nice, cause every widget has got his &quot;genealogic tree&quot; in his
type.
  
What I wan&apos;t now is to store every widget child in a list.
as every child should be from a different type, and as I wan&apos;t the user
to be able to add his own widget-class later, I first thought of the use
of polymorphic variant, like that:
        
class [&apos;a] button (father:&apos;a) =
object(self)
  val f = father
  val mutable childs = [`Whatever]
  method add_child (x) = childs &lt;- x::childs
  method get_variant  = `A self
end;;

but caml tells me that:
The method add_child has type ([&gt; `Whatever ] as &apos;a) -&gt; unit where &apos;a
is unbound

This could be solved by adding a &apos;b parameter to my class:

class [&apos;a, &apos;b] button (father:&apos;a) =
object(self)
  val f = father
  val mutable childs = [`Whatever]
  method add_child (x:&apos;b) = childs &lt;- x::childs
  method get_variant :&apos;b = `A self
end;;

but this may make my class type unreadable:

[&gt; &apos;Whatever | `Window of window ] window [&gt; &apos;Whatever | `Window of
window | `Panel of panel ] panel [&gt; &apos;Whatever | `Window of window |
`Panel of panel | `Button of button ] button

So, I have 2 questions:
_ Why should an open type as [&gt;`Whatever] be parameter of a class ?? As
far as I know it, [&gt;`Whatever] is equivalent to [&gt;`Whatever | `Foo of
bar | `Foobar of foobar ], isn&apos;t it ?? so what problem would it make for
the inheritage stuff (which are the reason of the use of parameter)
_Is there another way to make it ??? (yes, i know coca-ml, but, another
way ??)
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Skaller answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; The method add_child has type ([&gt; `Whatever ] as &apos;a) -&gt; unit where &apos;a
&gt; is unbound

&gt; _Is there another way to make it ???

The notation [&gt; `X] does not denote a type, but a family
of types (all types containing variant `X). Alternatively
you might say it is a type constraint.

But a list must have elements of a definite type.
You can define the type as for ordinary variants:

type widget = [ `Whatever | `Window of window | `Button of button]

and now make a widget list.

Unfortunately, you cannot add child widgets to a button
like this:

class button = object
  val mutable (childs:widget list)
  method add_child x = childs &lt;- x::childs
end

because button isn&apos;t defined yet .. and neither
is window... so you can&apos;t define widget.
        
Unfortunately the obvious way to fix this doesn&apos;t
work due to a syntactic problem in Ocaml:
  
type widget = ...
and class window = ...
and class button = ...

is what you need: mutual recursion. But it isn&apos;t allowed
to mutually recurse types and classes (not even class types).

So a direct solution is unfortunately impossible.
You must add a type parameter to each class like this:

class [&apos;w] button&apos; = ... (childs: &apos;w list)
class [&apos;w] window&apos; = .. .(childs: &apos;w list) ...

and now you can define:
  
type &apos;w widget&apos; = [`Window of [&apos;w] window&apos; | ...
  
Because these things all use a parameter,
they can all be defined without any mutual
recursion. So now you do this:

(* fixpoint *)
type widget = &apos;w widget&apos; as &apos;w

which effectively solves the type equation
&apos;w = &apos;w widget (and names the result widget).
Now define non-polymorphic classes:

class button = [widget] button&apos;
class window = [widget] window&apos;

This is not so bad for a single parameter &apos;w.
For multiple parameters the notation soon becomes
too unwieldy to be practical.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>François-Xavier Houard replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
But the answer you gave me, which I find quite nice, don&apos;t allow my user
to add his own class....
I could do the stuff with a parametrized module (the parameter given by
the user would contain the variant used in the program... Including the
ones of my library!!), or, even uglier, use a close variant in my
module, which would be like:
[ Window of window | Frame of frame | User_variant of &apos;a ]

And &apos;a, the parameter of the module, given by the user, would also be a
variant...

module SillyModule =
struct
        type t = [ MyWindow of myWindow | MyText of myText ];;
end
;;
module myGui = Gui (SillyModule);;
let a = new Window;;
let x = new myText a;;
let l = a#get_child in
match l with
h::t -&gt; (match h with
                myGui.User_variant v -&gt;
                        ( match v with
                            MyText t -&gt; .......
                            | _ -&gt;
                        )
                | _ -&gt; raise Not_found
        )
.....


Who the hell would use this ???

So, if I can&apos;t find a better solution, i could still try to find a
sado-m(l)asochist mailing list, to find potential users !

;))

Let&apos;s be more serious. What you said is fine, but, please, tell me there
is an easier solution to make it work with user defined class...
Please....
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Damien Doligez proposed</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
You don&apos;t really need to obfuscate your own code:

  match a#get_child with
  | MyGui.User_variant (MyText t) :: tt -&gt; .......
  | _ -&gt; raise Not_found
  ....
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Skaller also proposed</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Here is another solution: visitor pattern.

class &apos;w window = object (self)
  val mutable childs: &apos;w list
  ...
  method iter (f:&apos;w -&gt; unit) =
    List.iter f childs
end

.... user now can write:
  
type &apos;w mywidgets&apos; = [`A of &apos;w a_kind&apos; | `B of &apos;w b_kind&apos; .. ]
  
class [&apos;w] a_kind&apos; = object .....
class a_kind = widget a_kind&apos; ...

etc etc as before. Now the *user* must unify all the types
with a variant, but the class doesn&apos;t need to know
what is is until it is instantiated.

One way or the other there is no alternative to unifying
all the widget types with a sum (variant) or an abstraction
(class supertypes) or both.

Typical GUI like GTK do both (there are run time
tests for kinds of widgets, so you can do button
specific things on any kind of button etc).
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Nakata Keiko answered the original message</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I hope this would be of some help.

module type Ct = sig type t end

module type Crec =
  sig
    module T : Ct
    class button : object method add_child : T.t -&gt; unit end
  end

module COt(Crec : Crec) =
  struct type t = [`Whatever|`Button of Crec.button]
  end

module CO(Crec : Crec) =
  struct
    module T = COt(Crec)
    class button =
      object
        val mutable children : T.t list = [`Whatever]
        method add_child x = children &lt;- x::children
      end
  end
module rec X : (Crec with module T = COt(X)) = CO(X)

As I done, you can specify the type of elements of the list &quot;children&quot;
inside &quot;COt&quot;.
The above code is taken from
http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200403/msg00344.html
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>otags 3.07.1</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Cuihtlauac Alvarado announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Otags 3.07.1 is out:

  http://perso.rd.francetelecom.fr/alvarado/soft/otags-3.07.1.tar.gz
  
Thanks to Hendrick Tews, main contributor of this release.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>OCaml compared as a scripting language</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Richard Jones said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
It may interest people to know that OCaml was compared to other
computer languages for scripting:

http://merd.sourceforge.net/pixel/language-study/scripting-language/

It comes out somewhere in the middle.  A file utils library and extlib
could help.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Florian Hars replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt;I think it&apos;d be possible to assemble a very capable scripting language
&gt;without affecting the core language at all.

Isn&apos;t this what cash is about (minus the regexp stuff and the camlp4 sugar)?
http://pauillac.inria.fr/cash/
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>string_of_float -&gt; float_of_string locale dependency bug</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Evgeny Chukreev asked and Xavier Leroy answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; /tmp% echo $LANG
&gt; ru_RU.KOI8-R
&gt;
&gt; /tmp% ocaml -I /usr/local/lib/ocaml/3.07/camomile/ bigarray.cma camomile.cma
&gt;         Objective Caml version 3.07+2
&gt;
&gt; # float_of_string &quot;0,&quot;;;
&gt; - : float = 0.
&gt; # string_of_float 0,;;
&gt; Syntax error
&gt; # string_of_float 0.;;
&gt; Fatal error: exception Failure(&quot;float_of_string&quot;)

Do you have the same error if you don&apos;t load camomile.cma?  From a
quick test here, I believe not.

The Caml runtime system does depend on the LC_NUMERIC locale begin set
to its default value &quot;C&quot;, but it ensures that this is the case by never
calling setlocale(LC_ALL, &quot;&quot;) nor setlocale(LC_NUMERIC, &quot;&quot;).

Third-party libraries can invalidate this invariant by calling e.g.
setlocale(LC_ALL, &quot;&quot;).  Two possibilities:

- The library doesn&apos;t really need LC_ALL, e.g. it would be enough
  to set LC_CTYPE or LC_COLLATE and leave LC_NUMERIC unchanged.
  In this case, the library should be fixed.

- The library really needs to set LC_NUMERIC, in which case it&apos;s
  impossible to use that library with the Caml toplevel.

The C library API for internationalization is largely broken, and as
you can see there is nothing we can do to work around the fact that
the current locale is a global variable for the whole program.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>ocamllex/yacc and camlp4</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>John Goerzen asked and Luc Maranget answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Quick question: why are ocamllex and ocamlyacc not implemented with
&gt; camlp4?  They seem to be doing exactly what camlp4 is there for, and I
&gt; think would serve as great camlp4 examples (plus being able to extend
&gt; *their* syntax could be very powerful indeed.)

Hello,

First there is history, ocamllex and ocamlyacc predate camlp4, thus
they were not written with camlp4 initially.

Second there is bootstrap. Since the lexer and parser of ocamlc itself
are written with ocamllex/ocamlyacc, Making these tools to depend on
camlp4 would include camlp4 in the bootstrap cycle of ocamlc.
The resulting situation would complicate bootstraping ocamlc.

Of course there could be camlp4 versions of ocamllex/ocamlyacc in
addition to ocamllex/ocamlyacc versions of ocamllex/ocamlyacc. Well,
nobody ever thought about doing that, I guess.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Pierre Weis added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I would add two points to Luc&apos;s answer:

 1) ocamllex and ocamlyacc implementation technologies are damned fast
and it is difficult to compete with them using streams.

 2) Semantics differences between Yacc and functionnal parsing are
large and complex, so that implementing the precise Yacc semantics
with its reduce/reduce and shift/reduce conflicts and the default
conflicts resolution that Yacc also implements could not be a trivial
task.

Last but not least, the actual ocamllex/ocamlyacc implementations work
pretty well, so that there is no clear necessity to rewrite them.

In conclusion: pure Camlp4 implementation of ocamllex/ocamlyacc is
still an interesting and challenging progamming task for the next few
years, if you (or someone else) had the will and time to provide two
``great camlp4 examples&apos;&apos; to the rest of us...

Happy hacking :)
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Alain Frisch added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt;  1) ocamllex and ocamlyacc implementation technologies are damned fast
&gt; and it is difficult to compete with them using streams.

As I understand it, the question was about implementing ocamllex/ocamlyacc
frontend (parsing the specifications) and backend (producing OCaml code)
using Camlp4, not about implementing lexers/parsers using Camlp4 grammars.

I wrote a pa_ocamllex some time ago (and it is included in the OCaml
distribution), but it is no longer in sync with new ocamllex features
(capture variables).

Using Camlp4 to parse the specifications has several advantages: simpler
build procedure (no intermediate file to be generated), support for
alternative syntaxes (e.g. the revised syntax).
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Great Programming Language Shootout Revived</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Brian Hurt said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Thought I&apos;d point this article out for the people who&apos;ve stopped reading
slashdot:
http://developers.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=04/06/16/1622211&amp;mode=nested&amp;tid=126&amp;tid=156&amp;tid=185&amp;tid=90

The original GPLS was the best advertising Ocaml ever had.  It&apos;s why I
learned Ocaml- I discovered the original GPLS and started noticing Ocaml
ranking among the top scorers for fastest execution, least memory used,
and fewest lines of code, and said to myself &quot;I&apos;ve got to check that
language out- obviously there&apos;s something going on there.&quot;

What&apos;s starting to happen, now that the project has started up again, is
advocates/supporters of other languages have started to submit improved
versions of the code for their languages.  For example, I notice that
Ocaml has dropped from it&apos;s #1 place in least lines of code to #2, with
Ruby taking the lead.
  
I don&apos;t think we need to make a big thing out of this (hey, #2 across the
board is pretty damned good- we&apos;re beating both Java and C++ across the
board, in fact the only other language that comes close to Ocaml&apos;s
performance is, unsurprisingly, version of SML- MLton and SML/NJ).  But if
you have some spare time, and want to help out Ocaml&apos;s marketing, wander
over.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>... and many people replied ...</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
You can find the rest of this thread starting at:
http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200406/msg00234.html
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Implementing DSLs in OCaml/CamlP4</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Richard Jones asked</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Are there any decent tutorials on using OCaml/Camlp4 as a
Domain-Specific Language (DSL)?  I was intrigued by
http://www.venge.net/graydon/talks/mkc/html/index.html but it was fair
to say that I didn&apos;t really understand the finer points of what he was
talking about.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Walid Taha answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I like that talk, and especially that discussion on safety.  MetaOCaml
provides safer support essentially the same approach.  Good starting
points would be:

        http://www.cs.rice.edu/~taha/publications/journal/dspg04b.pdf
and     http://www.cs.rice.edu/~taha/publications/journal/dspg04a.pdf
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Missinglib 0.4.1</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>John Goerzen announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Missinglib 0.4.1 is now ready.  It represents major new effort since
0.0.1 was announced on caml-list.  This library is designed to provide
all those useful but missing features that the standard library
lacks.  Its pieces are designed to be used independent of each other,
so you do not have to subscribe to the &quot;Missinglib way&quot; just to use a
few of its functions (though its pieces do complement each other).
        
The &quot;crown jewels&quot; of Missinglib include the ConfigParser, a flexible
framework for reading and generating configuration files; and
Streamutil, which provides many elegant stream-related functions such
as map, filter, map_stream, and of_channel_lines.

 [ Please add missinglib to the Humps.  Thanks. ]

Here is an excerpt from the README (API docs are at the URLs below):

Author: John Goerzen &lt;jgoerzen@complete.org&gt;
URL: gopher://quux.org/1/devel/missinglib
     http://quux.org/devel/missinglib

-------------------------
What is Missinglib?
-------------------------

It&apos;s a collection of OCaml-related utilities.  The following modules are
are provided:

Compose                 Utilities for chaining functions together

Composeoper             Haskell-like operators for chaining functions

ConfigParser            System for parsing configuration files
                        These configuration files can have multiple
                        sections and resemble .INI files.  This module
                        is designed to be mostly compatible with
                        Python&apos;s ConfigParser module.

Hashtbloper             Hash table convenience operators

Hashtblutil             Hash table utilities

Lexingutil              Lexing-related utilities

Listutil                List-manipulation utilities
                        Functions are provided to help extract
                        portions of lists and be more convenient
                        for association lists.  Also, lists of strings
                        or chars can be written directly to output channels.

Slice                   Underlying API for Slice operators

Sliceoper               Flexible subparts of arrays, lists, and strings

Streamutil              Stream parser, conversion, and creation utilities
                        Provides features to create streams the yield
                        the lines of an input channel, the blocks of an
                        input channel, convert finite
                        streams to lists, map and filter streams
                        (similar to those functions on lists), and
                        fold streams.

Strutil                 String-related utilities
                        Includes functions to strip whitespace from
                        the beginning or end of strings, to split
                        strings into lists by whitespace or a custom
                        delimeter, etc.

Unixutil                Operating system utilities
                        Includes functions to process directories
                        (possibly recursively), test for file
                        existence, and an implementation of &quot;rm&quot;
                        with &quot;-r&quot; and &quot;-f&quot; options.

The entire library has no prerequisites save the OCaml standard library and
findlib and is designed to install without complexity on a variety of
systems.  It could also easily be embedded within your own source trees
so that users need not have it installed beforehand.

** THIS IS CURRENTLY ALPHA-QUALITY CODE; MAJOR API FLUCTUATIONS MAY YET OCCUR.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Interface between Ocaml and C++</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Gu Nu asked and Art Yerkes answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Does anybody know how to deal with C++ classes, such
&gt; as vectors, maps, in Ocaml? It seems that currently
&gt; Ocaml can  only support the interoperation of C. So
&gt; the first step is to try encapusuate a C++ class with
&gt; C interface, then write C interface for Ocaml.
&gt; However, it is so inconvient for std classes. Does
&gt; anybody has any better ideas?

The SWIG module for Ocaml has support for a few STL
types.  If you use those interfaces as a guide, you
could add support for more if the automatic wrapping
doesn&apos;t suit.

SWIG isn&apos;t perfect for everyone but some needs are
met very well, including using templates.

Look at http://www.swig.org/
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Eray Ozkural then asked and Art Yerkes answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; How does it handle convert C++ templates to ocaml code, I wonder. I had a
&gt; design in my mind, but it required quite a bit of monkeying around. What&apos;s
&gt; their solution?

The current solution is to specify which specializations of a given template
will be needed, after which the specialized template classes are treated as
ordinary classes.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>mod_caml's bytecode restriction due to Apache or just CGI dyn'linking?</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>James Leifer asked</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I had a question about mod_caml&apos;s design.  I understand from the web
page that confining CGIs to bytecode isn&apos;t particularly onereous.  The
argument that most of the overhead is in talking with the db makes
perfect sense.

Yet for some applications, native would be useful.  For example, for
read-only data that changes only a few times a day, one can pack it in
Ocaml hash tables and get high perfomance queries right in Ocaml.  In
such a setup where Ocaml handles both the page layout *and* the
functionality of a db, native code looks a lot more attractive.

So... Is the limitation to use bytecode due to the desire to support
*dynamic* linking of CGIs or for other reasons?  If only the former,
then could one simply forgo this feature and *statically* link all the
natively compiled CGIs together with the mod_caml glue to make a
library that gets delivered to Apache?  If the price is that I have to
restart Apache when changing my CGIs I would be willing to pay it.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Richard Jones answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; So... Is the limitation to use bytecode due to the desire to support
&gt; *dynamic* linking of CGIs or for other reasons?

Basically, yes.  We would need a version of Dynlink supporting native
code.

&gt; If only the former, then could one simply forgo this feature and
&gt; *statically* link all the natively compiled CGIs together with the
&gt; mod_caml glue to make a library that gets delivered to Apache?  If
&gt; the price is that I have to restart Apache when changing my CGIs I
&gt; would be willing to pay it.

&apos;Tis possible.  However I don&apos;t have any applications where having
natively compiled CGIs would make any noticable difference, so this
isn&apos;t the sort of thing which Merjis would develop.  However if you
have patches ...
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Basile Starynkevitch said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Sorry for the shameless plug - but I think that ocamljit can be used
to accelerate a bit such Ocaml propulsed web pages.

The GNUmakefile of ocamljit not only build the ocamljitrun executable
(a replacement for ocamlrun), but also a libcamljitrun.a which should
be a replacement for libcamlrun.a and hence might be useable (at least
on x86/linux) with mod_caml.

I suppose that mod_caml don&apos;t fork a process for every HTTP request
(in contrast to a pure CGI approach). This is particularily
appropriate for ocamljit since the overhead of bytecode to native
machine code translation is much less relevant here. (On pure CGI
short runs with ocamljitrun the translation time might be significant
- a few tenths of seconds for a &quot;big&quot; bytecode file).

Feel free to ask me about any practical problems of using ocamljit
with mod_caml (I didn&apos;t try, but believe it should be trivial).

Ocamljit is available on
http://cristal.inria.fr/~starynke/ocamljit.html and requires a recent
(ie CVS or future 3.08) ocaml system (source tree with built stuff)
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>James Leifer asked and Basile Starynkevitch answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; So, ocamljit plays well with dynamic .cmo linking?

Yes, it was designed to mimic as much as possible the bytecode interpreter.

The main misfeature of ocamljit is lack of [ocaml] debugger support -
because the few debug related bytecodes are not supported by it (in
the case yu run into them, you got a loud fatal error!)
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Parse crazy HTML, output XML</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Richard Jones asked and Gerd Stolpmann answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I have a bunch of HTML documents from an external source which I do
&gt; not control.  They aren&apos;t valid XML, by any means.  I need to read
&gt; them in, do a &quot;best effort&quot; to build a DOM, do various manipulations
&gt; over the DOM (such as removing &lt;script&gt; tags, replace &lt;B&gt; with
&gt; &lt;strong&gt;, etc.), and output an XHTML fragment.  I also need to do this
&gt; from an OCaml program.
&gt;
&gt; Example input:
&gt;
&gt; ---
&gt; This is &lt;B&gt;the sort of document&lt;/B&gt; which I have to parse.&lt;br&gt;
&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&gt; ---
&gt;
&gt; Desired output:
&gt;
&gt; ---
&gt; &lt;p&gt;
&gt; This is &lt;strong&gt;the sort of document&lt;/strong&gt; which I have to parse.
&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&gt; ---
&gt;
&gt; The problem is the parsing phase.  Both PXP and XmlLight will only
&gt; parse valid XML (as far as I can see).  Is there any simple pure OCaml
&gt; library for parsing HTML and producing a DOM?

The Nethtml of ocamlnet can do this (ocamlnet.sourceforge.net).
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
</cwn_body>
</cwn>
