<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?>
<cwn>
<cwn_head>
  <cwn_date>2004.10.19</cwn_date>
  <cwn_prev>2004.10.12</cwn_prev>
  <cwn_next>2004.10.26</cwn_next>
  <cwn_date_text>12 to 19 October, 2004</cwn_date_text>
</cwn_head>
<cwn_body>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>ssl-libraries</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200410/msg00117.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Johann Spies asked and Samuel Mimram answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Are there any libraries available for ssl-connections using ocaml?

I have made small &amp; quick bindings to ssl to be able to use ssl
encryption with unix sockets. I am willing to improve it, just tell me
if you need some (or much) more functions.

The library is named ocaml-ssl and you can find it here :

http://savonet.sf.net/
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Jason Hickey also answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
We use openssl in MetaPRL and have implemented an appropriate OCaml API.
I have extracted the SSL-specific files and placed them in
http://www.cs.caltech.edu/~jyh/ssl .  This can get you started, but it
may be a bit more than what you want--it also includes buffered IO and a
printf function.  You can strip the buffered IO code if you want just a
plain socket interface.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Narrowing class's public interface</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200410/msg00122.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Tony Edgin asked</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
What is the reasoning behind Ocaml not allowing the public methods of a class
to be hidden?

Some times its nice for a class to have &quot;global&quot; public methods (Java&apos;s public
methods) as well as public methods local to its module (Java&apos;s unprefixed
methods).  This allows for progressive encapsulation, where more distance
modules no very little about a class, while the more local modules know more
about the class.  Inheritance could be used to approximate this, but
sometimes subtyping makes more sense.

I apologize for my lack of clarity.  For those who couldn&apos;t understand my
question, here&apos;s an example.

module RandomVariables =
struct
        class type rv_type =
        object
                method instance : float
                method scale_by : float -&gt; rv_type
                method add : rv_type -&gt; rv_type
        end

        class gaussian _stdev _mean =
        object
                method stdev = _stdev
                method mean = _mean

                method instance =  (* elided *)
                        (** Returns a draw from the corresponding distribution.
                          *)

                method scale_by a =
                        new gaussian ((abs_float a)*._stdev) (a*._mean)

                method add (other : guassian) =
                        let sigma = sqrt (_stdev**2. +. other#stdev**2.)
                        and mu = _mean +. other#mean
                        in
                                new gaussian sigma mu
        end

        (* Truncated *)
end

(* Bad code which I would like to use *)
class gaussian_rv =
        (RandomVariables.gaussian float -&gt; float -&gt; RandomVariables.rv_type)

;;
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; What is the reasoning behind Ocaml not allowing the public methods
&gt; of a class to be hidden?

This is just a type soundness problem: as an ocaml object type only
describes the interface of an object, you have no way to make sure
that an object had originally a specific method (with the right type)
once you have hidden it.
Of course we could add some kind of declaration like
   method hidden m : type
and allow a subclass to convert a public method into such an &quot;hidden&quot;
one, but I&apos;m quite sure this is not what you are asking for?
(Note that such an addition would be rather heavy, as &quot;hidden&quot; method
must appear in object types too, i.e. &lt; hidden m : type; ... &gt;)

&gt; Some times its nice for a class to have &quot;global&quot; public methods
&gt; (Java&apos;s public methods) as well as public methods local to its
&gt; module (Java&apos;s unprefixed methods).  This allows for progressive
&gt; encapsulation, where more distance modules no very little about a
&gt; class, while the more local modules know more about the class.
&gt; Inheritance could be used to approximate this, but sometimes
&gt; subtyping makes more sense.

This problem has been thought of :-)
Look at the user&apos;s manual, section 3.17, for how to define &quot;friend&quot;
methods, i.e. methods accessible only from code in the same module.
Note that since ocaml modules are hierarchical, this actually allows
you more precision than Java&apos;s packages.

http://wwwfun.kurims.kyoto-u.ac.jp/soft/ocaml/htmlman/manual005.html#ss:friends
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>John Prevost added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
To expand a bit on what Jacques said, there are a lot of places in
O&apos;Caml where there are very very elegant ways to do things that a
background in more traditional OO languages might not make you think
of.  Here&apos;s a version of your original code that highlights just a
couple of those things:

module RandomVariables =
  (struct

    (* First thought: What if we make a generic random_variable class
       that could work for types other than float?  The most generic
       version can only describe its type and the method that returns
       an instance of the RV.  Here we see a class type with a type
       variable, describing a method instance that returns a value of
       that type.  There&apos;s no real reason to define this class type,
       except to provide a shorthand--when we say &quot;x random_variable&quot;,
       we mean a random variable that returns values of type x. *)

    class type [&apos;a] random_variable =
      object
        method instance : &apos;a
      end

    (* Of course, the rv_type class that you originally described had
       slightly more functionality.  Specifically, a scale_by method and
       an add method.  The first thing to note here is the type &apos;s, which
       is the &quot;self type&quot; for the object.  An object that is a
       float_random_variable has a method scale_by that takes a float and
       returns a new object with the same type as the original object.
       Likewise, add on an object of type t takes a second object of the
       same type, and returns a new object of the type those objects
       share.  This also shows us that if we want to add arbitrary
       random variables together (not just random variables of the same
       type), we&apos;re going to have to do things differently some day.

       The &quot;inherit [float] random_variable&quot; is shorthand for including
       that class type in this class type, specialized for the given
       type &quot;float&quot;.  Since O&apos;Caml uses structural subtyping, it&apos;s not
       necessary to inherit just to say that this is a subtype.  But it&apos;s
       easier than duplicating the definition. *)

    class type float_random_variable =
      object (&apos;s)
        inherit [float] random_variable
        method scale_by : float -&gt; &apos;s
        method add : &apos;s -&gt; &apos;s
      end

    (* This is the trick shown in the O&apos;Caml manual for &quot;friends&quot;.  We
       define a new type gaussian_repr, which will carry the &quot;secret value&quot;
       for our gaussian random variables.  We can&apos;t use the module type
       to hide the existence of a method for getting the internal
       representation--but we *can* prevent anyone outside this module
       from making use of the value once they get it.  See below in the
       module&apos;s signature. *)

    type gaussian_repr =
        { g_stdev : float;
          g_mean : float }

    (* The class is refactored slightly.  Note the use of {&lt; ... &gt;}
       instead of &quot;new gaussian ...&quot;.  This ensures that the new object
       is of the same type as the original object.  If you ever want to
       inherit from gaussian to re-use code, this means that the inheriting
       class will work correctly, instead of returning gaussians it will
       return new instances of itself.  Notice that we had to make a field
       repr to hold the internal state, instead of using the constructor&apos;s
       closure.  Without the &quot;val repr&quot;, we can&apos;t use {&lt; ... &gt;} to copy
       the object and change the intenral state of the new copy.

       The &quot;method value&quot; is another part of the friends trick.  Notice
       how we use it in add to get the repr of the other gaussian.  We
       could instead have hidden the return types of the original &quot;stdev&quot;
       and &quot;mean&quot; methods in your version--but I chose to change it to
       this so that it doesn&apos;t look too odd.  Remember we can&apos;t get rid
       of the methods, so users of the API would wonder &quot;why can&apos;t I get
       the stdev and mean out of the gaussian?!?&quot; *)

    class gaussian stdev mean =
      object (_ : &apos;s)
        val repr = { g_stdev = stdev; g_mean = mean }
        method value = repr
        method instance = (*fake*) repr.g_mean
        method scale_by a = {&lt; repr = { g_stdev = (abs_float a) *. stdev;
                                        g_mean = a *. mean } &gt;}
        method add (other : &apos;s) =
          let repr&apos; = other#value in
          let sigma = sqrt (repr.g_stdev ** 2.0 +. repr&apos;.g_stdev ** 2.0) in
          let mu = repr.g_mean +. repr&apos;.g_mean in
          {&lt; repr = { g_stdev = sigma; g_mean = mu } &gt;}
      end

  end : sig

    (* Okay.  Signature time.  The class types are identical. *)

    class type [&apos;a] random_variable =
      object
        method instance : &apos;a
      end

    class type float_random_variable =
      object (&apos;s)
        inherit [float] random_variable
        method scale_by : float -&gt; &apos;s
        method add : &apos;s -&gt; &apos;s
      end

    (* And here&apos;s where we hide the type of the representation.  We don&apos;t
       give a type equation after &quot;type gaussian_repr&quot;, so the type
       becomes opaque outside of this module. *)

    type gaussian_repr

    (* And now the definition of the gaussian class&apos;s type.  Here I just
       inherit all of the methods defined in the float_random_variable
       class type, and then add a new method &quot;value&quot;, which returns type
       &quot;gaussian_repr&quot;.  The name might be even better
       &quot;gaussian_internal_state&quot; or whatever, to show why the type
       definition is hidden from outside. *)

    class gaussian : float -&gt; float -&gt;
      object
        inherit float_random_variable
        method value : gaussian_repr
      end

  end)

And then we can proceed to use the above, which does compile cleanly.

Now, something to note:

Even though we inherit float_random_variable in the type for class
gaussian, gaussian is not, and never will be, a subtype of
float_random_variable.  The trouble is that we have a binary method
here.  Because add has type &apos;s -&gt; &apos;s, we can never discard any
internal state access methods.  Why not?  Think about what happens if
you put a variety of float_random_variables in a list.  Now you take
the first two items in the list and try to use #add on them.  Say the
first is a gaussian RV and the second is a log random variable.  The
definition of the method add can&apos;t deal with this--it will try to hand
the log random variable&apos;s state to the internals of the gaussian RV,
which has no idea how to deal with it.

HOWEVER, if we throw away the binary methods, we can in fact put a
collection of &quot;float random_variable&quot; objects in a list.  Here&apos;s some
output from an ocaml session:

# let a = new RandomVariables.gaussian 0.0 1.0;;
val a : RandomVariables.gaussian = &lt;obj&gt;
# let b = (a :&gt; RandomVariables.float_random_variable);;
This expression cannot be coerced to type
{ lots of error stuff, which boils down to &quot;can&apos;t get rid of that method&quot; }
# let c = (a :&gt; float RandomVariables.random_variable);;
val c : float RandomVariables.random_variable = &lt;obj&gt;

As you can see, casting to float_random_variable didn&apos;t work, but
casting to float random_variable worked just fine.  The system is
preventing us from doing something unsound: using a bunch of mixed
float_random_variables together in a way that wouldn&apos;t work (because
we can&apos;t add them together).  But when we mix them in a way that will
work (we&apos;ll only make instances of them), all is well.


The kinds of things that are problemmatic in this system are far
different from the kinds of things that are tricky in traditional OO
systems.  But with some experience, you can see how the system is
amazingly powerful.  I suggest reading not only the section of the
manual on friends, but all of Chapter 3 (Objects in Caml) and Chapter
5 (Advanced examples with classes and modules).

And feel free to ask about suggestions about how to structure your
system.  From the looks of your code, I have some ideas about where
you might be going, and about designs that might work better in a few
places.  If you do ask, make sure to describe your problem in terms of
what you want to do, rather than how you want to do it.  (i.e. &quot;I want
to be able to add arbitrary random variables together&quot;, not &quot;I want to
be able to get run-time type information on my random variables so
that I can find the code to add them together in the right way.&quot;)
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>a generic print (ugly hack)</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200410/msg00155.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Yoann Padioleau announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
the goal is to allow the programmer to write in his program for instance:

 let _ = print_string (generic_print [[1;3];[2;9;8];[3;4]] &quot;int list list&quot;) in
 ...
 let _ = print_string (generic_print [1;3;2;9;8;3;4] &quot;int list&quot;) in
 let v = ... (* big computation, big data structure *)
 let _ = print_string (generic_print v &quot;(int * float * color) assoc&quot;) in
 ...


and to get on stdout:
 [[1; 3]; [2; 9; 8]; [3; 4]]
 [1; 3; 2; 9; 8; 3; 4]
 [(1, 2.02, Red); (2, 4.02, Yellow)];


the type of generic_print is
 &apos;a -&gt; string -&gt; string

code:
 http://www.irisa.fr/prive/padiolea/hacks/generic_print.ml

the principle is that the toplevel of O&apos;Caml know how to print value,
so by &quot;reusing&quot; the toplevel, our program can too.


It is slow, ugly, not robust,  but it can be helpful.
any suggestion or critics are welcome.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Nicolas Cannasse asked and Yoann Padioleau answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I was thinking doing the same some times ago, but without relying on
&gt; toplevel (which stucks you to bytecode).

I am not stuck to bytecode.
the main program can be compiled  to native code.


I can also do:
  ocamlopt unix.cmxa str.cmxa  generic_print.ml -o test_generic
  ocamlmktop -o calc.top unix.cma str.cma  generic_print.ml


&gt; The idea was to be able to load CMI at runtime, and extract type
&gt; informations from it in order to correctly print and match types (this is
&gt; already what&apos;s doing ODLL with functions). It&apos;s quite a work and I didn&apos;t
&gt; finished it. CMI contains *exact* types informations which are not present
&gt; at runtime, but not structured in a convenient way for printing or matching
&gt; since they&apos;re directly dumped from the compiler type representation. But
&gt; once done, this would include some dynamism that ocaml lacks when
&gt; interacting with outter world (serialization for example).

I&apos;ve coded too in a more cleaner way a trick to achieve the same kind of
result (a generic print) by relying on camlp4.
I auto-generate string_of_....   function for each type (by doing an induction
over the AST of the type definition via  camlp4).
It was cleaner.
But i tend to prefer this uglier version :)
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>ML Workshop Proposal:  request for assistance</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200410/msg00178.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Matthias Blume asked</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Dear fellow ML-ers,

as far as I can tell, the last ML workshop was held with ICFP&apos;98.
Therefore, I think it is high time for a restart of this valuable
tradition.

I am planning to submit a proposal for an ML workshop to Patricia
Johann, the ICFP&apos;05 Workshop Chair.  But for this I need your help!

Information on the proposal process can be found on this web page:

   http://www.brics.dk/~danvy/icfp05/call-for-workshops.html

As you can see, the deadline for proposals is coming up very soon
(November 1st), so we need to act quickly.

In order of importance, I would like each of you to take a few minutes
and respond to the following questions:

   1.  Would you be interested in attending a new ML workshop, to be
       held in conjuction with ICFP&apos;05 in Tallin, Estonia?

   2.  Would you be willing to help organizing the event?  (I am
       willing to do my part, but I could use a few experienced &quot;old
       hands&quot;.)

   3.  Would you be willing to serve on the program committee (should
       you be asked).

   4.  Among researchers and students you know and who were not
       reached by this communication, how many do you think would be
       interested in attending?  (We need a reasonable estimate on the
       total numer of attendees.)

   5.  If anyone could help me out with details on publicity and
       potentially published proceedings, I&apos;d be very grateful.

   6.  If you notice that I missed someone who should have received
       this request but didn&apos;t, please forward it!  Thanks!

Given the short time frame, please don&apos;t delay your reply!

Many thanks in advance, and let&apos;s hope we all meet in Tallin (and not
just for
ICFP)!

Best regards,
Matthias Blume
blume@tti-c.org

------------------------

Draft statement of goals, shamelessly stolen from the &apos;98 workshop (If
you have suggestions for changes and improvements, please speak up!):

  The ML family of programming languages, whose dialects include
  Classic ML, Standard ML, Caml, and Objective Caml, has inspired a
  tremendous amount of language research, ranging from type inference
  to module systems to operational semantics to implementation. In
  large part ML typifies &quot;HOT&quot; (Higher-Order, Typed) language design
  and implementation.


Draft CfP (again, for the most part shamelessly stolen; request for
suggestions -- see above):

  We seek papers relevant to all ML-related topics including (but not
  limited to):

   * applications
   * extensions: objects, classes, concurrency, etc.
   * two-level language designs (Meta-ML, MetaOCaml, etc.)
   * type systems: inference, modules, specification,
     error reporting, etc.
   * implementation: compilers, interpreters, partial
     evaluators, garbage collectors, etc.
   * environments: libraries, tools, editors, debuggers, etc.
   * semantics

  Submitted papers should describe new ideas, experimental results, or
  informed positions regarding proposals for next-generation ML
  languages.  In order to encourage lively discussion, submitted
  papers may describe work in progress.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Announcing OMake 0.9.3</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Aleksey Nogin announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
The OMake team is proud to announce a new release of the OMake Build
System - OMake 0.9.3.

OMake is a build system, similar to GNU make, but with many additional
features:

   o Support for large projects spanning several directories or
     directory hierarchies.

   o Comes with a default configuration file providing support for
     OCaml, C and LaTeX projects, or a mixture thereof.
     Often, a configuration file is as simple as a single line

        OCamlProgram(prog, foo bar baz)

     which states that the program &quot;prog&quot; is built from the files
     foo.ml, bar.ml, and baz.ml.

   o Fast, reliable, automated dependency analysis using MD5 digests.

   o Portability: omake provides a uniform interface on Win32 and
     on Unix systems including Linux and Mac OS X.

   o Builtin functions that provide the most common features of programs
     like grep, sed, and awk.  These are especially useful on Win32.

   o Full native support for rules that build several things at once
     (such as ocamlopt building .cmx and .o).

   o Active filesystem monitoring, where the build automatically
     restarts whenever you modify a source file.  This can be very
     useful during the edit/compile cycle.

   o A companion command interpreter, osh, that can be used
     interactively.

The home site for OMake is http://omake.metaprl.org/

The changes in 0.9.3 include:

   - OMake now supports ocamlfind in its default configuration file
    (thanks to Bardur Arantsson for the initial patch).

   - OMake should now also work with OCaml 3.07 (in addition to 3.08).

   - A large number of bug fixes, including:
      - OMake should now compile correctly under Cygwin (thanks to
        Peter Jolly who provided the patch),
      - &quot;double-colon&quot; rules (that allow specifying multiple rules for
        the same target) should now work correctly,
      - kqueue-based file system monitoring (Mac OS X, FreeBSD) should
        now work correctly
      - array definitions should now work better.

   - Added a work around for the command line length limitation of
     lib.exe on Windows

   - Filesystem monitoring functionality now provides a choice whether

     to continue monitoring once the project is built successfully.

OMake 0.9.3 is still an alpha release.  While we have made an effort to
ensure that it is bug-free, it is possible some functions may not behave
as you would expect.  Please report any comments and/or bugs to the
mailing list omake@metaprl.org and/or at http://metaprl.org/bugzilla

OMake is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License.
OMake configuration files are distributed under the terms of an MIT-like
license. OMake sources, as well as a number of Linux and Windows
binaries are available from the OMake home page at http://omake.metaprl.org/
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Current status of wxCaml</cwn_title>
    <cwn_who>Cameron Zemek asked and SooHyoung Oh answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I am still looking into Ocaml, but if I start to use it I am very
&gt; interested in using wxWidgets. I was thinking it would be good idea to
&gt; start an open source project on sourceforge (wxcaml.sf.net).
&gt;
&gt; How much of wxWidgets does your binding support?
&gt;
&gt; Have you though of using SWIG?

Thank you for your interest to wxCaml.

Before making it as an open source project,
I think more revision is necessary because it&apos;s only starting point of ocaml
binding to wxWindows.

The state of the wxCaml is that there are lots of binding to wxWindow
functions (widgets).
&quot;wc *.idl&quot; shows that it has about 5700 lines (including some commented
lines),
and &quot;wc wxcaml.ml&quot; shows it has about 9000 lines.
It means that it has many interfaces to wxWindow functions, almost to all
basic widgets.
You can find which widgets has binding or not by checking the &quot;wxcaml.ml&quot;
file.

As you know, lablgtk team makes very good modules and classes
for ocaml binding of another widget library.
I think the wxCaml project should follow the same direction as lablgtk

Before following wxhaskell method,
I tested &quot;SWIG&quot;  but it didn&apos;t give me good impression.
I remember it produced dull interfaces.

Right now, I don&apos;t have enough time to proceed with wxCaml project,
so I welcome anyone who wants to continue this project.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
</cwn_body>
</cwn>
