<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?>
<cwn>
<cwn_head>
  <cwn_date>2005.02.22</cwn_date>
  <cwn_prev>2005.02.15</cwn_prev>
  <cwn_next>2005.03.01</cwn_next>
  <cwn_date_text>15 to 22 February, 2005</cwn_date_text>
</cwn_head>
<cwn_body>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Polymorphic variant typing</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00416.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Gilles Dubochet asked and Jacques Garrigue answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; The following O&apos;Caml expression:
&gt; let incr g x = match x with
&gt; 	| `Int i -&gt; `Int (i+1)
&gt; 	| x -&gt; (g x);;
&gt; 
&gt; Receives type:
&gt; (([&gt; `Int of int ] as &apos;a) -&gt; ([&gt; `Int of int ] as &apos;b)) -&gt; &apos;a -&gt; &apos;b
&gt; 
&gt; Why? I am quite astonished. I would have expected a type more like:
&gt; ([&gt; ] -&gt; [&gt; ]) -&gt; [&gt; `Int of int ] -&gt; [&gt; `Int of int ]
&gt; 
&gt; or in Wand or Rémy-like row variable notation with which I am a little 
&gt; more comfortable (I am not exactly sure the preceding type is correct 
&gt; in the &apos;at leat - at most&apos; notation of O&apos;Caml):
&gt; ([ &apos;a ] -&gt; [ &apos;b ]) -&gt; [ `Int of int | &apos;a ] -&gt; [ `Int of int | &apos;b ]

The reason is simple enough: variants in ocaml are not based on Remy&apos;s
rows, but on a type system with kinded variables, more in Ohori&apos;s style.
This is described in detail in &quot;Simple type inference for structural
polymorphism&quot;, which you can find at
  http://wwwfun.kurims.kyoto-u.ac.jp/~garrigue/papers/

The main reason for this choice is avoiding making rows explicit,
i.e. having a multi-sorted type algebra. Note also that ocaml object
types, while originally based on Remy&apos;s system, are hiding their
row-variables, and can be described in the same formalism.

&gt; Could anyone be kind enough to give me some clues about where to look 
&gt; at to find an explanation or even better, explain me what is going on? 
&gt; I am particularly puzzled by the fact that the g function&apos;s *argument* 
&gt; type is &apos;at least `Int of int&apos;. This rejects the following code which 
&gt; seems intuitively correct:
&gt; incr (function `Float f -&gt; `Float (f+.1.));;

Pragmatic reasons for this choice are given in Section 3 of
  &quot;Typing deep pattern-matching in presence of polymorphic variants&quot;
which you can find at the same place.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Gilles Dubochet then asked and Jacques Garrigue answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Just to make it crystal clear for me: You say that the &quot;main reason for 
&gt; this choice is avoiding making rows explicit&quot;, does this mean that the 
&gt; O&apos;Caml team feels that row-based type information is too complicated 
&gt; for an average user since you either steer away of hide it in an object 
&gt; model?

Basically yes. Hence the clever tricks to have types containing hidden
row variables, like #t, [&lt; t], [&gt; t]. Having explicit row variables
was considered at some point, but it was not done because types would
become much more verbose. Consider for instance that with variants,
presence/absence information is needed for each tag.

On the other hand, advanced features like explicit polymorphism require
some understanding of the presence of hidden variables, and how they
interact, so at that level of proficiency it&apos;s not clear whether
hiding them really helps. And I&apos;m now playing with abstract rows,
which makes the decision even less clear...
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>interprocess mutex</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00435.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Janne Hellsten asked</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I need to sequentialize two processes accessing the same GDBM database 
(OCaml&apos;s dbm library).  Since GDBM allows for only one writer at a time, 
I need a way to block until the previous writer has finished.  I think 
there is a way to do this with the original GDBM library since it claims 
to handle the file lockings properly -- I could block based on the 
returned error codes.  However, this functionality does not appear to be 
exposed through the Dbm module.

Of course I can implement this blocking myself with an interprocess 
mutex.  But how can I implement such a mutex in OCaml?  I couldn&apos;t find 
anything from the standard library that would resemble my problem.

Is it easily doable or do I need to go and start hacking C code?  I&apos;ve 
never done it on Unix but I know it&apos;s easily done on Windows.

Thanks in advance,
Janne

P.S.  I&apos;m using GDBM merely as a cache between process invocations, so 
using a more heavyweight DB is out of the question.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Alex Baretta answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
Unix.lockf is the way to go.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Janne Hellsten then replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
OK, this is what I came up with (uses ExtLib&apos;s Std.finally):

---
let create_lock name =
  let chnl = open_out name in
  output_string chnl &quot;Lockfile - don&apos;t delete&quot;;
  close_out chnl

let with_write_block name f =
  if not (Sys.file_exists name) then
    create_lock name;
  let fd = Unix.openfile name [Unix.O_RDWR] 0o660 in
  Std.finally
    (fun () -&gt; Unix.close fd)
    (fun _ -&gt;
       Unix.lockf fd Unix.F_LOCK 0;
       f ()) ()

let test =
  with_write_block &quot;lock_name&quot; (fun () -&gt; Printf.printf &quot;this code 
blocks if other process already acquired lock!&quot;)
---

I hope I&apos;m using lockf correctly.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>XQuery Implementation: Galax version 0.5.0 available</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00442.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Mary Fernandez announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
We are proud to announce version 0.5.0 of Galax, an open source
implementation of XQuery 1.0.

This version implements the October 2004 XQuery working drafts and
includes a completely redesigned compiler with an algebraic optimizer,
a more efficient XML parser, and numerous bug fixes.

Galax 0.5.0 can be downloaded from the Galax Web site at:

   http://www.galaxquery.org/

In addition to the Galax source, pre-compiled binaries are available
for Linux, MacOS, Solaris, and Windows with MinGW.

Galax provides APIs for O&apos;Caml, C, and Java and is implemented in
O&apos;Caml.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Safe marshall?</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00439.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Mike Hamburg asked and Gerd Stolpmann answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Is there any way to call Marshall in a type-safe way?  I need to use
&gt; marshaling for a networking program, and I&apos;d rather not leave Marshal
&gt; as an arbitrary code execution vulnerability (which it is as far as I
&gt; can tell: switching on a Marshaled value should produce a computed
&gt; jump, which can be set by an attacker to point to an arbitrary place).
&gt;  Am I stuck writing my own marshal function?

Marshal is not type-safe, no chance. I see three options for you:

- If it is a closed protocol, you can sign the marshaled values

- You can use other serializers. A quite simple and fast serializer is the
  XDR encoder in my SunRPC implementation (see
  http://ocaml-programming.de/programming/rpc.html). Other options
  I know are BER (see ocamldap), XML-RPC, SOAP, and Ensemble.

- Write the serializer yourself. Maybe this is an option for you
  if you need maximum performance.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Oliver Bandel then asked and Gerd Stolpmann answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Well.. is there already an XDR-binding for OCaml?

Yes, as already pointed out, it is part of my SunRPC implementation:
http://ocaml-programming.de/programming/rpc.html . It is not a binding,
however, but a pure O&apos;Caml implementation.

It is quite easy and obvious how to use the XDR part alone without
the rest of RPC. For example, to define a record with an integer
and a string of maximum 20 characters:

open Xdr
open Rtypes
let my_type_term =
  X_struct [ &quot;my_int&quot;, X_int;
             &quot;my_string&quot;, (X_string (uint4_of_int 20)) ]
let my_type = validate_xdt_type_term my_type_term

Now, to encode a value:

let my_val =
  XV_struct [ &quot;my_int&quot;, (XV_int (int4_of_int 42));
              &quot;my_string&quot;, (XV_string &quot;Sample&quot;) ]
let my_val_as_wire_string =
  pack_xdr_value_as_string my_val my_type []

my_val_as_wire_string can now be sent over the network. For
decoding, use:

let my_val_again =
  unpack_xdr_value my_val_as_wire_string my_type []

If the string is illegal (e.g. my_string is longer than
20 characters), exceptions will be thrown.

One can also use ocamlrpcgen to generate parts of the above
code, including automatic conversion between XDR and the
corresponding O&apos;Caml types (e.g. an XDR struct is converted
to an O&apos;Caml record type). For complex protocols, the overhead
of learning ocamlrpcgen is worth the effort.

One should also consider using RPC directly rather than to invent
a new networking layer.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>New book: Objective CAML for Scientists</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00475.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Jon Harrop announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
We&apos;ve just published our first book on OCaml!

http://www.ffconsultancy.com/products/ocaml_for_scientists

Let me know what you think. :-)
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Estimating the size of the ocaml community</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00485.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Continuing last week&apos;s thread, Jon Harrop said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I was just reading this presentation and stumbled upon some figures it 
contains of the number of freshmeat projects written in different languages:

http://www.uclan.ac.uk/facs/destech/gradschool/autumnschool/thu11built-karlin2.pdf

According to this, just over a year ago (09/2003), OCaml was the 31st most 
popular language with 22 projects.

Checking freshmeat now, OCaml is the 24th most popular language with 52 
projects. Here&apos;s the full {language, projects} list:

{{C, 7066}, {Java, 3769}, {C++, 3523}, {Perl, 3300}, {PHP, 2947}, {Python, 
    1763}, {Unix Shell, 721}, {Tcl, 421}, {JavaScript, 409}, {SQL, 
    405}, {Objective C, 260}, {Other, 221}, {Assembly, 220}, {Ruby, 219}, {C#,
     155}, {Other Scripting Engines, 125}, {Scheme, 111}, {Lisp, 81}, {PL/SQL,
     78}, {Delphi, 74}, {Fortran, 62}, {Ada, 56}, {Common Lisp, 54}, {OCaml, 
    52}, {Emacs-Lisp, 51}, {Pascal, 48}, {Haskell, 48}, {Awk, 46}, {Zope, 
    41}, {Smalltalk, 33}, {ASP, 33}, {Visual Basic, 31}, {Basic, 30}, {Eiffel,
     28}, {ML, 27}, {YACC, 24}, {Forth, 23}, {Cold Fusion, 
    20}, {Object Pascal, 19}, {Prolog, 18}, {Erlang, 18}, {Pike, 11}, {Lua, 
    11}, {Rexx, 10}, {Modula, 9}, {Groovy, 5}, {Logo, 4}, {Euphoria, 4}, {APL,
     3}, {PROGRESS, 2}, {Pliant, 2}, {Dylan, 2}, {XBasic, 1}, {Simula, 
    1}, {REALbasic, 1}, {Euler, 1}}

I also computed the fractional increase in the number of projects for each 
language to determine how rapidly languages have been adopted over the past 
year. C# is 1st and OCaml is 2nd:

{{C#, 3.44444}, {OCaml, 2.36364}, {Objective C, 1.91176}, {Common Lisp, 
    1.86207}, {JavaScript, 1.74043}, {Haskell, 1.71429}, {Ruby, 
    1.71094}, {Java, 1.57304}, {Emacs-Lisp, 1.54545}, {Delphi, 1.48}, {Ada, 
    1.47368}, {Python, 1.47162}, {PHP, 1.43058}, {C++, 1.41999}, {Scheme, 
    1.40506}, {SQL, 1.38225}, {Fortran, 1.37778}, {Unix Shell, 
    1.30144}, {Other Scripting Engines, {}}, {PL/SQL, 1.27869}, {C, 
    1.28077}, {ASP, 1.26923}, {Pascal, 1.26316}, {Assembly, 1.24294}, {Lisp, 
    1.22727}, {Zope, 1.20588}, {Perl, 1.19392}, {Tcl, 1.17927}, {Awk, 
    1.15}, {Other, 0.840304}}

Considering that C# is pushed by Microsoft, Objective C is pushed by Apple and 
LISP is pushed by Thomas Fischbacher ;-), I think this is very impressive.

I&apos;ve also checked the number of unique posters to caml-list per month, which 
has continued to rise exponentially since 1992, currently weighs in at 300 
and is set to hit 1,000 in the year 2008.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Diego Olivier Fernandez Pons said and Jon Harrop answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Part of the 27 ML projects are in fact Caml projects.

Indeed, the following twelve seem to be written in OCaml:

Unison, FFTW, MATHPLOT, WDialog, PXP, GeneWeb, SwiftSurf, FaCiLe, pxpvalidate, 
Camlserv, Lazy-L and JSON.

I just had a look at sourceforge, which has far more projects (14,325 C, 
14,813 C++ and 14,074 Java) by comparison, and the accredited language seems 
to be wrong much more often. Assuming that all of the 132 SML projects are 
actually in OCaml, this gives 155 projects OCaml, i.e. about two orders of 
magnitude less common that the most popular languages.

Also, I think that web searches for &quot;resume&quot; and &quot;CV&quot; are likely to be 
inaccurate. Searching for &quot;written in *&quot; seems more reasonable. This gives:

792,000 Java
636,000 C
424,000 Perl
312,000 C++
221,000 Python
92,900 C#
30,100 Ruby
20,300 Lisp
11,700 Scheme
5,240 ocaml
974 caml

Again, OCaml is about two orders of magnitude below the most popular 
languages.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo added</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
For FFTW, only a small part is written in O&apos;Caml, a program which generates
optimized C codelets for the FFT butterflys.

The vast majority of FFTW is written in C.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Online Programming Course for Beginners, in Ocaml (in french)</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00510.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Arthur Chargueraud announced</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I&apos;d like to announce the release of an Ocaml programming course.
It is designed for beginners, and does not require any knowledge
in programming at all. Anyone aged over 12 should be able
to complete the course on his own, and thus learn the fundamentals
of programming. For the time being, it is only available in french,
but it will be translated into english later on.

Table of contents :
   Chapitre 0  Introduction
   Chapitre 1  let, if, for
   Chapitre 2  float, int, ref
   Chapitre 3  function
   Chapitre 4  array, char, string
   Chapitre 5  bool, random
   Chapitre 6  while, rec
   Chapitre 7  expression
About 130 exercices are part of the tutorial.

As you may notice, the course currently only covers about the first half
of general programming concepts. I may cope with the second half in the 
future.


The tutorial is available as text version, as PDF or PS files (about 170 
pages),
but also through an online interactive version : one can test and submit
source code, that will be compiled and evaluated online.

Access the tutorial : http://www.france-ioi.org/cours_caml/index.php

Note : access is free to all, but if you want to submit code
       you will need to go through a quick registration.

The material is hosted by France-IOI, an organisation focused on the 
development
of algorithmics and programming for algorithmics in french speaking 
countries.

If you have specific questions, conctact me on : cours_caml@france-ioi.org
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
  <cwn_entry>
    <cwn_title>Need for a built in round_to_int function</cwn_title>
    <cwn_url>http://caml.inria.fr/archives/200502/msg00491.html</cwn_url>
    <cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo said</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
I am about to port some code from C to O&apos;caml. This code uses the 
C99 function :

    long int lrint (double d) ;

which performs rounding on the double and then converts that to
a long int.

In O&apos;caml the only option seems to be:

    let round_to_int f = int_of_float (f +. 0.5) ;;

The problem is that this code on i386 produces really slow code:

    804b385:    dd 44 98 fc        fldl   0xfffffffc(%eax,%ebx,4)
    804b389:    de c1              faddp  %st,%st(1)
    804b38b:    83 ec 08           sub    $0x8,%esp
    804b38e:    d9 7c 24 04        fnstcw 0x4(%esp)
    804b392:    66 8b 44 24 04     mov    0x4(%esp),%ax
    804b397:    b4 0c              mov    $0xc,%ah
    804b399:    66 89 44 24 00     mov    %ax,0x0(%esp)
    804b39e:    d9 6c 24 00        fldcw  0x0(%esp)
    804b3a2:    db 1c 24           fistpl (%esp)
    804b3a5:    8b 04 24           mov    (%esp),%eax
    804b3a8:    d9 6c 24 04        fldcw  0x4(%esp)
    804b3ac:    83 c4 08           add    $0x8,%esp

The killer here is the two fldcw (floating point load control word)
instructions, around the fistpl (which actually does the float to int 
conversion). Loading the FP control work causes a flush of the FPU
pipeline. In code with a lot of floating point code interspersed
with a round to int, there can be a significant slow down due to
the fldcw instructions.

The lrint function in C, replaces all the above with one fistpl
and a single mov instruction and leaves the floating point
control word intact. In C code that moved from:

    (int) floor (f + 0.5)

to
    lrintf (f)

I have seen an up to 4 fold increase in speed.

I&apos;ve looked at the code for the O&apos;Caml compiler and I think I 
know how to implement this, at least for x86 and PowerPC, the two
architectures I have access to. If I was to supply a patch would
it be accepted?


I know other suggestions like this one :

    http://sardes.inrialpes.fr/~aschmitt/cwn/2003.11.18.html#1

were not viewed favourably, but the addition of a single function
with an explicit behaviour is a far neater solution.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Robert Roessler answered and Erik de Castro Lopo replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I will preface this by a Slashdot-like &quot;IANANA&quot; (I Am Not A Numerical 
&gt; Analyst).

Nor am I. I don&apos;t play one in a TV show either.

&gt; The above approach is more or less what you expect if you (as a 
&gt; compiler code generator) a) want to do rounding following C/C++ 
&gt; standards (&quot;Truncate (toward 0)&quot;), and b) make no assumption regarding 
&gt; the state of the IEEE hardware rounding setting...

Yes.

&gt; You, on the other hand, are willing to make an assumption regarding 
&gt; the hardware rounding mode - [presumably] that it is set to the 
&gt; power-on default of &quot;Round to nearest, or to even if equidistant&quot;, 
 &gt; which may not be unreasonable - it just needs to be explicit that this 
&gt; *is* the assumption, and that you have a way of verifying (or at least 
&gt; reason to believe) that other software components in your app&apos;s 
&gt; environment are not invalidating this assumption.

From the lrint manpage on Linux:

    These functions round their argument  to  the  nearest  integer  value,
    using  the  current rounding direction.  If x is infinite or NaN, or if
    the rounded value is outside the range of the return type, the  numeric
    result  is unspecified.  A domain error may occur if the magnitude of x
    is too large.

I would suggest something similar for the proposed O&apos;Caml function.

&gt; The fact that the default hardware rounding mode does NOT match &quot;(int) 
&gt; floor (f + 0.5)&quot; should also be mentioned... the &quot;+ 0.5&quot; attempts to 
&gt; do what the hardware would call &quot;Round up (toward +infinity)&quot; 

Careful, that could very easily be confused with  the C functions ceil().

&gt; This could take the form of a compiler switch exactly like &quot;/QIfist&quot;, 

A compiler switch is significantly more complicated than my proposal
for a new built-in function with a well defined behaviour.

The compiler switch causes all int_to_float to behave like a round
instead of a truncate. My proposal allows a single file to have
both behaviours.

&gt; Of course, if something like this were to added to ocamlopt (for 
&gt; target architectures using IEEE floating point), code (an additional 
&gt; bytecode op?) emulating the same behavior could be added to the 
&gt; runtime to maintain consistency across the interpreted and native 
&gt; operating environments - or not.

I believe that the bytecode interpreter simply uses the definitions
supplied by ocamlopt. Once ocamlopt has this functionality there
is not much else required to allow the interpretter to use the same
functionality.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Robert Roessler replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; I would suggest something similar for the proposed O&apos;Caml function.

Exactly like the &quot;FIST[P]&quot; instruction without explicit control word 
saving, setting and restoring - which is believable, since according 
to your first post, your reference implementation is done this way.

&gt; &gt;The fact that the default hardware rounding mode does NOT match &quot;(int) 
&gt; &gt;floor (f + 0.5)&quot; should also be mentioned... the &quot;+ 0.5&quot; attempts to 
&gt; &gt;do what the hardware would call &quot;Round up (toward +infinity)&quot; 
&gt; 
&gt; 
&gt; Careful, that could very easily be confused with  the C functions ceil().

Umm, 2 of the IEEE hardware rounding modes *do* seem to match floor() 
and ceil()... it is probably not a coincidence. :)

&gt; &gt;This could take the form of a compiler switch exactly like &quot;/QIfist&quot;, 
&gt; 
&gt; 
&gt; A compiler switch is significantly more complicated than my proposal
&gt; for a new built-in function with a well defined behaviour.
&gt; 
&gt; The compiler switch causes all int_to_float to behave like a round
&gt; instead of a truncate. My proposal allows a single file to have
&gt; both behaviours.

Actually, emulating the VC7 &quot;/QIfist&quot; does NOT cause &quot;all int_to_float 
to behave like a round instead of a truncate&quot; - it does exactly what 
we are already talking about: do the int_of_float with a &quot;bare&quot; 
FIST[P], operating in whatever rounding mode the hardware is already 
in (presumably one we want and expect it to be in).

&gt; &gt;Of course, if something like this were to added to ocamlopt (for 
&gt; &gt;target architectures using IEEE floating point), code (an additional 
&gt; &gt;bytecode op?) emulating the same behavior could be added to the 
&gt; &gt;runtime to maintain consistency across the interpreted and native 
&gt; &gt;operating environments - or not.
&gt; 
&gt; 
&gt; I believe that the bytecode interpreter simply uses the definitions
&gt; supplied by ocamlopt. Once ocamlopt has this functionality there
&gt; is not much else required to allow the interpretter to use the same
&gt; functionality.

The bytecode interpreter has nothing to do with ocamlopt... in fact, 
the primitive for doing int_of_float is precisely

return Val_long((long) Double_val(f));

which will perform a &quot;truncate&quot; operation for the conversion, since 
that is what the C standard requires. :)
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; Actually, emulating the VC7 &quot;/QIfist&quot; does NOT cause &quot;all int_to_float 
&gt; to behave like a round instead of a truncate&quot; - it does exactly what 
&gt; we are already talking about: do the int_of_float with a &quot;bare&quot; 
&gt; FIST[P], operating in whatever rounding mode the hardware is already 
&gt; in (presumably one we want and expect it to be in).

Implementing your proposal, means that int_of_float will change
behaviour depending on a compiler flag. I think thats a bad
idea.

My proposal leaves int_of_float just as it is and defines a new
function:

    val round_to_int : float -&gt; int

which expand to a FISTPL instruction and one or two glue 
instructions.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo added to his original post</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
OK, I have a patch that seems to do the right thing on x86 and
PowerPC:

    http://www.mega-nerd.com/tmp/round_to_int.diff

I&apos;m not 100% happy with the mods to byterun/floats.c. In order to
use the C99 lrintf() function in caml_round_to_int() I had to
define _ISOC9X_SOURCE etc before including &lt;math.h&gt;. The real
solution (when using GCC) is to add -std=c99 to the command line.

Using the following test program:

    http://www.mega-nerd.com/tmp/round_to_int.ml

with the hacked ocamlopt compiler I&apos;m getting about a 3 times speed
improvement using round_to_int on a Pentium III. The speedup on P4
is supposed to be even more because of the P4&apos;s deeper pipeline.
On PowerPC, there is no speedup because PowerPC has two separate
instructions for float to int, one which rounds and one which 
truncates.

I&apos;d be interested in any comments from the official ocaml maintainers.
What are the chances of this going into the official distribution?

I also have access to a machine with a MIPS CPU. I don&apos;t know
MIPS assembler but I&apos;ll see what I can do.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Xavier Leroy answered</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; [ &quot;round float to int&quot; primitive ]
&gt; with the hacked ocamlopt compiler I&apos;m getting about a 3 times speed
&gt; improvement using round_to_int on a Pentium III. The speedup on P4
&gt; is supposed to be even more because of the P4&apos;s deeper pipeline.

On the other hand, according to the P4 optimization manuals, the P4 is
supposed to special-case this particular use of fnstcw / fldcw, so
perhaps the situation is no worse than on the P3.  At any rate:

&gt; I&apos;d be interested in any comments from the official ocaml maintainers.
&gt; What are the chances of this going into the official distribution?

Essentially zero :-(  Basically, this is a case where additional stuff is
introduced in the machine-independent parts of ocamlopt and in every
code generator just to work around the brain-dead x87 floating-point
instruction set.  Every other processor (as well as the SSE2 instr.set
on the P4) has a fast &quot;truncate float to int&quot; instruction, from which
an efficient &quot;round to nearest int&quot; is easy to obtain (truncate (x +. 0.5)).  

I spent a lot of time in the past trying to extract decent float
performance out of the x87 instruction set, under the strict
constraint that these performance hacks should be confined to the
x86-specific parts of ocamlopt.  Nowadays, I no longer care about
performance for x87: users who want good float performance should
simply use the x86-64 architecture (with SSE2 floats), it&apos;s cheaply
available from both AMD and Intel and works so much better for
floats...  At the extreme, I&apos;d rather do a x86+SSE2 port (for P4 and
P3M-class processors) than spend more time on x86+x87.
    </cwn_what>
    <cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo replied</cwn_who>
    <cwn_what>
&gt; On the other hand, according to the P4 optimization manuals, the P4 is
&gt; supposed to special-case this particular use of fnstcw / fldcw, so
&gt; perhaps the situation is no worse than on the P3.  

OK, I&apos;ve just tested this. On P4 the performance hit of fnstcw / fldcw 
is not as bad as it is with P3, but its still significant:

Using this test program (compiled with my hacked version of ocamlopt):

     http://www.mega-nerd.com/tmp/round_to_int.ml

On a 450MHz P3:

    Time int_of_float : 5.970000
    Time round_to_int : 2.360000

On a 2.8GHz P4:

    Time int_of_float : 0.420000
    Time round_to_int : 0.260000

&gt; Essentially zero :-(  Basically, this is a case where additional stuff is
&gt; introduced in the machine-independent parts of ocamlopt and in every
&gt; code generator just to work around the brain-dead x87 floating-point
&gt; instruction set.

Obviously it is your decision, but I think round_to_int is a common 
enough operation to warrant its own function. The ISO C Standards
committee thought so.

&gt; Every other processor (as well as the SSE2 instr.set

Quite honestly I think the value of SSE and SSE2 are over sold.
There are certain algorthims which simply can&apos;t be made to run
as fast on SSE/SSE2 as they run on the x87 FPU.

For instance, my audio sample rate converter:

    http://www.mega-nerd.com/SRC/

If I compile this on a P3 with gcc-3.4 using -mfpmath=sse -msse,
the highest quality (and hence slowest) converter runs 50% slower 
than the x87 FPU version. I have also tried re-writing the algorithm 
in hand optimised SSE code. The best I could get (I&apos;m not an assembler 
expert) was still 10% slower than the x87 FPU.

I have just now repeated my experiment by compiling SRC on a P4 
with -msse2 (-mfpmath=sse2 doesn&apos;t work), the converter runs 75% 
slower than the x87 FPU version.

&gt; I spent a lot of time in the past trying to extract decent float
&gt; performance out of the x87 instruction set,

&lt;snip&gt;

&gt; Nowadays, I no longer care about
&gt; performance for x87: users who want good float performance should
&gt; simply use the x86-64 architecture (with SSE2 floats), 

I&apos;d love to get my hands on one of these, but I really do doubt
that its performance will be much better than that of the P4. 
The main problem is that generating good SSE/SSE2 code from
a high level language is an order of magnitude more difficult
than generating code for the x87 FPU.
    </cwn_what>
  </cwn_entry>
</cwn_body>
</cwn>
