<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2006.07.18</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2006.07.11</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2006.08.01</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 11 to 18, 2006</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head>There won't be any CWN next week as I'll be in vacations without internet access.</cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Small comparison of OCaml web frameworks</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/3183236b87fd8376/dce9a6377df103bb#dce9a6377df103bb</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>David MENTRE announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I've started a short comparison of OCaml web frameworks for WDialog, 
Ex-Nunc, Ocsigen and mod_caml: 
  http://www.demexp.org/en/doku.php?id=web_client_development_framework#comparison_of_ocaml_frameworks
This page is a Wiki. Feel free to fix any error or omission you might 
see (please add a meaningful comment in that case), as I have not tested 
each framework (except WDialog). 

I'm also interested into other criteria of comparison you might see 
interesting.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Nicolas Cannasse added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I added both haXe (&lt;http://haxe.org&gt;) and Neko (&lt;http://nekovm.org&gt;) to the 
list of your web frameworks. 

Since the haXe compiler is written in OCaml, that might interest some 
people on this list as well. haXe is an high-level OO language with a 
modern type system (type inference, enums, ML polymorphism). It targets 
three platforms : 
  - it has a Javascript/AJAX code generator so you can use it to code 
the client side of your website. 
  - it has a Neko code generator that can be used with NekoVM to write 
the server side of your website : NekoVM is a small embeddable VM with a 
"mod" for Apache. 
  - it has a Flash/SWF generator so you can use haXe to develop Flash 
RIA and other applications. 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>2006 ICFP contest</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/aacf46db85aa53d4/9c7b1493b8680424#9c7b1493b8680424</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>William Lovas announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Just a heads up: registration opened about a week ago for the 2006 ICFP 
Programming Contest.  This year's contest is being organized by the POP 
group at Carnegie Mellon, and promises to be quite a bit different from 
previous years' competitions -- hopefully better :) 

The somewhat cryptic theme offered is "computational archaeolinguistics". 
O'Caml teams have traditionally made a strong showing in the past, though 
the coveted first and second prizes have eluded them in recent years. 
Maybe it's time for a triumphant return! 

The standard announcement follows below.  Stay tuned to icfpcontest.org for 
details as they develop. 

cheers, 
William 

--- 9th annual ICFP Programming Contest --- 

Language lovers: 

Registration is now open for the 9th Annual ICFP Programming Contest! 

    http://icfpcontest.org/ 

The contest, associated with the International Conference on 
Functional Programming, will be held on the weekend of July 21-24. The 
contest task will be released at noon EDT on Friday, and entries will 
be accepted until noon EDT on Monday. Registration is free and open to 
all. Teams may participate from any location, and may use any 
programming language(s). Last year, 360 participants formed 161 teams 
from 26 countries. 

Prize money totaling $1750 US will be awarded to help defray the costs 
of travel to the conference for the winners and for small cash prizes. 
In addition, the winners of the contest will receive bragging rights 
for the programming language of their choice. This makes the contest a 
popular avenue for demonstrating the superiority of a favorite 
language, or for exercising an experimental tool. 

Though the specifics are secret until the contest begins, we promise 
that this year's task will be very different from past competitions. 
The theme is "computational archaeolinguistics." 

Stay tuned for more information as the contest approaches! 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Request for expressions of interest in commercial Objective Caml support</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/a88478f699baaf83/14c3f70b16702677#14c3f70b16702677</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Fermin Reig announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This is a letter of introduction and a request of expressions of 
interest in commercial support for Objective Caml. 

xrnd is a technology research and systems development company. We 
provide a broad range of professional services including contract 
systems R&amp;D, high-level consulting, software development and training. 

We are currently investigating extending our use and support of 
Objective Caml to include commercial support for users of the system. 
This will provide a number of services: 

        - industrial strength proprietary software development 
          using Objective Caml 

        - training and proof of concept pathfinder projects 

        - long term supported Objective Caml distribution with 
          additional libraries and extended Windows support 

        - implementation and contribution of features such as improved 
          64 bit code generation, vectorization and Windows support 

        - crisis support for urgent bugs in custom code, distribution 
          or libraries 

We consider our relationship with INRIA and the greater community to 
be vital. Our contributions will have copyright assigned to INRIA 
where the Caml team would like to include the code in their 
distribution. While not every change will make it into the standard 
distribution in this manner, our distribution will differ only where 
necessary to provide requested features or pending changes to the 
standard version. We expect that this will include, for example, 
extended Windows support, which INRIA will not be pursuing. 

We would be grateful for serious expressions of interest by email to 
us directly so that we can gauge the practical market for this 
support, and are happy to answer initial inquiries off-list. 

We look forward to working with you. 

Regards, 
Fermin Reig, for the xrnd team. 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocaml, MacOSX and GUIs</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/ddda45c5396fac4d/5f05309086264336#5f05309086264336</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo asked and Xavier Leroy answered</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; For Mac, I notice that there is a pre-compiled Mac binaries for 
&gt; the compiler: 
&gt;     http://caml.inria.fr/distrib/ocaml-3.09/ocaml-3.09.0.dmg 
&gt; I presume that these are PowerPC binaries. Is that correct? 

Yes. 
&gt; Is there likely to be a version soon targetting the Intel CPU soon? 

The source distribution for 3.09.2 contains full support for MacOSX/Intel, 
including native-code generation.  There are still a few small 
ocamlopt bugs in this port, which I'm currently ironing out. 
&gt; So, on to GUIs. My GUI requirements are rather simple. In fact 
&gt; the lablTk libraries should do the trick. Has anyone actually 
&gt; done any Ocaml development with a lablTk GUI targeting all three 
&gt; platforms? If so, how did it work out? 

In the standard distribution, there's ocamlbrowser, which has a 
labltk-based GUI and works on all three platforms. 
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue said and Janne Hellsten answered</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Unfortunately, on MacOSX ocamlbrowser only works properly with the X11 
&gt; version of Tk (which is very easy to install.) 
&gt; I tried several times to make it work with the Aqua version, but was 
&gt; never completely successful. 

I tried compiling ocamlbrowser directly from GODI and it worked out of 
the box on my MacBook Pro.  AFAIK this was using the Aqua version -- 
at least it didn't launch X11 like all the other X11 apps do. 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>sqlite3 bindings</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/a745ca5acf6ffc4e/98a50c2109b00fcd#98a50c2109b00fcd</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Ted Kremenek announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
i think there are more than one available SQLite bindings for OCaml,   
including some that are just for versions of SQLite before the API   
was changed in version 3 and others engineered directly for SQLite3.   

I am using Báröur Árantsson's bindings that are available at: 

http://www.imada.sdu.dk/~bardur/personal/45-programs/ 

These particular OCaml bindings in many ways directly mirror the   
SQLite3 C API; they are not a DBI-like interfaces, but work well if   
you are familiar with SQLite3. 

I have modified the bindings slightly for my own needs by adding a   
few methods and fixing a few bugs (any fixes of which I plan to   
eventually contribute back to Bárður), but it works very well with   

the latest version of SQLite3.  I am using it just fine with version   
3.3.6 of SQLite.  I have successfully used it to create database   
files of several gigabytes (populated with marshaled OCaml objects   
using Sqlite3's blob type). 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml NAE releases cf-0.8 and iom-0.3</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/107d784e15e50746/dd7d1f25a8ddaeae#dd7d1f25a8ddaeae</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>j h woodyatt announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The OCaml Network Application Environment (NAE) released updates to   
the Core Foundation (Cf) and I/O Monad (Iom) library modules today.   
See the project page on SourceForge.Net for downloads. 

        &lt;http://sf.net/projects/ocnae&gt; 

The update to Cf is mostly bug fixes, but type names were changed   
almost everywhere to remove confusing "_t" suffixes.  Also, the   
[Cf_gadget] interface was significantly altered.  The update to Iom   
is completely overhauled (again, &lt;sigh/&gt;). 

===== OCaml NAE Core Foundation (cf) library ===== 

This distribution is the Objective Caml Network Application   
Environment (NAE) 
Core Foundation library, which is a collection of miscellaneous   
extensions to 
the Objective Caml standard library. 

Highlighted features include: 

- Functional streams and stream processors (extended). 
- Functional bootstrapped skew-binomial heap. 
- Functional red-black binary tree (associative array). 
- Functional sets based on red-black binary tree. 
- Functional real-time catenable deque. 
- Functional LL(x) parsing using state-exception monad. 
- Functional lazy deterministic finite automaton (DFA). 
- Functional lexical analyzer (using lazy DFA and monadic parser). 
- Functional substring list manipulation (message buffer chains). 
- Gregorian calendar date manipulation. 
- Standard time manipulation. 
- System time in Temps Atomique Internationale (TAI). 
- Unicode transcoding. 
- Extended socket interface (supports more options, and UDP w/ 
multicast). 
- Universal resource identifier (URI) manipulation. 
- I/O event multiplexing (with Unix.select). 

Note: see the ISSUES file for a list of open problems in this release. 

===== OCaml NAE Reactive I/O Monad (iom) library ===== 

This distribution is the Objective Caml Network Application   
Environment (NAE) 
Reactive I/O Monad library, which implements I/O monad functions   
designed to 
facilitate writing of concurrent, reactive, single-threaded network   
application 
services in a functional style. 

Note: see the ISSUES file for a list of open problems in this release. 

===== Required Components ===== 

This library requires the following external components: 

- Objective Caml (v3.09 or newer) 
- Findlib (tested with v1.0.4) 
- OCaml NAE Core Foundation (cf-0.8) 

Principal development was on Mac OS X 10.4 w/ XCode 2.3 using GCC   
4.0.  No 
other platforms were tested for interoperability. 

===== Changes in Cf-0.8 ===== 

Highlights of the changes: 

+ Fix bugs and remove warnings generated when compiling with OCaml   
3.09 series. 
+ Changed named of types to remove [_t] suffixes (that were never a   
good idea). 
+ Rewrote the gadget monad again, to permit input backtracking on the   

flow 
   resulting from evaluation. 
+ Minor changes to event polling to simplify interface. 
+ Modularity improvements to socket API. 
+ Update the hard-coded TAI-UTC leap second archive. 
+ Update copyrights and author email address. 
+ Minor improvements to lazy sequences and functional messages. 
+ Removed obsolete modules. 

--- [Makefile] 
     Use -warn-error A on debug builds. 

--- [Cf_deque] 
     Use recursive module instead of magic.  Add [to_list], [of_list]   

and 
     [of_seq] convenience functions. 

--- [Cf_rbtree] 
     Optimizations for better performance.  (Further optimizations   
are possible. 
     While these modules offer more adaptability than the standard   
OCaml library 
     data structures, they do not offer superior performance.  In   
some cases, 
     performance is a little better than the standard, but in most   
cases, the 
     standard library is runs faster.  This is particularly true for   
the binary 
     set operator functions.) 

--- [Cf_ip4_addr,Cf_ip6_addr] 
     Fixed an awful bug in the [compare] functions that caused the   
return value 
     to be mistyped. 

--- [Cf_tai64] 
     Update the hard-coded TAI-UTC leap second archive.  Add a   
comment describing 
     where to retrieve the data. 

--- [Cf_scan_parser] 
     Fix brokenness surfaced by OCaml 3.09 series. 

--- [Cf_gadget] 
     Re-engineered, again.  This time, the integrated state is   
dropped from the 
     monad, and the scheduler is no longer implemented in the   
imperative style. 
     As a result, evaluating the monad now produces a flow that permits 
     backtracking on the input. 

--- [Cf_state_gadget] 
     This is the old [Cf_gadget] from version 0.7, with some minor   
improvements. 

     Use [try... with] to catch only the [Queue.Empty] exceptions   
raised by the 
     calls to [Queue.take] in the scheduler itself.  All other   
exceptions are 
     passed through the flow produced by [Cf_gadget.eval]. 

     Added [abort] and [wirepair] monads.  Simplified by removing   
[fsimplex] 
     monad, and the [simplex_t] and [duplex_t] types. 

--- [Cf_machine] 
     Obsolescent.  Use the [start] and [next] classes in [Cf_gadget]   
instead. 

--- [Cf_message, Cf_seq] 
     Add [to_function] for convenience constructing [Scanf.scanbuf]   
objects. 
     The indirection is required to keep [Scanf] from having to be   
loaded if it 
     isn't used. 

--- [Cf_journal] 
     Add [`Notice] event level, and associated method in [agent]   
class.  Cleared 
     up some ambiguous language in the documentation. 

--- [Cf_nameinfo] 
     Interface was busted for all queries except with the default hints. 
     Refined interface to support narrowed queries. 

--- [Cf_poll] 
     Unified ['a state_t] and ['a file_state_t] into a single   
concrete variant 
     type and removed the polymorphism on the state variant in all   
the derived 
     event classes.  Event classes are now parameterized by event   
type alone. 

     Changed [time] class to be a repeating interval timer event. 

     Fixed [idle] so that events that reload themselves are not   
serviced until 
     the next cycle. 

--- [Cf_ipX_proto, Cf_xxx_socket] 
     Moved the definitions of the protocol modules into the   
[Cf_ipX_proto] 
     modules.  This will allow [Iom] to link with the core socket API   

without 
     also linking in all the convenience classes for synchronous I/O. 

--- [Cf_lexer] 
     Obsolete, therefore removed. 

--- Changed names of types to remove [_t] suffixes. 

     Module              Type names changed 
     ------              ------------------ 
     [Cf_journal]        [invalid_t], [fail_t], [error_t], [warn_t],   
[info_t], 
                         [debug_t], [basic_t], [enable_t], [level_t] 
     [Cf_seq]            [cell_t] 
     [Cf_flow]           [cell_t] 
     [Cf_gadget_t]       [work_t], [gate_t], [wire_t], [guard_t] 
     [Cf_lex]            [counter_t] 
     [Cf_socket]         [socktype_t], [domain_t], [protocol_t],   
[sockaddr_t], 
                         [sockopt_t], [tag_t], [address_t], [msg_flag_t] 
     [Cf_sock_common]    [address_t] 
     [Cf_ip4_addr]       [network_t] 
     [Cf_ip4_proto]      [tag_t], [address_t] 
     [Cf_ip6_proto]      [tag_t], [address_t], [mreq_t] 
     [Cf_uri]            [host_t], [server_t], [authority_t],   
[segment_t], 
                         [abs_path_v], [rel_path_v], [path_t],   
[absolute_t], 
                         [relative_t], [reference_t] [abs_special_t], 
                         [abs_special_hier_t] 

--- [t_cf] 
     Test Cf_scan_parser.scanfx "%!". 

===== Changes in Iom-0.3 ===== 

This release is yet another major overhaul.  The programming   
interfaces are 
all new again and coded from scratch-- this time with more extensive,   

but still 
far from exhaustive, testing and regression. 

Previous release were rough drafts, and this new one is every bit as   
much of a 
rough draft as those were, but I feel more confident than before that   

no major 
overhauls of this design will be required.  Minor design flaws may   
require 
corrections, and bugs are very likely to be exposed over time with   
usage, but 
future changes in the 0.xxx version sequence should be incremental,   
rather than 
total. 

All along, I have been aiming for a framework that appears to be as   
adaptable 
as the venerable STREAMS framework from Unix SVR4.  With this   
release, I feel 
like I have finally succeeded in that effort.  Only time will tell,   
however, if 
I am right. 

Highlights of the new design: 

+ Uses new stateless [Cf_gadget] module (from Cf-0.8) with state classes 
   instead of the old stateful [Cf_gadget] (from Cf-0.7). 
+ Conventions established for multiplexing communication between   
gadgets on 
   multiple wires, i.e. a [jack] is used for sending control and   
receiving 
   notification, and a [plug] is used for receiving control and sending 
   notification. 
+ Support for Unix pipes. 
+ Redesigned interface to TCP streams. 
+ Generalized support for simplex and duplex octet stream processsing   

layers, 
   e.g. framing discipline, packet multiplexing, etc. 

See t/t-relay.ml for an undocument example of how to use the new Iom   
modules. 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCamlTeX 0.6 release</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/34b934d0c45eac48/da37b02e483c6caa#da37b02e483c6caa</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Geoffrey Alan Washburn announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I just finished a new release of OCamlTeX, which fixes several bugs, 
provides much more useful error reporting, and significantly more 
documentation.  You can grab the latest using the darcs version control 
system by running 
     darcs get http://free-the-mallocs.com/repos/ocamltex 

For more information, check out 
&lt;http://free-the-mallocs.com/index.php?n=Software.OCamlTeX&gt;. 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
