<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
	<cwn_head>
		<cwn_date>2007.12.11</cwn_date>
		<cwn_prev>2007.12.04</cwn_prev>
		<cwn_next>2007.12.18</cwn_next>
		<cwn_date_text>December 04 to December 11, 2007</cwn_date_text>
	</cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>Job announcement -- Ocaml &amp; C hacker</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/a967497d00894c5f#0b2af984b97b1c2b</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Berke Durak announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Exalead is a French software editor based in central Paris and 
developing enterprise search solutions and a web search engine 
(http://exalead.fr/).  Our young teams include web, natural language, 
indexing, database and network specialists.  We count a good number of 
C hackers. 

We develop an important part of our software in Exascript, our 
extension of Java.  Currently, we are rewriting our compiler in Ocaml 
(it was originally written in C) and targeting the Java virtual 
machine (instead of our in-house virtual machine). 

To help with this task, Exalead is looking for a good hacker fluent in 
Ocaml and C.  Having some familiarity with Java and its virtual 
machine is a plus. 

We are looking for someone who: 

- has an excellent grasp of low-level systems programming in C, 
- has been hacking Ocaml for some time, 
- has an understanding of garbage-collected virtual machines, and the 
   way they interact with native code, 
- is familiar with compilation techniques, 
- and likes to work in small teams and without formal specifications. 

Tasks to be expected are as follows. 

- Participate in the development of the Exascript compiler in a small 
   team of two to four people. 
- Ensure that existing native C and C++ application-level code works 
   smoothly on the JVM. 
- Examine the code base to detect parts that can be difficult to port, 
   possibly by developing automated analysis tools. 
- Devise, run and interpret benchmarks, deduce possible optimizations 
   and implement them. 
- Adapt and rewrite the base libraries to run under the JVM, using 
   existing Java components if possible. 
- Adapt developer tools to work smoothly with Exascript (such as Emacs 
   modes or Eclipse plug-ins). 

This is a permanent position for a full-time job. 

If you are interested, write to berke.durak@exalead.com
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>The Caml vs. the Leopard</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/92e8f5867182417a#2c18da30c9a031bc</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Gordon Henriksen announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Good news for Mac users and early adopters! Ocaml versions in CVS now compile 
cleanly on Leopard with or without setenv MACOSX_DEPLOYMENT_TARGET 10.4. To 
get the code:

# HEAD branch
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@camlcvs.inria.fr:/caml co ocaml -d ocaml-3.11.x

# release310 branch
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@camlcvs.inria.fr:/caml co -r release310 ocaml -d ocaml-3.10.x

This isn't a release yet, so run at your own risk. Thanks for hacking that 
patch into shape, Xavier.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>Ocaml code for Okasaki's "Purely Functional Data Structures"</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/a374fa6c9d9a7917#842ac97335a24ec6</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Erik de Castro Lopo asked and Paolo Donadeo answered</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
&gt; I'm currently reading Okasaki's book and a bit of googling told me 
&gt; that Markus Mottl translated the code examples into Ocaml. 
&gt; Unfortunately the links to the code are all dead. Does anybody have 
&gt; this code somewhere or know where it might be available? 

Try here, it's the OCaml page of Markus Mottl: 
http://ocaml.info/home/ocaml_sources.html
			</cwn_what>
			<cwn_who>Ashish Agarwal then asked and Maxence Guesdon answered</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
&gt; How do items on the Hump get updated? Markus Mottl's libraries are obviously 
&gt; a valuable resource, but the Hump's information for at least a few of his 
&gt; libraries are out of date. Unfortunate for newbies who don't know about the 
&gt; above link. 

The better way to have the hump updated is to 
- send an email to hump@caml.inria.fr, 
- or announce new software or updates on the caml-list, so I can add it to 
or update the hump.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>Questions on replacing finalizers and memory footprints</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/818e4443c627d478#9e1988d25a4e0cb9</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Thomas Fischbacher asked and Richard Jones answered</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
&gt; Also, is there a simple way to implement a function (perhaps using 
&gt; Obj.magic) which will walk a (possibly circular) network of tuples, 
&gt; arrays, variadic entities and lists, and return the total number of 
&gt; bytes used up by that structure? I see that this should be possible 
&gt; in principle with the present implementation of the runtime if one 
&gt; could get some basic information about the internal type of an array. 

You might get some ideas by having a look at the ancient module 
(http://merjis.com/developers/ancient), specifically at how the C 
function _mark in ancient_c.c is implemented.  Also have a look at the 
implementation of the Marshal module in the OCaml sources which takes 
a slightly different approach. 

If you want to do this in pure OCaml, probably your best bet would be 
to just Marshal the structure and count how big it is.  It'll be slow 
of course.
			</cwn_what>
			<cwn_who>Thomas Fischbacher then said and Jon Harrop added</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
&gt; Actually, the situation that brought up this question is that I have a 
&gt; complicated internal data structure which will free 300 MB of RAM if I 
&gt; delete it, while serializing it produces a file of 94 MB only... 
&gt; So, I would like to have more clarity what is going on here, and which 
&gt; part of this data structure eats how much space. 

I had never though of measuring the size of a marshalled data structure. Turns 
out its representation of ints can be more concise than the code 
representation though: 

# String.length (Marshal.to_string (Array.make 1000000 0) []);; 
- : int = 1000025 
# String.length (Marshal.to_string (Array.make 1000000 123456789) []);; 
- : int = 5000025 
# String.length (Marshal.to_string (Array.make 1000000 max_int) []);; 
- : int = 9000025 

which is probably what you're observing. 

Marshalling also handles sharing but that seems to refer to DAGs in memory 
rather than hash consing: 

# String.length (Marshal.to_string (Array.make 1000000 0., Array.make 1000000 
0.) []);; 
- : int = 16000031
			</cwn_what>
			<cwn_who>Xavier Leroy answered the OP</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
&gt; Also, is there a simple way to implement a function (perhaps using 
&gt; Obj.magic) which will walk a (possibly circular) network of tuples, 
&gt; arrays, variadic entities and lists, and return the total number of 
&gt; bytes used up by that structure? I see that this should be possible 
&gt; in principle with the present implementation of the runtime if one 
&gt; could get some basic information about the internal type of an 
&gt; array. 

Jean-Christophe Filliâtre's "size" library does exactly this: 
       http://www.lri.fr/~filliatr/software.en.html
			</cwn_what>
			<cwn_who>Jean-Christophe Filliâtre then said</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Indeed. However, note that it uses internally a hash table to store 
blocks already considered (in order to correctly account for sharing), 
and thus it is potentially incorrect if the GC moves some blocks during 
the count, for instance during a resizing of the hash table (which 
triggers the GC). I don't know how to avoid this issue; any help is welcome.
			</cwn_what>
			<cwn_who>Berke Durak also replied</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
I once had more or less the same problem in the EDOS project with huge 
data structures. 

Filliâtre's size library was also growing too large a hashtable, 
so I decided to use something else. 

My solution was to marshal the data structure and then analyze the 
marshalled data by recomputing its type. 

You first write a TYPER module that represents the types in your 
marshalled data structure, then use the Analyzer module on your 
output. 

I was more interested in the size strings were taking in memory, 
but it should be easy to modify.  All the ugly parts (parsing the 
marshal format, and the combinators for describing the types) 
have been defined. 

https://protactinium.pps.jussieu.fr:12345/svn/edos/users/berke/dvhfz/analyze.ml
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>PLplot library bindings</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/b11096c05bce6a56#7da616bfabd6f76f</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Hezekiah M. Carty announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
I would like to announce the availability of some reasonably complete 
OCaml bindings for the PLplot data plotting library [1]. 

These are separate from previously announced PLplot bindings [2] - 
those used SWIG to generate the interface, while this set of bindings 
uses camlidl.  These bindings are also somewhat more complete. 

The code can be downloaded from: 
http://code.google.com/p/ocaml-plplot/ 

Requirements: 
- OCaml (tested with 3.10.0, should work on older versions?) 
- PLplot version 5.7.x or 5.8.x 
- camlidl 
- findlib 

The license is the same as PLplot (LGPLv2+). 

This code has been developed on a 32bit CentOS 5 system, using godi 
for the OCaml installation.  I would be happy to hear about any 
successes or failures on other systems. 

There is currently only one example included, which corresponds to 
example 11 on the PLplot website.  The PLplot documentation is a good 
reference as this binding is very close to the C library.  There are 
some OCaml specific items though, so feel free to ask if you have 
questions or problems. 

Enjoy! 

[1] - http://plplot.sourceforge.net/ 
[2] - http://vityok.org.ua/cgi-bin/odd.cgi/Ocaml-plplot
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>LablGL 1.03</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/34efc309ece49f80#853cdba29b09101a</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Since it seems that it contains some useful bug fixes, 
here is a new release of LablGL. 

The main changes are: 

2007-04-13: 
* add glPolygonOffset 
* fix Glut.createMenu 
* fix GlTex.gen_textures 

2006-07-29: 
* make LablGlut's callback window dependent 
* simplify glutInit 

You can find it at: 

  http://wwwfun.kurims.kyoto-u.ac.jp/soft/olabl/lablgl.html 

There is a (semi-)binary release for windows, with both Togl and Glut 
support, that can be used directly with the OCaml MSVC or mingw 
ports. ocamlopt is supported too, with the exception of Togl on mingw. 
(Read carefully the installation instructions, particularly for ocaml 
3.10)
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
	</cwn_body>
</cwn>