<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
	<cwn_head>
		<cwn_date>2008.12.16</cwn_date>
		<cwn_prev>2008.12.09</cwn_prev>
		<cwn_next>2008.12.30</cwn_next>
		<cwn_date_text>December 09 to 16, 2008</cwn_date_text>
		<cwn_extra_head>There won't be a CWN next week. Merry Christmas to all!</cwn_extra_head>
	</cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>OCaml version 3.11.0 released</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/ae440d7937df6eef#</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Xavier Leroy announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Binary distributions for Windows (MSVC and Mingw toolchains) are now
available from the usual place:

         http://caml.inria.fr/download.html
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>pa_monad 6.0</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/d3c6aacbfed3f44b#</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Jacques, Lydia and Oleg announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
pa_monad has been updated to work with Objective Caml 3.11.0.  Quite a 
lot of maintenance work has also been performed (including a renumbering 
of the versions to be less haphazard).  See 
http://www.cas.mcmaster.ca/~carette/pa_monad/index.html for details.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>daml - a CUDA binding</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/f7e8a8a537521f4c#</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Sashan Govender announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
I've uploaded some work on a CUDA binding to OCaml  that I've been
doing in my spare time over here
&lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/daml/&gt;. Here's a brief summary of
what you can do with it at the moment:

- allocate memory on a gpu
- deallocate that resource
- copy and integer array from OCaml onto the gpu
- execute a kernel function to process the data on the gpu
- copy the result back into the OCaml array.

There are a few example programs in the repository as well.

Pretty basic but gotta start somewhere and my time for free software is
limited.

Things to todo:
- Devise a strategy for minimizing copies from the host data structure
to the gpu.
- Expose more of the CUDA runtime API (this can for the most part be
done with camlidl)
- Expose the CUDA driver API.
- Write some more example progams.
- Tidy up the OMakefiles.

Any feedback appreciated.

There's a mailing list here daml-users@lists.forge.ocamlcore.org for
questions.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>SICSA Chairs, Lectureships and Research Fellowships at St Andrews</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/7b07fbeb8ad21ed4#</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Kevin Hammond</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
The School of Computer Science is about to advertise 2 chairs (full
professor), 1 lectureship (assistant professor) and 2 postdoctoral research
fellowships, with a closing date of 27th February 2009. The posts are
sponsored by SICSA (the Scottish Informatics and Computer Science Alliance).

http://www.cs.st-andrews.ac.uk/sicsa-ad

The chairs and lectureship are permanent, tenured positions.  The fellowships
are three-year positions.  There will be additional lectureships advertised in
the future.

Applications from good researchers welcomed.

I would be happy to answer general questions about the School, town etc., of
course.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
	</cwn_body>
</cwn>