<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
	<cwn_head>
		<cwn_date>2008.01.22</cwn_date>
		<cwn_prev>2008.01.15</cwn_prev>
		<cwn_next>2008.01.29</cwn_next>
		<cwn_date_text>January 15 to 22, 2008</cwn_date_text>
	</cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>Ledit 1.17</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/9fccb760c1cbfefd#49ed5d9140019075</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Daniel de Rauglaudre announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
I am happy to announce a new release of "ledit" : 1.17 

Ledit is a line editor, allowing to use interactive commands with 
control characters like in emacs. 

Main changes: 
  - Added binds for Home, End, Page Up, Page Down, Delete, Shift Home, 
    Shift End. See CHANGES file or ledit manual page when installed. 
  - Added option -t to display the sequences generated by the keys 
    (for debugging) 

Downloadable at: 
    http://pauillac.inria.fr/~ddr/ledit/
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>OCamlExc port on 3.10</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/2d193cc4e32bcbd7#0f7ea0a09220fe03</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Nicolas barnier announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
I've just finished "porting" the venerable OCamlExc to work with OCaml 3.10.0: 
mostly a few modified paths and vars in the Makefile and the translation of 
interface files using CamlTk with LablTk. 

I had also to add on a case-by-case basis some missing stdlib functions 
(actually just "fake" ones that has the same type and exceptions raising 
than the genuine 3.10.0 stdlib ones) because special versions of the old 
stdlib/*.ml files are copied in the OCamlExc distribution with the external 
primitive types specifically annotated. I could also have annotated the 
current stdlib files, but I just felt it was more work. 

The result seems to work quite well and would be much useful, however some 
"recent" features like module and signature inclusion (and objects as well) 
still lacks and prevent from using OCamlExc on larger softwares. 

So I was wondering if there is any current or recent projects (or interests) 
to resume OCamlExc development and complete the set of handled constructs, 
as I'm afraid I'll have neither the time nor the skills to do the job. 
I hope such a precious tool will be included in the official OCaml distribution 
one day... 

-- Nicolas 

P.S. : My packaging abilities are very poor as well, so I'll be glad to provide 
the modified OCamlExc files to anyone interested in building a (e.g.) .deb package.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>Another print anything module</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/8c98d2be2c0dc722#b4230771cc9a3a22</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>tmp123@menta.net announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Based in the implementation of ExtLib's Std.dump and the code of 
camlp4r, another module to "print/dump any value" has been implemented. 
Thanks to the original authors. 

The reason of the new version is to add two requirements need in my 
current project: 
1) A strong split of: the analisis of value structure; the map of this 
structure over the value; and the print (or usage) of the resulting 
mapped data. 
2) Allow the user to provide no information, some information or all 
information about field names and any other data that can not be 
obtained automatically from the value. 

Code uses camlp4r revised syntax, but as usual module can be used with 
any syntax. 

You can find the source, reference documentation and example at: 
http://www.geocities.com/tmp_456/dump/index.html 

Any comments, from "useless", "already done" to "improve ..." are welcome.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>GODI available for O'Caml 3.10.1</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/e828bd75c78ccf9b#6c54da6a6cb8a01c</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
the GODI distribution of OCaml is now officially available for OCaml 
version 3.10.1. This is the first official release for an OCaml version 
of the 3.10 series - due to the camlp4 transition we've waited quite 
long before doing so in order to give all developers a chance to port 
their code to the new camlp4 style. Unfortunately, this transition isn't 
complete yet, so not all packages of the 3.09 release are available for 
the 3.10 release (see list below). We encourage skilled users to help 
out. 

You can get this release by either upgrading an existing GODI 
installation, or by doing a fresh install. If upgrading, some special 
attention is required, however. 

A list of packages is available in the web, see the link on the GODI 
homepage: http://godi.ocaml-programming.de/index.html 

------------------------------------------------------------ 
Doing a fresh install of OCaml 3.10.1 with GODI 
------------------------------------------------------------ 

- Download the bootstrap tarball from 
  http://www.ocaml-programming.de/packages/godi-bootstrap-20080118.tar.gz 

  (This link is published on the GODI homepage.) 

- Extract the tarball: 
  tar xzf godi-bootstrap-20080118.tar.gz 

- Do the first stage of the bootstrap: 
  cd godi-bootstrap-20080118 
  ./bootstrap --prefix &lt;somedir&gt; 

  where &lt;somedir&gt; may be an arbitrary, not yet existing directory 
  (please _don't_ use /usr or /usr/local) 

- Add &lt;somedir&gt;/bin and &lt;somedir&gt;/sbin to PATH 
  PATH=&lt;somedir&gt;/bin:&lt;somedir&gt;/sbin:$PATH 
  export PATH 

- Do the second stage of the bootstrap: 
  ./bootstrap_stage2 

  For the second stage you need an Internet connection. 

- Run godi_console to install libraries and applications! 

Links for troubleshooting etc.: see below. 

------------------------------------------------------------ 
Upgrading an existing GODI installation to OCaml 3.10.1 
------------------------------------------------------------ 

Edit godi.conf. This file is usually installed as 
&lt;prefix&gt;/etc/godi.conf. Set GODI_SECTION to 3.10, e.g. 
change the line 

GODI_SECTION=3.09 

to 

GODI_SECTION=3.10 

Run godi_console, and "Update the list of packages". Then "Select source 
packages", and "upgrade all" with 'u'. Finally, type 's' to start the 
installation, and 'o' to commit this action. 

Note that you'll run into an error if you have some package installed 
that is not (yet) available for OCaml 3.10.1. The error is usually 
cryptic, but indicates a "Version conflict". 

If you select the packages to upgrade manually, make sure you always 
select godi-ocaml and godi-ocaml-src. Otherwise, the upgrade won't 
happen. 

------------------------------------------------------------ 
Packages not yet available 
------------------------------------------------------------ 

The following packages are not (yet) available: 

godi-col, godi-heredoc, godi-json-static, godi-micmatch_pcre, 
godi-pa_arg, godi-camlp4-manual, godi-galax, 
godi-ocamlduce, /godi-ocamlducebazar. 

The following packages have intentionally been deleted, because we have 
replacements: 

godi-equeue, godi-equeue-gtk1, godi-equeue-gtk2, godi-equeue-tcl, 
godi-netclient, godi-shell, godi-rpc, godi-wlex. 

------------------------------------------------------------ 
Resources 
------------------------------------------------------------ 

Documentation is available here: 

http://godi.ocaml-programming.de/doclinks.html 

On the right navigation bar on this page, you can also find links for 
the mailing list, the bug tracker, and the subversion repository.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
	</cwn_body>
</cwn>