<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
	<cwn_head>
		<cwn_date>2008.01.08</cwn_date>
		<cwn_prev>2008.01.01</cwn_prev>
		<cwn_next>2008.01.15</cwn_next>
		<cwn_date_text>January 01 to 08, 2008</cwn_date_text>
	</cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>Camlp5 release 5.07</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/b1f9d468c7953a62#f80db29ae370019c</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Daniel de Rauglaudre announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
New release of Camlp5 : 5.07 

Changes: 
 - Added function [Grammar.Entry.parse_all] returning the list of all 
   solutions when using the parsing algorithm [Backtracking]. 
 - Added "pprintf" statement to use the Camlp5 pretty print system more 
   easily and shortly. A chapter of the documentation describes it. 

Sources and documentation available at: 
   http://pauillac.inria.fr/~ddr/camlp5/
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>OCaml 3.10.1 release candidate 2</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/89a1b8929048e7d8#1834fd8c2f9e462e</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Damien, for the OCaml team, announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
I have the pleasure of announcing the second release candidate 
of OCaml 3.10.1. 

There are only two changes from RC1: 

1. The type-checking of recursive modules was too restrictive 
    in RC1 (and not restrictive enough in 3.10.0).  (PR#4470) 
2. There was a problem with the native port on HPPA. (PR#4339) 

As usual, this is a source-only version released for testing 
by power users and package managers. 

If you are using recursive modules, or if you are running OCaml 
on HPPA machines, please download and test this version.  If 
you haven't tested RC1 yet, please test RC2 instead. 

As usual, you should drop me &lt;damien.doligez@inria.fr&gt; a mail 
after testing, and tell me about any problem you had.  Don't forget 
to tell me also if all goes well. 
This release is available, as usual, at 
&lt;ftp://ftp.inria.fr/INRIA/cristal/ocaml/ocaml-3.10/ocaml-3.10.1+rc2.tar.bz2&gt;
&lt;ftp://ftp.inria.fr/INRIA/cristal/ocaml/ocaml-3.10/ocaml-3.10.1+rc2.tar.gz&gt;
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>patch for top level backtraces</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/240be27661ff5c05#3aca59d1ea232430</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Jake Donham announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Here is another backtrace patch that gives backtraces in the top level and 
for dynamically-loaded code. 

  http://skydeck.com/blog/programming/more-stack-traces-in-ocaml/
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>ExtLib 1.5.1 released</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/0d65e8674d5a4460#533d6bb7d3e4e9ee</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Janne Hellsten announced</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
The OCaml ExtLib developers are proud to announce the release of ExtLib 1.5.1. 

The release should be considered a minor bug fix release. Along with 
the new version, we also announce that the ExtLib project has moved to 
a new home at &lt;http://code.google.com/p/ocaml-extlib/&gt;. 

The release tarball can be downloaded from: 
http://code.google.com/p/ocaml-extlib/downloads/list 

GODI packages have already been upgraded to the latest version. Debian 
and Fedora package upgrades are expected to happen soon. 

See the project home page for more information.
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
			<cwn_title>An ocaml livecd</cwn_title>
			<cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_frm/thread/75e8b2ac37b33363#5c5d5e7430774535</cwn_url>
			<cwn_who>Adrien Nader said</cwn_who>
			<cwn_what>
Some time ago there was a discussion about the usefulness of an ocaml livecd. 
There is already Demolinux or Juppix but they both contain a lot of 
data (.iso weigh about 700MB) and Demolinux is really aging. 

So here is a test version for a new one. 
The goal of the livecd is not to have java, eclipse or apache, it is 
to provide a comfortable environment for ocaml but also general usage 
while consuming few resources. Hopefully it is easy to plug-in modules 
in the root filesystem whenever one wants (see 
http://slax.hosting4p.com/modules.php ). This modular approach is 
important as it reduces space usage (both on the cd and in memory) 
while keeping all the functionnalities. 

The base is slackware-current with linux-live scripts (1) and slax's 
kernel (2) as a mysterious problem prevents me from using my owns. 
The build process is pretty easy and reproductible by anybody within 
two hours. Feel free to ask if you want the small scripts I've written 
: one creates an iso from a subset of slackware-current, the other one 
removes some files and move some others in order to create modules for 
C development [headers and gcc data] and documentation. 

(1) : http://www.linux-live.org 
(2) : taken from slax6rc7 iso along with modules, 
http://merlin.fit.vutbr.cz/mirrors/slax/SLAX-6.x/rc7/ 

The result is a 147MB iso file with a graphical environment which can 
run on computers with 128MB of RAM. Right now this livecd features 
xfce, ocaml-3.10.1-rc1, ledit, ocamlfind, gvim (vi is elvis though), 
mousepad, gmplayer, pcmanfm (file-manager), emelfm (same), Thunar 
(same). It also features fftw2 which I wanted for myself and I'll be 
happy to include any other module one could want (I've forgotten 
lablgtk2 for example). 

Basic usage/advice is : 
- upon boot, use &lt;TAB&gt; to edit the command-line and use vga=0x315 for 
800x600 console display, vga=0x317 for 1024x768 and vga=0x31A for 
1280x1024. 
- log in as root (the filesystem is read-only), there is currently no password. 
- use the startx command for the gui (vesa 1024x768 by default, works 
for geforce go 7600, geforce 7600gt, radeon x300) and if you have a 
weird terminal, quit xfce, run xorgsetup and use a higher color depth. 
You may run xorgsetup anytime display is problematic in fact. 
- ocaml with ledit and unix.cma is the yellow helmet on the left 

There are already todo and fixme lists: 
fixme, most being immediate to fix: 
 * higher  default resolution for boot 
 * debug off for pcmanfm (its inotify debug is a real flood) 
 * /etc/group, I'm not sure of the proper syntax 
 * include the development and documentation modules (ocaml 
documentation is not concerned, it is always there) 
 * lablgtk 
 * wput 
 * network which is available but not activated by default. 

todo: 
 * emacs with tuareg is absent but only because I don't personnaly use 
and can't make it properly (I've already found the friend I'm going to 
work on this ;) ) 
 * ndiswrapper with stripped driverpacks ( 
http://driverpacks.net/DriverPacks/DriverPack.php?pag=l ) to support 
some wifi cards (as my bcm43xx for instance) 
 * drocaml but I would like to make it lighter otherwise it will have 
troubles running 
 * cameleon2 which surprinsingly doesn't compile on my computer 
 * improved bootscreen (but don't be afraid, there'll be no ugly gfx ;) ) 
 * copy2ram (copy data from cd or usb key to ram to improve performance) 

The iso file can be downloaded at 
http://ocaml.yaxm.org/files/llama/llama.iso and yes I really had no 
idea for the name. ;p 
Any feedback is highly appreciated. 

PS: Am I allowed to redistribute the oreilly book in pdf format ? 
What about the ocaml pdf by inria ?
			</cwn_what>
		</cwn_entry>
	</cwn_body>
</cwn>