<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2009.09.29</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2009.09.22</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2009.10.06</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>September 22 to 29, 2009</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Cache algorithms: implementation or library available?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/2f3207bee5591cc2#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hugo Ferreira asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I would like to know if anyone has or knows of an Ocaml
library or open-source code implementation of some cache
algorithms (example: least recently used).

Basically I need to cache a function that maps a list
of ordered integers into a value (float, integer). I
would like something that allows setting a maximum size
of the map and automatically discards the data.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Martin Jambon suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
There are so many possible access patterns and trade-offs:

- speed requirements?
- memory requirements?
- constant size or just bounded?
- is the probability of accessing an element a function of time?

I see two frequent use cases:

a.  some elements are accessed more frequently than others regardless of time
b.  recently-accessed elements have a higher probability of being accessed

Alain Frisch provides an implementation of roughly a hash table in which
buckets hold only one element, which looks great at least for case (a):

 http://alain.frisch.fr/soft.html#memo
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann also suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Maybe the Wink cache server is interesting for you:

http://oss.wink.com/cache/

It is an LRU cache with a maximum size, and entries can also expire by
time. If you are more looking for a local cache module, you can pick the
relevant parts out of the cache_server.ml implementation.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jan Kybic also suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I have written something similar some time ago. I am attaching the
code, maybe you will find it useful but beware that I have written it
just for my own purposes, so the code might be hard to read, there are
very little comments, you will probably have to modify it, and I do
not have time to provide support.

The idea is that as long as there is enough memory, the function
values are cached (memoized). When the memory gets tight, the
"cheapest" entries are forgotten. For this purpose, the function
evaluations are timed.

(Editor note: as the code is quite long, please follow this link to read it:
&lt;http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/msg/547c9d4a7a6f501f&gt;.)
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Dario Teixeira also suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The Ocsigen folks have also developed a caching module for Ocsimore.
It may be interesting to you if your app uses Lwt..  The module is
called 'Cache':  http://ocsigen.org/ocsimore/sources/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OC4MC : OCaml for Multicore architectures</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/19a97f2b6e9812c4#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Philippe Wang announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This is some additional "noise" about "OCaml for Multicore architectures" (or
"Ok with parallel threads GC").
----------------------------

Dear list,

We have implemented an alternative runtime library for OCaml, one that allows
threads to compute in parallel on different cores of now widespread CPUs.

This project will be presented at IFL 2009
(&lt;http://blogs.shu.edu/projects/IFL2009/&gt;).

A testing version available online at
http://www.algo-prog.info/ocmc/
It works with OCaml 3.10.2 for Linux x86-64bit, we haven't met any bugs with
the latest build (it doesn't *unexpectedly* crash, not yet).

Hope you'll enjoy,

--
Mathias Bourgoin, Adrien Jonquet, Emmanuel Chailloux, Benjamin Canou, Philippe
Wang
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>The editor says</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This announcement started a huge conversation. Next follow some additional
technical information and Xavier Leroy's position about this patch. If you
want to read the whole discussion, please follow the archive link above.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Philippe Wang later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
A few words on the GC's design (that uses stop&amp;copy algorithm several times) :

Heaps :
- a set of pages are used to give threads the possibility to allocate
memory without interfering with other threads, such as there is no
mutex locking at local memory allocation. Each thread borns with an
empty page, when it's full, the thread takes another one.
- a big heap is shared between all, there is a mutex over it to
prevent parallel memory allocation into this one.

Collection :
- when there are no pages left, a collection stops-the-world and
copies living values (of the pages) to the shared heap
- when the shared heap is full, a collection stops-the-world and
copies all living values (pages+shared heap) to a new shared heap
(which can be grow if need be)

Special operations :
- if there is a blocking operation (e.g. mutex lock or I/O operation),
the mechanism is roughly the same as original INRIA OCaml's : it tells
the GC that there is no need to stop it when stopping the world.
- if there is a thread with no allocation and no blocking operation,
the behaviur is the same as INRIA OCaml.

The number of pages, the size of a page, and the size of the shared
heap can be changed before running a program by setting some
environment variables (cf. last lines README file included in the
distribution package).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jon Harrop asked and Philippe Wang replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Are values such as float arrays copied in their entirety or are they allocated
&gt; outside the shared heap and only a pointer to them is copied?

They should be in a heap (page or shared). We don't allocate many
things outside the heaps.

&gt; Is the copy operation parallelized?

Nope. When the world is stopped for the collection, everything is done
sequentially until the world is resumed.
I don't think it's relevant to parallelize the copy operation (hell to
implement&amp;debug, then I don't think that performance would be very
interesting because we would probably need a write mutex on the
destination heap)

&gt; Is there a write barrier but no read barrier? If so, what exactly does the
&gt; write barrier do?

There is a lock when a thread is created because we need to update the
list of existing threads and we have to give it a page.
Then, each time a thread wants memory, it checks if the world needs to
be stopped. If the world needs to be stopped, it means that there is a
necessary collection waiting for the world to be stopped.
There is lock if a thread needs to allocate memory in the shared heap
so that two threads don't end up using the same space for different
things.
If two threads want to write in the same block, it's up to the
programmer to prevent (or allow) such a thing with a mutex (or
whatever other mechanism).

&gt;&gt; Special operations :
&gt;&gt; - if there is a blocking operation (e.g. mutex lock or I/O operation),
&gt;&gt; the mechanism is roughly the same as original INRIA OCaml's : it tells
&gt;&gt; the GC that there is no need to stop it when stopping the world.
&gt;
&gt; Can users mark external calls in their bindings as blocking so the GC will
&gt; treat them appropriately?

Yes, it's the same as INRIA OCaml : enter_blocking_operation /
leave_blocking_operation functions.
It's mandatory that in the section between entrance and exit, the
thread is not accessing anything allocated in a Caml heap.
If there is need to write some value returned by the blocking
operation, it should be written in a C side value (on C stack or with
C malloc) and put back to Caml heap after exit (and then C free if C
malloced).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Addressing the potential inclusion of the patch, Xavier Leroy said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
That would be suicidal.  I definitely do not want to belittle the work
of Philippe and his teammates -- what they did is an amazing hack
indeed --, but you need to keep in mind the difference between a
proof-of-concept experiment and a product.

In a proof-of-concept experiment, you implement the feature want to
experiment with and keep everything else as simple as possible
(otherwise there is little chance that you'll complete the
experiment).  That's exactly what Philippe et al did, and rightly so:
their GC is about the simplest you can think of, they didn't bother
adapting some features of the run-time system, they target AMD64/Unix
only, etc.  Now they have a platform they can experiment with and make
measurements on: mission accomplished.

In a product, you'd need something that is essentially a drop-off
replacement for today's OCaml and can run, say, Coq with at most a 10%
slowdown.  That's a long way to go (I'd say a couple of years of work).
For example, single-generation stop-and-copy GC is known to have
terrible performance (both in running time and in latency) for
programs that have large data sets and allocate intensively.  This is
true in the sequential case and even worse in a stop-the-world
parallel setting, by Amdahl's law.  Note that the programs I mentioned
above are exactly those that the Caml user community cares most about
-- not matrix multiply nor ray tracers, Harrop's propaganda
notwithstanding -- and those for which OCaml has been delivering
top-class performance for the last 12 years -- again, Harrop's
propaganda notwithstanding.

On your way to a product, you'd need to independently-collectable
generations (which means some work on the compiler as well), plus a
parallel or even better concurrent major collector.  And of course a
lot more work on the runtime system and C interface to make everything
truly reentrant while remaining portable.  And probably some kind of
two-level scheduler for threads.  And after all that work
you'd end up with an extremely low-level and unsafe parallel
programming model that you'd need to tame by developing clever
libraries that mere mortals can use effectively (Apple's Grand Central
was mentioned on this thread; it's a good example)...

In summary, Philippe and his coauthors do deserve a round of applause,
but please keep a cool head.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Benjamin Canou then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
One of our main goals for OC4MC is to serve as a parallel and shared memory
low-level concurrency implementation, on top of which higher level research
concurrency libraries and language extensions can be built. And as most of us
agree, multicores, and soon manycores, are hard to program, in particular
because of the memory bandwidth. So there probably are experiments to be done
to help this at the language level, now that we have this parallel runtime.
Moreover, and to answer a question that appeared in this thread, we provide
our simple GC, but we separated the GC algorithm from the runtime, so OC4MC is
also a low-level playground to experiment with your own GCs and choose the one
you want to use at linking.

To sum up, let's see OC4MC as an experimentation platform that leverages some
restrictions of OCaml, but of course neither as a drop-in replacement for the
official distribution nor as the future of OCaml. We do not claim that the
ideal solution to bring shared memory parallelism to OCaml is, as OC4MC does,
only to replace the runtime (and that INRIA can just replace the official
runtime by our hacked one). However, from a pragmatic (and optimistic) point
of view, the modifications to the compiler have been kept very lightweight,
yet sufficient to break binary compatibility. So if the excitement continues
around OC4MC as in this thread, maybe these modifications could be integrated
into the distribution since they really do not touch the core of the compiler
and cannot cause a lot of maintenance overhead.

I will add that we did not made this experiment to beat F# or python's
hashtables, so I will not comment on that here. The point about performance is
that it should be *predictable*. We now have rewritten and debugged most of
the memory related behaviors present in the original runtime in a more generic
(and OC4MC friendly) way to achieve this, and if it's not the case for some
particular cases, we'll be glad to (try to) fix these bugs.

On the maintenance side, as Philippe said, we already have some half working
version with ocaml 3.11.x, but partly because of the changes made to the
native runtime in this release and partly because of [1], porting the patch is
not trivial.

Cheers and have fun experimenting with OC4MC (so it will compensate the amount
of debugging we spent on it ;-) ).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New release 2.21 of htmlc</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/34b0b84f90bde6d8#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Pierre Weis announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Htmlc, a general purpose text file generator with a programmatic approach in
the spirit of functional programming. (&lt;http://htmlc.inria.fr/&gt;)

I am pleased to announce the 2.21 version of Htmlc, a convenient tool to
generate and manage text files of any kind, in particular computer programs
or documentation.

Htmlc can act as a fast general purpose preprocessor for all of your text
files. Being reliable and having a clean semantics, Htmlc always behaves as
expected and produces the results you wanted :)

As its name indicates, Htmlc greatly helps to create and modify a set of WEB
pages in order to maintain the common look of those pages and factorize the
repetive parts of their HTML code.

This version is a development and bug fix release and documentation has been
improved.

Htmlc expanses on the fly ``$id'' variables written in the source document:
the binding for $id could be written in the document or in an Htmlc
environment source file (and guess what ? the syntax to define id is
 ``let id = value;;'',
so that environment files for Htmlc are valid Caml implementation files :).

Htmlc let you define and then apply functions to produce new text or edit the
text source at hand. You can define the functions either directly in the text
being processed or in an external standalone file, loaded on request.  Try
"htmlc -print_env" to figure out the initial environment when processing
begins.

Htmlc allows the automatic insertion of the result of arbitrary Unix commands
into the generated pages.

Htmlc encourages the usage of simple HTML templates that lowerize the burden
of writing the HTML pages.

Htmlc is also very convenient to produce the final HTML page result of a CGI
program from static templates and execution environments created on the fly
by the CGI.

Htmlc is still evolving from its initial satus of SSI static resolver to the
plain HTML page compiler we are all dreaming of. So, please, don't hesitate
to send your constructive remarks and contributions !

Htmlc home page is http://htmlc.inria.fr/
Htmlc source files can also be uploaded via nonymous ftp at
ftp://ftp.inria.fr/INRIA/cristal/caml-light/bazar-ocaml/htmlc-2.21.0.tgz
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>LablGtk 2.14.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/5f98782de1d62af9#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Following a number of improvements in the repository, here is a new
release of LablGtk2, the ocaml interface to the Gtk+ GUI library and
friends (glade, rsvg, gnomecanvas, gnomedruid, panel, gtkspell,
gtksourceview2.)

This release is still based on the gtk+-2.12.x series, but the name is
updated so that we do not look lagging (gtk+ is already at 2.16.6...)
It will work with older versions too.

You can find it at:

 http://wwwfun.kurims.kyoto-u.ac.jp/soft/olabl/lablgtk.html

There is a (semi-)binary releases for windows, with glade, gnomecanvas
and rsvg support, that can be used directly with the OCaml MSVC or mingw
ports. ocamlopt is supported too.

The main change is the update to gtksourceview2, but there are many
smaller improvements too. For instance, we ship a patch that allows you
to build a working unison on top of the quartz version of gtk.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ebuild for OCaml Batteries included</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/746727291fc3ddca#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Ivan Chernetsky announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
If there are anyone interested in it, please go to
http://github.com/ichernetsky/gentoo-overlay
It is a result of quick and dirty attempt, but it's usable anyway.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>xpath or alternatives</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/48e05d49b0f21b8a#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Richard Jones asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I need to do some relatively simple extraction of fields from an XML
document.  In Perl I would use xpath, very specifically if $xml was an
XML document[1] stored as a string, then:

   my $p = XML::XPath-&gt;new (xml =&gt; $xml);
   my @disks = $p-&gt;findnodes ('//devices/disk/source/@dev');
   push (@disks, $p-&gt;findnodes ('//devices/disk/source/@file'));

This isn't type safe or pretty, but it is very easy to use for quick
and dirty extraction.

What is the OCaml equivalent for this sort of code?

Alain Frisch has a library called Xpath
(&lt;http://alain.frisch.fr/soft.html#xpath&gt;), but unfortunately this
relies on the now obsolete wlex program.

Is there a completely alternative way to do this?  Better still, in 3
lines of code??

Rich.

[1] for XML doc, see: http://libvirt.org/formatdomain.html
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yaron Minsky suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I don't have the code in front of me, but I've done something like   
this using the list monad. i.e., using bind (= concat-map) and map   
chained together, along with a couple operators I wrote for lifting   
bits of XML documents into lists, by say returning the subnodes of the   
present node as a list. 

It was quite effective.  I got the inspiration from a similar tool we   
have for navigating s-expressions, which we should release at some   
point... 
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Till Varoquaux also suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
There are a few projects out here:

xtisp
http://www.xtisp.org

xstream
http://yquem.inria.fr/~frisch/xstream/

and of course the good old cduce/xduce/ocamlduce. All in all naive
querying is not hard and tree automata:

(e.g.) http://www.grappa.univ-lille3.fr/~filiot/tata/

can provide a good middle ground between efficiency and simplicity.
The problem you might run into is that XML is a tricky format to deal
with and some of these tools will choke up on complex files
(namespaces,switching character encoding, weird entities in the DTD
etc..).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>pa_polyrec: syntax for polymorphic recursion</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/5a97eeeefef2ad41#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jeremy Yallop announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the initial release of pa_polyrec, a syntax extension 
for polymorphic recursion in OCaml.

  https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/pa-polyrec/

There are several methods for encoding polymorphic-recursive functions in
OCaml; this extension allows them to be written directly, using a natural
syntax. For example, given the following type of perfectly-balanced trees we
might wish to write a function for summing the leaves.

 type 'a perfect = Zero of 'a | Succ of ('a * 'a) perfect

In standard OCaml such a function can be written as follows:

 let sump f =
   (object (o)
       method sump : 'a. ('a -&gt; int) -&gt; 'a perfect -&gt; int =
         fun f -&gt; function
          | Zero x -&gt; f x
          | Succ x -&gt; o#sump (fun (a, b) -&gt; f a + f b) x
    end)#sump f

 let sum_perfect = sump id

Using pa_polyrec one can write the function in the following less obfuscated
style:

 let rec sump : 'a. ('a -&gt; int) -&gt; 'a perfect -&gt; int =
   fun f -&gt; function
    | Zero x -&gt; f x
    | Succ x -&gt; sump (fun (a, b) -&gt; f a + f b) x

 let sum_perfect = sump id

Note that the type variable 'a in the type of the function is quantified: this
is what differentiates polymorphic-recursive functions from standard OCaml
recursive function definitions.

More complex usage is supported, including mutual recursion. A number of
examples are included in the distribution, including several modules from
Chris Okasaki's thesis "Purely Functional Data Structures" and code from
Richard Bird and Ross Paterson's paper "de Bruijn notation as a nested
datatype".
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocamlcore.org/&gt;.

ssh.ocamlcore.org is alive:
  &lt;http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=432&gt;

pa_polyrec 0.1 released:
  &lt;http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=431&gt;

LablGTK2 2.14.0:
  &lt;http://caml.inria.fr/cgi-bin/hump.cgi?contrib=304&gt;

Cameleon 1.9.19:
  &lt;http://caml.inria.fr/cgi-bin/hump.cgi?contrib=467&gt;

Jane Street Summer Project round-up:
  &lt;http://ocaml.janestcapital.com/?q=node/68&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>