<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2010.03.16</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2010.03.09</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2010.03.23</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>March 09 to 16, 2010</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
	  <cwn_entry>
	   <cwn_title>testers wanted for experimental SSE2 back-end</cwn_title>
	   <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/ddb8d5d6318bef5a#</cwn_url>
	   <cwn_who>Xavier Leroy announced</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
This is a call for testers concerning an experimental OCaml compiler
back-end that uses SSE2 instructions for floating-point arithmetic.
This code generation strategy was discussed before on this list, and I
include below a summary in Q&amp;A style.

The new back-end is being considered for inclusion in the next major
release (3.12), but performance testing done so far at INRIA and by
Caml Consortium members is not conclusive.  Additional results
from members of this list would therefore be very welcome.

We're not terribly interested in small (&lt; 50 LOC), Shootout-style
benchmarks, since their performance is very sensitive to code and data
placement.  However, if some of you have a sizeable (&gt; 500 LOC) body
of float-intensive Caml code, we'd be very interested to hear about
the compared speed of the SSE2 back-end and the old back-end on your
code.

Switching to Q&amp;A style:

Q: Where can I get the code?

A: From the SVN repository:

svn checkout http://caml.inria.fr/svn/ocaml/branches/sse2 ocaml-sse2

Source-code only.  Very lightly tested under Windows, so you might be
better off testing under Unix.

Q: What is this SSE2 thingy?

A: An extension of the Intel/AMD x86 instruction set that provides,
among other things, 64-bit float arithmetic instructions operating
over 64-bit float registers.  Before SSE2, the only way to perform
64-bit float arithmetic on x86 was the x87 instructions, which compute
in 80-bit precision and use a stack instead of registers.

Q: Why this sudden interest in SSE2?

A: SSE2 has several potential advantages over x87, including:

- The register-based SSE2 model fits the OCaml back-end much better
 than the stack-based x87 model.  In particular, "let"-bound intermediate
 results of type "float" can be kept in SSE2 registers, while in
 the current x87 mode they are systematically flushed to the stack.

- SSE2 implements exactly 64-bit IEEE arithmetic, giving float results
 that are consistent with those obtained on other platforms and with
 the OCaml bytecode interpreter.  The 80-bit format of x87 produces
 different results and can causes surprises such as "double rounding"
 errors.  (For more explanations, see David Monniaux's excellent article,
 http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00128124/ )

- Some x86 processors execute SSE2 instructions faster than their x87
 counterparts.  This speed difference was notable on the Pentium 4
 in particular, but is much smaller on more recent processors such as
 Core 2.

Note that x86-64 bits systems as well as Mac OS X already use SSE2 as
their default floating-point model.

SSE2 also has some potential disadvantages:

- The instructions are bigger than x87 instructions, causing some
 increase in code size and potentially some decrease in instruction
 cache efficiency.

- Computing intermediate results in 80-bit precision, like x87 does,
 can improve the numerical stability of poorly-conditioned float
 computations, although it doesn't make a difference for well-written
 numerical code.

Q: Is SSE2 universally available on x86 processors?

A: Not universally but pretty close.  SSE2 made its debut in 2000, in
the Pentium 4 processor.  All x86 machines built in the last 4 years
or so support SSE2, but pre-Pentium 4 and pre-Athlon64 processors do not.

Q: So if you adopt this new back-end, OCaml will stop working on my
trusty 1995-vintage Pentium?

A: No.  Under friendly pressure from our Debian friends, we agreed to
keep the x87 back-end alive for a while in parallel with the SSE2
back-end.  The x87 back-end is selected at configuration time if the
processor doesn't support SSE2 or if a special flag is given to the
configure script.

Q: I observed a 20% (speedup|slowdown)!  Should I tell the world about it?

A: If your benchmark spends all its time in 10 lines of OCaml, maybe
not.  On such small codes, variations in code and data placement alone
(without changing the instructions that are actually executed) can
result in performance variations by 20%, so this is just experimental
noise.  Larger programs are less sensitive to this noise, which is why
we're much more interested in results obtained on real OCaml
applications.  Finally, one micro-benchmark slowed down by a factor of
2 for reasons we couldn't explain.

Q: What are those inconclusive results you mentioned?

A: On medium-sized numerical kernels (e.g. FFT, Gaussian process
regression), we've observed speedups of about 8% on Core 2 processors
and somewhat higher on recent AMD processors.  On bigger OCaml
applications that perform floating-point computations but not
exclusively, the performance difference was lost in the noise.

Looking forward to interesting experimental results.
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Later on, Xavier Leroy added</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
Right.  Sorry for not mentioning this.  The x86-64 bit code generator for
OCaml uses SSE2 floats, like all C compilers for this platform.  The
experimental back-end I announced is for x86-32 bit.  Some more Q&amp;A:

Q: I have OCaml installed on my x86 machine, how do I know if it's 32
or 64 bits?

A: Do:

 grep ^ARCH `ocamlopt -where`/Makefile.config

If it says "amd64", it's 64 bits with SSE2 floats.
If it says "i386", it's 32 bits with x87 floats.
If if says "ia32", it's the experimental back-end: 32 bits with SSE2 floats.

Q: If I compile from sources, which code generator is chosen by
default? 32 or 64 bits?

A: OCaml's configure script chooses whatever mode the C compiler
defaults to.  For instance, on a 32-bit Linux installation, the 32-bit
generator is selected, and on 64-bit Linux installation, it's the
64-bit generator.  Mac OS X is more tricky: 10.5 and earlier default
to 32 bits, but 10.6 defaults to 64 bits...
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Gaëtan Dubreil said</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
With my audio processing application of about 1300 LOC, i get a speedup of
about 9%. I run the application on Intel Pentium M under Kubuntu.
The application spend all the time doing computation on bigarray of float.
For me, the gain is appreciable. In real time audio processing, a speedup of
9% can be crucial.
	   </cwn_what>
	  </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
	   <cwn_title>OCaml Meeting 2010, 3 weeks before end of subscription</cwn_title>
	   <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/95349872532c4907#</cwn_url>
	   <cwn_who>Sylvain Le Gall announced</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
For the third time, I am proud to invite all OCaml enthusiasts to join
us at OCaml Meeting 2010 in Paris.

This year event takes place in Paris on Friday 16th April 2010.
Subscription is opened and will be closed on Friday 2nd April 2010.

Presentations include:

* Enforcing Type-Safe Linking using Inter-Package Relationships for
 OCaml Debian packages
* The Ocamlviz visualization toolkit
* Cluster computing in Ocaml
* Ocaml in a web startup
* React, functional reactive programming for OCaml
* OASIS, a Cabal like system for OCaml
* OPA, same web, but with types and lambda
* OC4MC, Objective Caml for MultiCore
* Lwt, Cooperative Light-Weight Threads
* naclgrid: the collaborative rendering farm, a JoCaml-powered
 desktop grid

The meeting is sponsored by INRIA, the Caml Consortium and OCamlCore.
Inscription is free but the number of participants is limited.

Further information and inscriptions:
http://wiki.cocan.org/events/europe/ocamlmeetingparis2010

The day after OCaml Meeting, Mehdi Dogguy from PPS helps me to organize
an informal day where OCaml teams can meet to work. We will have 2
classrooms, each can host 45 persons. There will be an internet access
and a blackboard in each room. Inscription is free.

Further information and inscriptions:
http://wiki.cocan.org/events/europe/ocamlhackingdayparis2010

Volunteers willing to help before/during these events can contact me
directly. We are particularly looking for a video team. You can also
forward this invitation to any groups that can be interested in (Haskell
user group, CUFP mailing list...)

For people who need further information, you can contact me (see
wiki.cocan.org for contact details).
	   </cwn_what>
	  </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
	   <cwn_title>CCSS 1.0</cwn_title>
	   <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/d417348eec3c5dfe#</cwn_url>
	   <cwn_who>Dario Teixeira announced</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
CCSS is a preprocessor for CSS (Cascading Style Sheets), extending the
language with arithmetic operations and variables.  It was born out of
frustration with the unbearable slowness and lack of support for some
CSS3 constructs in other similar tools such as LESS [1].  Here are
some points to be aware:

 - The CSS source is actually parsed into an AST, which is then converted
  again into a CSS textual representation for output.  You can therefore
  use it as a pretty-printer.  On the downside, comments are stripped out.

 - Because it is an actual parser, it is fairly straightforward to hack
  your own custom transformations to the AST.  The scanner is Ulex-based,
  whereas Menhir is required for building the parser.

 - CCSS knows only of CSS syntax, and has no knowledge of actual CSS
  properties and valid values for each.  This simplifies the program
  and makes it future-compatible, but also means that will gleefully
  accept nonsensical CSS properties such as the following:

  h1 {foo: bar;}

 - The scanner/parser does not cover some of the hairy corners of CSS.
  It does however handle new syntactic constructs introduced with CSS3.

 - The arithmetic operations are unit-aware, and will complain if you
  try adding apples and oranges, for example.


Examples of use and the syntax for the language extensions are described
in the project's homepage, which also includes building instructions and
download links [2].  Note that the source-code is released under the terms
of the GNU GPL v2.

Last, but not least, though no particular attention was given to performance,
it does fulfill the initial goal of making execution time as close to zero
as not to get in the way...

Hope you find it useful -- feedback is welcome!

Best regards,
Dario Teixeira


[1] http://lesscss.org/index.html
[2] http://ccss.forge.ocamlcore.org/
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>After a discussion on units, Daniel Bünzli said and Dario Teixeira replied</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
&gt; The problem is that different kind of objects naturally use different
&gt; kind of units. A font size or line height for example is usually
&gt; expressed in pts and a standard paper or photographic print size will
&gt; be in cms (or inches).

Sure, and nothing stops you from using those different units in different
contexts.  CCSS only constrains you if you try doing *arithmetic* with
those units, which I posit should rarely be an issue, precisely because
they live in different contexts.

But anyway, I've implemented unit conversion, which you can find in SVN [1].
In the next release this feature may be activated at user discretion.

Units are divided into four categories, and units within the same category
may be mixed.  The result gets the same unit as the first operand.  The
categories are as follows:

  length: mm, cm, in, pt, pc
   angle: deg, grad, rad
    time: ms, s
frequency: hz, khz

In the following example, the output for all properties will be "2in":

h1
 {
 foo1: 1in + 1in;
 foo2: 1in + 2.54cm;
 foo3: 1in + 25.4mm;
 foo4: 1in + 72pt;
 foo5: 1in + 6pc;
 }


Best regards,
Dario Teixeira

[1] http://forge.ocamlcore.org/scm/viewvc.php/?root=ccss
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Later on, Dario Teixeira added</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
In the meantime I've released version 1.1, which includes the requested
unit conversion feature.  It works as I described in a previous email,
but is not activated by default.  If you really need this feature, simply
provide option '--convert' (short version '-c') upon command line invocation.

For more information: http://ccss.forge.ocamlcore.org/
	   </cwn_what>
	  </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
	   <cwn_title>Shared memory parallel application: kernel threads</cwn_title>
	   <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/f58f59b700c317fb#</cwn_url>
	   <cwn_who>Hugo Ferreira asked</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
I need to implement (meta) heuristic algorithms that
uses parallelism in order to (attempt to) solve a (hard)
machine learning problem that is inherently exponential.
The aim is to take maximum advantage of the multi-core
processors I have access to.

To that effect I have revisited many of the lively
discussions in threads related to concurrency, parallelism
and shared memory in this mailing list. I however still
have many doubts, some of which are very basic.

My initial objective is to make a very simple tests that
launches k jobs. Each of these jobs must access
a common data set that is read-only. Each of the k threads
in turn generates its own data. The data generated by the k
jobs are then placed in a queue for further processing.

The process continues by launching (or reusing) k/2 jobs.
Each job consumes two elements from the queue that where
previously generated (the common data set must still be
available). The process repeats itself until k=1. Note
that the queued data is not small nor can I determine
a fixed maximum size for it.

I have opted to use "kernel-level threads" that allow use
of the (multi-core) processors but still allow "easy"
access to shared memory".

I have done a cursory look at:
- Ocaml.Threads
- Ocaml.Unix (LinuxThreads)
- coThreads
- Ocamlnet2/3 (netshm, netcamlbox)
(An eThreads library exists in the forge but I did not examine this)

My first concern is to take advantage of the multi-cores so:

1. The thread library is not the answer
  Chapter 24 - "The threads library is implemented by time-sharing on a
  single processor. It will not take advantage of multi-processor
  machines." [1]

2. LinuxThreads seems to be what I need
  "The main strength of this approach is that it can take full
   advantage of multiprocessors." [2]


Issue 1

In the manual [3] I see only references to function for the creation
and  use of processes. I see no calls that allow me to simply generate
and assign a function (job) to a thread (such as val create : ('a -&gt; 'b)
 -&gt; 'a -&gt; t in the Thread module). The unix library where LinuxThreads
is now integrated shows the same API. Am I missing something or
is their no way to launch "threaded functions" from the Unix module?
Naturally I assume that threads and processes are not the same thing.

Issue 2

If I cannot launch kernel-threads to allow for easy memory sharing, what
other options do I have besides netshm? The data I must share is defined
by a recursive variant and is not simple numerical data.

I would appreciate any comments.

TIA,
Hugo F.


[1] http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml/manual038.html
[2] http://pauillac.inria.fr/~xleroy/linuxthreads/
[3] http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml/libref/ThreadUnix.html
[4] http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml/manual035.html
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann suggested</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
I think you mix here several things up. LinuxThreads has nothing to do
with ocaml. It is an implementation of kernel threads for Linux on the C
level. It is considered as outdated as of today, and is usually replaced
by a better implementation (NPTL) that conforms more strictly to the
POSIX standard.

Ocaml uses for its multi-threading implementation the multi-threading
API the OS provides. This might be LinuxThreads or NPTL or something
else. So, on the lower half of the implementation the threads are kernel
threads, and multi-core-enabled. However, Ocaml prevents that more than
one of the kernel threads can run inside its runtime at any time. So
Ocaml code will always run only on one core (but you can call C code,
and this can then take full advantage of multi-cores).

This is the primary reason I am going with multi-processing in my
projects, and why Ocamlnet focuses on it.

The Netcamlbox module of Ocamlnet 3 might be interesting for you. Here
is an example program that mass-multiplies matrices on several cores:

https://godirepo.camlcity.org/svn/lib-ocamlnet2/trunk/code/examples/camlbox/manymult.ml

Netcamlbox can move complex values to shared memory, so you are not
restricted to bigarrays. The matrix example uses float array array as
representation. Recursive variants should also be fine.

For providing shared data to all workers, you can simply load it into
the master process before the children processes are forked off. Another
option is (especially when it is a lot of data, and you cannot afford to
have n copies) to create another camlbox in the master process before
forking, and to copy the shared data into it before forking. This avoids
that the data is copied at fork time.

One drawback of Netcamlbox is that it is unsafe, and violating the
programming rules is punished with crashes. (But this also applies, to
some extent, to multi-threading, only that the rules are different.)
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Sylvain Le Gall also suggested</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
I think you should also have a look at ocaml/mpi for communication:
http://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/ocamlmpi/
and ancient for accessing read-only memory:
http://merjis.com/developers/ancient

MPI can work on a single computer to take advantage of multi-core
through multi-processus.
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Philippe Wang also suggested</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
If your program doesn't need usage-proved stability, you may be
interested in the "OCaml for Multicore" project which provides an
alternative runtime library (prototype quality) which allows threads
to compute in parallel.
http://www.algo-prog.info/ocmc/
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Richard Jones also suggested</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
At least look at OCaml Ancient for sharing the data.  You possibly may
not use it, but it was designed pretty much for what you have in mind.
The README should be informative:

http://merjis.com/developers/ancient
http://merjis.com/_file/ancient-readme.txt

(You should also look at the API and source).  You didn't mention how
large your read-only data set is, but OCaml Ancient should be able to
handle 100s of gigabytes, assuming a 64 bit machine.  We used to use
it with 10s of gigabyte data sets without any issues.

As others have said, don't use threads to launch your jobs.  Look at
one of the fork-based libraries.  In addition to the ones mentioned,
take a look at PreludeML, which is internally very simple and should
give you a good start if you decide to write your own:

http://github.com/kig/preludeml

If you want to spread the jobs over multiple machines, then OCaml MPI
is probably the way to go.
	   </cwn_what>
	   <cwn_who>Hugo Ferreira then said and Richard Jones replied</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
&gt; I will be using a single 8-CPU machine for the experiments.
&gt; For the problem at hand shared the memory model seems to be
&gt; a better fit than messaging.

I've not actually tried it, but I bet you can use a hybrid model --
Use MPI as an easy way to spread the jobs over the nodes and for
coordinating the processes, then have each process open a shared
Ancient file (backed by NFS) for the read-only data.
	   </cwn_what>
	  </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
	   <cwn_title>CamlPDF 0.5</cwn_title>
	   <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/a2fd08554b864254#</cwn_url>
	   <cwn_who>John Whitington announced</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the CamlPDF 0.5 release, which includes a couple of
new modules (Pdfdate for date manipulation, Pdfannot for annotations and
Pdfmarks for bookmarks). Almost every other module has been improved in some
way.

Download: http://www.coherentpdf.com/ocaml-libraries.html

More importantly, I've finally found time to write a short introduction to
CamlPDF, which lets you try some basic work within the OCaml top level:

http://www.coherentpdf.com/introduction_to_camlpdf.pdf

There have been some API modifications which are not backward compatible, but
the changes to your source are easy to make. This should be the last release
with such changes.

There is now a CamlPDF mailing list:

http://www.freelists.org/list/camlpdf
	   </cwn_what>
	  </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
	   <cwn_title>OCamlspotter 1.1</cwn_title>
	   <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/8e7de0721812e539#</cwn_url>
	   <cwn_who>Jun Furuse announced</cwn_who>
	   <cwn_what>
I have updated OCamlSpotter, a compiler enhancement for source code browsing,
to version 1.1, which is aimed for OCaml 3.11.2 and some enhancements
since its first release.

OCamlSpotter is a tool which finds definition places of various names
(identifiers, type names, modules, etc) in OCaml programs automatically for
you. The original OCaml's -annot option provides the same sort of
functionality but OCamlSpotter provides much more powerful browsing: it can
find definitions hidden in the deep nested module aliases and functor
applications.

- The -annot option of ocamlc and ocamlopt is extended and creates
  &lt;module&gt;.spot files (&lt;module&gt;.spit for .mli), which record the location
  information of the names defined and used in the module.

- A small application ocamlspot provides automatic where-about spotting of the
  definition of the name you are interested in, using &lt;module&gt;.spot files
  created by the patched compilers.

- ocamlspot.el provides interactive ocaml-spotting of definition locations in
  emacs.

- Interfaces for other editors such as vi could be built easily, if you want.

This release of OCamlSpotter is 1.1. Some bugs found in 1.1rc1 were fixed.

Further information and download is available at:

  http://jun.furuse.info/hacks/ocamlspotter
	   </cwn_what>
	  </cwn_entry>
		<cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocamlcore.org/&gt;.

CamlPDF 0.5:
  &lt;http://caml.inria.fr/cgi-bin/hump.cgi?contrib=571&gt;

CamlPDF 0.5 Released:
  &lt;http://coherentpdf.com/blog/?p=44&gt;

GHC 6.12.1 in Debian Testing.:
  &lt;http://www.mega-nerd.com/erikd/Blog/CodeHacking/Debian/ghc6.12_testing.html&gt;

FP-Syd #22.:
  &lt;http://www.mega-nerd.com/erikd/Blog/FP-Syd/fp-syd-22.html&gt;

CCSS 1.1 released:
  &lt;http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=561&gt;

CCSS 1.1:
  &lt;http://caml.inria.fr/cgi-bin/hump.cgi?contrib=722&gt;

CCSS 1.0 released:
  &lt;http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=560&gt;

LLVM, OCaml and Debian:
  &lt;http://le-gall.net/sylvain+violaine/blog/index.php?2010/03/10/55-llvm-ocaml-and-debian&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>