<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2010.09.28</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2010.09.21</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2010.10.05</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>September 21 to 28, 2010</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
	  <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>pfff_visual, a fancy code visualizer/navigator for OCaml, and more</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/07285a0dca9c392f#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yoann Padioleau announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It is my pleasure to announce pfff_visual, a code visualizer/navigator
for OCaml. Note that this is not a replacement for Emacs or vi, but more a
companion that works with Emacs/Vi.

A demo is available here:
part1: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HRZjBGD3osw
part2: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=993pmNLY_VU

pfff_visual is using pfff, which is mainly an OCaml API to write
static analysis, dynamic analysis, code visualizations, code
navigations, or style-preserving source-to-source transformations such
as refactorings on source code. For now the effort is focused on PHP
but there is preliminary support for Javascript, and C++ code.
There is also preliminary support for OCaml code so that the infrastructure
can be used on the code of pfff itself.

You can get the source of pfff and pfff_visual here:
http://github.com/facebook/pfff

Here is how to install it:
$ git clone git@github.com:facebook/pfff.git
$ ./configure
$ make depend; make; make opt
$ ./pfff_visual /path/to/project/using/supported/languages

pfff has been tested on MacOS and Linux and is licensed under the LGPL.

Thanks to 
- Lex Stein for ocamlbdb
- Olivier Andrieu for ocamlcairo
- Jacques Garrigue for ocamlgtk
- Martin Jambon, Mika Illouz and Gert Stolpmann for lib-json
- Nicolas Canasse for lib-xml
- Jane Street for lib-sexp
- Thomas Gazagnaire for dynType
- Maas-Maarten Zeeman for OUnit.ml
- Thorsten Ohl for xHTML.ml
- Sylvain Conchon, Jean-Christophe Filliâtre and Julien Signoles for 
  ocamlgraph
- Xavier Leroy for ocamlmpi
- Markus Mottl for ocamlpcre
- Iain Proctor for ocamlthrift
- Guillaume Cottenceau for pleac
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yoann Padioleau later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
For the people who refuse to vomit while watching a video,
here are a few screenshots of the visualizer applied on the linux
kernel source, the ocaml source, and the source of pfff itself:

http://padator.org/software/pfff/pfff_linux_source.jpg
http://padator.org/software/pfff/pfff_ocaml_source.jpg
http://padator.org/software/pfff/pfff_ocaml_source2.jpg
http://padator.org/software/pfff/pfff_ocaml_source3.jpg
http://padator.org/software/pfff/pfff_pfff_source.jpg

The screenshots can not show the integration with Emacs though.  You'll have
to suffer and watch the videos for that.

If you don't have git, you can still download pfff by following this link:
 http://github.com/facebook/pfff/archives/master
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Postdoc vacancies in OUCL Information Systems Group</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/385328219b9682d9#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Ian Horrocks announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
OXFORD UNIVERSITY COMPUTING LABORATORY 

INFORMATION SYSTEMS GROUP 

POST-DOCTORIAL RESEARCH ASSISTANT POSTS 

The Computing Laboratory has a vacancy for three postdoctoral research
assistants to work in the Information Systems Group. The posts are funded by
EPSRC as part of the LogMap project (1 post) and ExODA project (2 posts) - see
http://www.comlab.ox.ac.uk/projects/LogMap/ and
http://web.comlab.ox.ac.uk/projects/ExODA/ for more information. The posts are
available immediately and will be of 24 months (for LogMap) or 36 months (for
ExODA) duration.

Applicants should have, or expect shortly to obtain, a PhD in computer science
or some other relevant discipline, and should have a strong background in
theoretical computer science. Experience in some or all of the following areas
would be useful but is not essential: logics and automated reasoning;
databases and database theory; ontologies and ontology languages; knowledge
representation. Implementation experience would also be useful. The posts will
require occasional travel to international conferences and workshops.

The successful applicants will join an internationally leading and rapidly
growing research group led by Professor Georg Gottlob and Professor Ian
Horrocks - see http://web.comlab.ox.ac.uk/research/is/ - and with more than 25
doctoral and post-doctoral researchers working on a range of projects in the
area of databases and knowledge representation and reasoning.

Further particulars, including details of how to apply, are available from
http://www.comlab.ox.ac.uk/news/documents/info-syst-posts-fps.pdf

The closing date for applications is 22nd October 2010.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>post-doctoral position or 1-year graduate internship -- GUI for TLA+</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/0adcf6c6e8d0457f#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jean-Jacques Levy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The Microsoft Research-INRIA Joint Centre welcomes applications for a
post-doctoral position or graduate internship in the area of tools for
interactive theorem proving. The 1-year scholarship can start from fall 2010.

The successful candidate will contribute to the development of the GUI of the
TLA+ proof system. TLA+ is Lamport's logic for specification and verification
of programs. The system is already developed and distributed at

 http://www.msr-inria.inria.fr/Projects/tools-for-formal-specs

The candidate should be able to program in Java + Eclipse. Knowledge in
mathematical logic is also recommended. The work will be performed inside the
"Tools for Formal Specs" group [Damien Doligez, Denis Cousineau, Leslie
Lamport, Stephan Merz] at MSR-INRIA Joint Centre in Orsay (south of Paris,
France). It will be a prolongation of the interface already developed by
Kaustuv Chaudury, Simon Zambrosky, and Dan Ricketts.

Applications should include a curriculum vitae in pdf format and should be
sent to

Centre de Recherche Commun INRIA-Microsoft Research,
Parc Orsay Université, 28, rue Jean Rostand, 
91893 Orsay Cedex, France
Telephone: +33 1 69 35 69 70
Fax: +33 1 69 35 69 69

E-mails: damien.doligez@inria.fr, http://lamport.org

Please email me for any further questions about the position and the related
project.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocamlcore.org/&gt;.

Liquidsoap at ON2: Test signals, October, 22-23 2010 in Berlin:
  &lt;http://blog.rastageeks.org/liquidsoap/article/liquidsoap-at-on2-test-signals&gt;

Programming with effects II: Introducing eff:
  &lt;http://math.andrej.com/2010/09/27/programming-with-effects-ii-introducing-eff/&gt;

Programming with effects I: Theory:
  &lt;http://math.andrej.com/2010/09/27/programming-with-effects-i-theory/&gt;

On the State of API Documentation:
  &lt;http://gaiustech.wordpress.com/2010/09/27/api-documentation/&gt;

lazy me, BronKerbosh algorithm revisited:
  &lt;https://mancoosi.org/~abate/lazy-me-bronkerbosh-algorithm-revisited&gt;

Enhanced Ocaml Documentation Version 3.12:
  &lt;http://www.wisdomandwonder.com/link/5310/enhanced-ocaml-documentation-version-3-12&gt;

Resources for Learning CamlP4:
  &lt;http://www.wisdomandwonder.com/link/5302/resources-for-learning-camlp4&gt;

LDAP / Scope in database code (3):
  &lt;http://gaiustech.wordpress.com/2010/09/24/ldap-1-scope-in-database-code-3/&gt;

kprintf and failwith:
  &lt;https://mancoosi.org/~abate/kprintf-and-failwith&gt;

Onotify 0.6 : the first public release !:
  &lt;http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=688&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
