<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2010.06.01</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2010.05.25</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2010.06.08</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>May 25 to June 01, 2010</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
	<cwn_body>
	  <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>new emacs tuareg mode release</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/f575a5d8b3d491/c29929560758a842</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sam Steingold announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Tuareg 2.0.1 is now available from 
&lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/frs/?group_id=43&gt;. 
The main difference is a skip-syntax bug fix. 
The sources are also available via svn from 
&lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/scm/?group_id=43&gt;. 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Sysadmin/programmer combo positions at Jane Street</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/30b18d5391e1bb8c#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Owen Gunden announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
In addition to the more conventional development positions described in
Yaron Minsky's recent email, we are hiring people with skills at both
functional programming and systems administration.

Most of our systems automation software is either written in ocaml or
will be sooner or later.

-----

Sysadmin/Programmer combo
(aka Systems Automation Specialist)

Seeking:

Responsible, careful, passionate and skillful technology specialists to help
build and maintain our increasingly automated technology infrastructure.

You'll need to be adept with unix (specifically linux) administration. For
example, you want to be able to format filesystems, install bootloaders, and
make rpm packages. It's even better if you understand system calls, kernel
parameters, IO schedulers, and other lower level internals.

You'll also need to be a good programmer. We only want people who've had
experience writing significant amounts of real-world code. OCaml is our
language of choice, but it's okay if you don't know it so long as you can
learn it. Experience in ruby, python, php, perl, scheme, haskell, erlang, and
others are all acceptable.

About us:

Jane Street is a proprietary trading firm with offices in NYC, London
and Hong Kong (respond to this ad if you're interested in any of the
above). We have about 200 employees total, the majority of whom work in
NYC. While this makes us a medium-sized business, the culture
more closely resembles that of a small startup: The atmosphere is casual and
informal; we care about doing good work more than dress codes or hours put in;
there's not much room for office politics; and, there's a lot of financial
upside if you do great work.

We have a large datacenter on-site and several colocation facilities, with
hundreds of servers total. We manage all of this with just a small team by
leveraging our programming skills to create scalable, automated systems. We
use a lot of open source tools and write the rest ourselves.

Our systems team is tightly integrated with the rest of the company so you get
exposure to a broad range of concepts and ideas. Unlike at other large
financial firms, our technology group is highly regarded and central to our
business, not just a footnote.

Perks:

In addition to our excellent benefits which you can read about here:

 http://www.janestreet.com/workplace/benefits.php

we have on-site classes taught by employees on subjects ranging from
programming to finance to trading to bridge (yes, the game).


If this sounds like a match to your background, skills, and disposition, let
us know. Send a cover letter indicating why you think you're a good fit, along
with your resume, to ogunden@janestreet.com.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Offre d'emploi / Job offer</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>http://groups.google.com/group/fa.caml/browse_thread/thread/73993da1c22feb57#</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>David Rajchenbach-Teller announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
** Informaticiens de haut niveau

MLstate est une jeune entreprise innovante en campagne depuis 2008 pour la
reconquête du web. Notre objectif : réinventer les bases technologiques et
scientifiques des applications web, pour une toile plus saine, plus sûre et
plus sécurisée. Notre équipe R&amp;D compte une vingtaine de passionnés, docteurs
ou ingénieurs en informatique, et est sur le point de s’agrandir.

Si vous êtes informaticien de haut niveau, inspiré et ingénieux, si vous êtes
doté d’une forte culture informatique et scientifique, d’une grande
connaissance des langages fonctionnels et impératifs, de la compilation, des
systèmes de types, contactez-nous. Le candidat idéal, docteur ou non, avec ou
sans expérience industrielle, aura aussi des connaissances en distribution,
parallélisme, bases de données, sera capable d’évoluer dans un environnement
polyglotte et disposera de la finesse nécessaire pour construire des produits
finis.

Les problèmes à résoudre sont difficiles. Pour relever le défi, contactez-nous
à careers@mlstate.com .


** High-level computer scientists

Since its foundation, in 2008, Paris-based start-up MLstate has been
campaigning to reconquer the web. Our objective: reinvent technological and
scientific foundations of web applications, and make the web saner, safer and
more secure. Our R&amp;D team comprises about 20 enthusiastic computer scientists,
doctors or engineers, and is now preparing to scale up.

If you are a high-level computer scientist, inspired, resourceful, if you have
a strong culture in computer science, in both functional and imperative
programming languages, in compilation, in type systems, contact us. Ideal
candidates, PhDs or not, with or without industry experience, will also have a
background in distribution, concurrency, databases, will be able to live and
work in a multilingual environment, and will have the subtlety necessary to
build finish products.

The problems we need to solve are difficult. If you are up to the challenge,
contact us at careers@mlstate.com .
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
	  <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocamlcore.org/&gt;.

Caml Trading talk at CMU:
  &lt;http://www.wisdomandwonder.com/link/4900/caml-trading-talk-at-cmu&gt;

Offres d’emploi pour informaticiens de haut niveau:
  &lt;http://dutherenverseauborddelatable.wordpress.com/2010/05/31/offres-demploi-pour-informaticiens-de-haut-niveau/&gt;

FP-Syd #24.:
  &lt;http://www.mega-nerd.com/erikd/Blog/FP-Syd/fp-syd-24.html&gt;

Gematric Search:
  &lt;http://alaska-kamtchatka.blogspot.com/2010/05/gematric-search.html&gt;

Tuareg 2.0.1:
  &lt;http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=618&gt;

Shopping Carts with Ocsigen.:
  &lt;http://blog.dbpatterson.com/post/637836183&gt;

DrScheme Style Buffer Evaluation for OCaml in Emacs:
  &lt;http://www.wisdomandwonder.com/article/4797/drscheme-style-buffer-evaluation-for-ocaml-in-emacs&gt;

ocaml-cyclist:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/ocaml-cyclist/&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>