<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2011.07.26</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2011.07.19</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2011.08.02</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 19 to 26, 2011</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Sawja release 1.3</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00097.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Vincent Monfort announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We have the pleasure to announce a new release of Sawja, the Static
Analysis Workshop for JAva.

Sawja is a library written in OCaml, relying on the Javalib library,
and providing a high level representation of Java bytecode
programs. Whereas Javalib is dedicated to isolated classes, Sawja
handles bytecode programs with their class hierarchy and control flow
algorithms. Sawja also provides some stackless intermediate
representations of code and static analysis tools that makes analyses
easier.

The main new feature of this release is an Eclipse plugin for analyses
developed with Sawja, which can be integrated into the IDE without
requiring any additional Java code generation. By having these tools
readily available in the leading environment for Java programmers, we
aim at promoting the adoption of advanced static analysis tools in
industrial settings, and at providing a solid basis for
upstream/academic analysis debugging and demonstration.

More information, examples, and a series of tutorials are available at
&lt;http://sawja.inria.fr&gt;. The Sawja devteam is looking forward to your
questions and feedback on the library.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>GODI News: 3.12.1 released, new website</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00104.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
the GODI project just updated the release line for Ocaml-3.12 which
bases now on version 3.12.1. We have done extensive tests, and found
only some minor incompatibilities for ocamlbuild (which is a bit pickier
now and chokes sometimes when it sees extra files it does not know
about). These could be resolved. At the same time, the 3.12 release
loses its beta status (which had it for quite a long time), and is now
the recommended Ocaml version.

GODI also gets a newly designed web site: http://godi.camlcity.org is
now much more illustrative and informative. As a special bonus, a news
feed is included with the newest package releases (right now only as
HTML, RSS will follow later). Also the list of packages has been
reworked and is now fully dynamic (instead of generated).

The new bootstrap for GODI is now available as
http://www.camlcity.org:81/download/godi-rocketboost-20110717.tar.gz
It also got a bit of developers' attention, and is now more intuitive.
(For example, the stage 2 of the bootstrap is now automatically started.
The bootstrap is now interactive by default.) If you do not want to run
another bootstrap, you can also upgrade your existing GODI installation:

* If you already have a 3.12 installation, just follow the normal
upgrade path for packages in godi_console. Ocaml 3.12.1 is a normal
package upgrade here.

* If you still use a 3.11 installation, just edit godi.conf, and replace
the line setting GODI_SECTION, and set this variable to 3.12. Then
perform a package upgrade using godi_console (as above).

There are a few remaining issues with the new version:

- Batteries: It is reported that there is an incompatibility with the
  new Hashtbl signature. It is being worked on this. Currently the
  package is broken. It is recommended that users wait until the
  problems have been resolved.
- Ocamlduce is still unavailable for 3.12.1. This also affects
  dependencies like godi-tyxml.
- After installing GODI on a newly set up system, I found problems
  for godi-mlgmp, godi-fftw, and godi-lablgtk(1), because they
  are out of sync with current C libraries, or the C libraries have
  become unavailable (like gtk1).
- There are a few applications which are still broken:
  apps-felix, apps-nurpawiki, apps-pkglab, apps-regstab. The
  package maintainers are notified.

The documentation archive docs.camlcity.org is still switching to 3.12
as default source for documentation. This means not all package docs are
available yet (but an impressive subset is already). I hope this will be
fixed until tomorrow.

A final word about GODI and OASIS. Sylvain is very interested in
providing the OASIS packages in a format that GODI understands. There is
now the plan that GODI extracts the required information from its
package db, and OASIS uses this to wrap its packages so these can be
included as package source into godi_console. We are now working on
this.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocamlcore.org/&gt;.

Moving out of the 70s...:
  &lt;http://blog.rastageeks.org/ocaml/article/moving-out-of-the-70s&gt;

smf:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/smf/&gt;

Grammar Tool:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/gratool/&gt;

GODI upgrades to Ocaml-3.12.1:
  &lt;http://blog.camlcity.org/blog/godi_3_12_1.html&gt;

OCaml RSS Feed Parser:
  &lt;http://www.rktmb.org/post/2011/07/20/OCaml-RSS-Feed-Parser&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
