<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2011.08.02</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2011.07.26</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2011.08.09</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 26 to August 02, 2011</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Hashtbl performance</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00117.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Toby Kelsey asked and Fabrice Le Fessant replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; I have written two versions of a small program, one using an (int list) 
&gt; data structure and the other an ((int*int) list); and I tested using 
&gt; Hashtbl, Set and (Jean-Christophe Filliatre's) Trie to cache these elements 
&gt; in each version.
&gt; The relative run times of the programs turns out to be:
&gt; 
&gt;                  Hashtbl  Set  Trie
&gt; (int list)         1      2.1  2.0
&gt; ((int*int) list)  34.7    2.6  2.1
&gt; 
&gt; 
&gt; There is a slight inherent speed difference between the 2 versions but the 
&gt; major effect is the cache type (in fact the caching difference must be 
&gt; larger than these ratios due to non-cache computations). I expected Hashtbl 
&gt; might be a bit slower than more specialised data structures, but the large 
&gt; speed difference with different data structures was unexpected. Presumably 
&gt; the slow-down is due to excessive hash collisions.
&gt; 
&gt; I had expected that the generic Hashtbl would be written to give adequate 
&gt; speed for all types of data and when I look at OCaml code on the web 
&gt; Hashtbl is usually used, so it seems most OCaml programmers believe the 
&gt; standard Hashtbl is a reasonable choice for most data types as well.
&gt; 
&gt; I haven't tested the Batteries or OCaml-Core hash tables so these may be 
&gt; more consistent, but if not, my question is can you predict how well 
&gt; Hashtbl will work for different types of data and so what to use it with, 
&gt; or it is just not reliable enough for general-purpose caching/memoization?
&gt; 
&gt; If anyone wants to look at the code, the (int list) Hashtbl version is at 
&gt; &lt;http://rosettacode.org/wiki/Sokoban#OCaml&gt; and the other versions are in 
&gt; &lt;http://pastebin.com/hGn1AL9L&gt; temporarily. Apart from the caching and the 
&gt; int/int pair changes they should be identical.
 I think it is a well known bug of the hash function:

let list = ref [];;
for i = 1 to 30 do
  list := i :: !list;
  Printf.printf "%d " (Hashtbl.hash !list)
done;;

1 65601 8392706 797307010 578301955 797307010 8392706 65601 1 0 0 0 0 0
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0

As you can see, long lists all have the same hash value. It is due to
the fact that the hash function does a depth-first traversal of the
datastructure, starting with the last field, instead of a breadth-first
traversal, and, as it only visits 10 nodes, they are always the same
ones for all lists of length &gt; 10.

Thus, you should consider using your own hash function, probably only
considering the ints in the list and its length. Then, use the functor
in the Hashtbl module.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Nicolas Barnier then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
You could also use the hash_param : int -&gt; int -&gt; 'a -&gt; int
function in the functor which allows to specify the number
of nodes traversed to compute the key :

# let list = ref [];;
  for i = 1 to 30 do
  list := i :: !list;
  Printf.printf "%d " (Hashtbl.hash_param 50 50 !list)
done  ;;
1 65601 8392706 797307010 578301955 731304131 182476804 222011652
582000645 696017221 383840262 291574150 409554951 301052359 474071048
875971080 459423753 1026998857 314757130 771437194 56324107 59478731
841228300 921690892 921690892 841228300 59478731 56324107 771437194
314757130 - : unit = ()
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Xavier Leroy then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Both Fabrice's and Nicolas's suggestions are excellent.

Let me just add that this problem with lists as hashtable keys is one
of the known issues with OCaml's current generic hash function: the
other is that the mixing functions used are simplistic and exhibit
some statistical bias, even for strings.

The SVN trunk for OCaml contains a complete reimplementation of the
generic hash function that addresses both issues: lists and other
complex keys are traversed breadth-first in a more cautious manner
than before, and the mixing functions are based on MurmurHash 3, which
exhibits very good statistical properties.  All this should go in the
next major release 3.13.  So, everyone with an interest in efficient
hash tables is welcome to try the trunk sources and let me know of any
problems encountered.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>utop 1.0 released</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00128.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jérémie Dimino announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am pleased to announce the first release of utop, a new toplevel for
OCaml.

utop has two modes; in can run in a terminal or in emacs. In the
terminal it supports real-time completion, colors, parenthesis matching
and prompt customization. In emacs it supports completion and
integration with the tuareg mode, and behaves more like a toplevel than
the default one of the tuareg mode, i.e. you cannot erase the prompt.

You can download utop here:

  https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/utop/
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Scherer then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
In case someone else is interested, I computed the transitive closure
of the various dependencies. If you want to play with utop you will
need:
- utop:
    https://forge.ocamlcore.org/frs/download.php/664/utop-1.0.tar.gz
- which depends on lambda-term:
    https://forge.ocamlcore.org/frs/download.php/663/lambda-term-1.0.tar.gz
- which itself depends on zed:
    https://forge.ocamlcore.org/frs/download.php/662/zed-1.0.tar.gz
- which relies on a version &gt;= 8 of Camomile; if you still have
  version 7, compilation is going to fail (but only after the configure
  step; Jérémie, consider this a bug report)
    http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/camomile/camomile-0.8.3.tar.bz2

The good news is that you don't have to look at the build system used,
"./configure; make; sudo make install" works like a charm.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Thomas Gazagnaire also added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
And also ocamlfind, react and lwt :-)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Great Renaming</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00135.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Damien Doligez announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We have implemented the decision taken at this year's OCaml meeting: to
change the name of the language and system to "OCaml" in one word, with
capital O and capital C, and nothing between them.

That makes it much easier to find on search engines, so we suggest that
everyone uses this new name (most of you already do anyway).

With a non-negligible amount of work, I have changed the sources
(including the copyright headers!), the Web site, and the documentation.
As a side-effect, recompiling the documentation fixed PR#5317 at last.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Time to register for CUFP</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00145.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yaron Minsky announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The talks and tutorials for CUFP are now up, and it's a really
interesting protocols, covering a broad range of FP topics, and
including quite a bit that touches on OCaml specifically.

Note: The deadline for reduced-fee registrations is August 15th.

I hope to see a lot of you there!

y
_____________________________________________________________ 

   Commercial Users of Functional Programming Workshop 
                       (CUFP) 2011

                 Call for Participation 

                  Sponsored by SIGPLAN 

                Co-located with ICFP 2011

_____________________________________________________________ 

                 September 22-24, 2011
                     Tokyo, Japan

        http://cufp.org/conference/schedule/2011

       Reservation available through ICFP's website
     https://regmaster3.com/2011conf/ICFP11/register.php

_____________________________________________________________ 


Functional programming languages have been a hot topic of academic
research for over 35 years, and they have seen an ever larger
practical impact in settings ranging from tech startups to financial
firms to biomedical research labs. At the same time, a vigorous
community of working programmers employing functional languages 
has come into existence.

CUFP is designed to serve this community. The annual CUFP workshop is
a place where people can see how others are using functional
programming to solve real world problems; where practitioners meet and
collaborate; where language designers and users can share ideas about
the future of their favorite language; and where one can learn
practical techniques and approaches for putting functional programming
to work.

CUFP 2011 will feature two days of tutorials given by language
experts, on the 22nd and 23rd, and a day of talks on the 24th.
Attendees may register for any subset of the days.

Day 1, Tutorials (September 22nd)
=================================

   Morning:
     - Building reliable Client-Server Applications in Erlang
       (Francesco Cesarini)
     - Jane Street's OCaml Core library (Yaron Minsky)
   Afternoon:
     - Building a functional OS (Anil Madhavapeddy, David Scott,
       Richard Mortier)
     - Collaborative Scientific Software (Ashish Agarwal)

Day 2, Tutorials (September 23rd)
=================================

   Morning:
     - Parallel Programming in Haskell (Simon Peyton Jones, Simon
       Marlow, Manuel Chakravarty)
     - Systems Programming in Scala (Steven Jensen, Marius Eriksen)
   Afternoon:
     - The Snap framework for web applications in Haskell (Gregory
       Collins)
     - F# for the working functional programmer (Michael Sperber)

Day 3, Talks     (September 24th)
=================================

   Keynote
     Lennart Augustsson (Standard Chartered)

   Theorem-based derivation of an AES Implementation
     John Launchbury (Galois)
   
   Discrete Event Simulation using Erlang
     Olivier Boudeville (EDF)

   Model based testing of AUTOSAR automotive components
     Thomas Arts (Quviq)

   HTML5 web application development in OCaml
     Keigo Imai (IT Planning)

   Large-scale Internet Services in Scala at Twitter
     Steve Jenson and Wilhelm Bierbaum (Twitter)

   Applying Functional Programming to Build Platform-Independent
   Mobile Applications
     Adam Granicz (Intellifactory)

   Fourteen Days of Haskell: A Real Time Programming Project in Real
   Time
     Gregory Wright (Alcatel-Lucent)

   Disco: using Erlang to implement Mapreduce, Nokia
     Prashanth Mundkur and Ville Tuulos and Jared Flatow (Nokia)

   Functional mzScheme DSLs in Game Development
     Dan Liebgold (Naughty Dog)

   OCaml and Acunu Experience Report
     Tom Wilkie and Andrew Byde (Acunu)

There will be no published proceedings, as the meeting is intended to 
be more a discussion forum than a technical interchange, but videos
of all the talks will be placed online after the event. 

For more information, including presentation abstracts  and the most
recent schedule information, visit:

   http://cufp.org

See you there! 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Linear Scan Register Allocator for ocamlopt/ocamlnat</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-08/msg00000.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Benedikt Meurer announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
As mentioned earlier we have a student working on an implementation of the 
Linear Scan Register Allocator [1] for ocamlopt (and thereby ocamlnat). It 
took some time, but now there's a first working patch which looks promising. 
This work is done by Marcell Fischbach as part of his diploma thesis. The 
idea is to use the linear scan algorithm to drive the register allocation in 
the native top-level ocamlnat at some point, as suggested by Fabrice Le 
Fessant [2].

Marcell is now working to implement a proof-of-concept of an inline assembler 
for ocamlnat on i386 based on code from Alain Frisch an Fabrice Le Fessant. 
The result will also be contributed once ready, and will be used to 
effectively compare ocamlnat and the byte-code ocaml top-level.

The linear scan implementation reuses as much of the existing ocamlopt 
functionality as possible, so additional maintenance overhead should be 
manageable. Comments and suggestions are welcome of course. Please keep 
Marcell CC'ed with any replies as he's not subscribed to the list.

greets,
Benedikt


[1] http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=330250
[2] 
http://caml.inria.fr/pub/ml-archives/caml-list/2010/11/a1b0ed0934ff51df4ac07c5e9da6e9d6.en.html

(Please see the archive link for the attached file.)
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Benedikt Meurer then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Mantis ticket created: http://caml.inria.fr/mantis/view.php?id=5324
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Scherer asked and Benedikt Meurer replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; This work is meant to make a compromise between generated code quality
&gt; and compilation speed to have good performances in rapid
&gt; prototyping/development scenario.
&gt; 
&gt; Do you have more precise measurements on
&gt; - the relative costs of the successive transformations during native
&gt; compilation (including external linking etc.)? Which proportion of
&gt; time is currently used for register allocation?

Right now most of the time in ocamlnat is spent in waiting for the assembler 
and linker to finish and the runtime linker to load the generated library 
file. However there are no precise timing results yet.

Marcell did a rough test with ocamlopt last week, building the test suite 
with both graph coloring and linear scan on a 2009 iMac (Core 2 Duo). The 
overall time spent in the register allocator dropped from 28s to 8s.

&gt; - the performance cost of this new allocator in the generated code? I
&gt; suppose the results may vary between different architectures (eg. x86
&gt; is probably more sensitive to good allocation decisions than x86_64).

Same here... not yet. From what I've seen, the generated amd64 code is really 
close to the graph coloring code (isomorphic up to register renaming in most 
cases). Dunno for i386 yet.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Wojciech Meyer said and Benedikt Meurer replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; It's also worth to note that there is some generic mid/back-end code ready, 
&gt; in my OCaml native compiler framework called DragonKit in a spirit of LLVM, 
&gt; which I am currently actively working on. It's already able to express a 
&gt; toy language and JIT compile and run it within the same process on top of 
&gt; x86 architecture:
&gt; 
&gt; The code includes:
&gt; - SSA based IL using polymorphic variants
&gt; - monadic code generator
&gt; - plugable passes using first class modules
&gt; - very ad-hoc register allocator
&gt; - X86 backend
&gt; - example that evolved from LLVM kaleidoscope ported to DragonKit to 
&gt; Pascal/ML like language, and another example using direct translation to 
&gt; X86 backend.
&gt; 
&gt; The code is functorised and almost purely functional (with few exceptions 
&gt; where there is no benefit of doing that).
&gt; 
&gt; Maybe it could have some use in your new toplevel, or maybe it would be 
&gt; worth to reuse some of your work in DragonKit (or viceversa).
&gt; 
&gt; I welcome anybody wanting to join me in this effort.
&gt; 
&gt; Please take a look at:
&gt; 
&gt; http://www.github.com/danmey/DragonKit

I doubt that this would be applicable in the context of ocamlopt. What we are 
heading for is simply a way to avoid the external as and ld invocations by 
doing the work in-process. Code generation is done already, we just replace 
the last phase (see emit.ml).

BTW: On a related note, we also have a student working on a LLVM backend for 
ocamlopt as part of his bachelor thesis, which may be related to what you do.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ocaml puzzles</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa-roc.inria.fr/wws/arc/caml-list/2011-07/msg00143.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>William Le Ferrand announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Last week, we were three friends experimenting an "ocaml hackathon" :
we met and we built a simple webservice where you can either post
problems or try to solve them.

It's now online at http://www.baoug.org and the code is released at
https://github.com/baoug/ocaml-challenges . It's an 100% ocsigen 2.0
website, leveraging the newest features of the framework
(client/server interactions, message bus, etc ..)

Although baoug.org is still lacking a lot of features (syntax
highlighting, client side code checking, solution ranking, etc etc),
we hope that it can already provide at least as much fun as we got
when we wrote it. Actually, it's already waiting for your challenges
:)

This website is also the seminal event of baoug, the Bay Area OCaml
User Group. We plan to organize some ocaml events here; the next one
will be another hackathon to improve on baoug (if we get some feedback
from you all!); we're based in California but everyone is invited, as
we can get remote contributions. So far we're three, Marc Simon, Mike
Well an I (William Le Ferrand), but we'll grow up, hopefully.

If you want to contribute to the platform or if you have some ideas
for fresh features, please get in touch !

If you want to get more information about ocsigen and the way we
leverage it, please don't hesitate either.

What about posting a little challenge on www.baoug.org now :) ?
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>William Le Ferrand later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
By the way, we have a dedicated mailing-list for the Bay Area OCaml
User Group (actually it's a google group)
http://groups.google.com/group/baoug
Feel free to register to stay tuned; we'll organize a new meeting in
the coming weeks.

Many thanks to Cedric for his challenge on www.baoug.org ; who'll be
the next poster :) ?
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>rixed suggested and William Le Ferrand replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; To make this a little more fun, you should add scores :
&gt; you'd earn points when solving puzzles and also when contestants
&gt; fail to solve yours.

Right; there is now a "top 5" of best solvers per problem, but we can
add a real gaming dimension. That's stuff for a new hackathon :)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocamlcore.org/&gt;.

Opportunity:
  &lt;http://blog.camlcity.org/blog/search1.html&gt;

Rethinking Univ:
  &lt;http://ocaml.janestcapital.com/?q=node/95&gt;

Functional circular doubly linked lists:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/fcdll/&gt;

Time to register for CUFP!:
  &lt;http://ocaml.janestcapital.com/?q=node/94&gt;

Objective Caml renamed to OCaml:
  &lt;http://caml.inria.fr/ocaml/name.en.html&gt;

utop:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/utop/&gt;

Definability and extensionality of the modulus of continuity functional:
  &lt;http://math.andrej.com/2011/07/27/definability-and-extensionality-of-the-modulus-of-continuity-functional/&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
