<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2013.06.25</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2013.06.18</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2013.07.02</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>June 18 to 25, 2013</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>0.3 release of dolog</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2013-06/msg00121.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>François Berenger announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
A new version is available in OPAM:
# opam list dolog
dolog 0.3 the dumb, but colorful, OCaml logger

The only new feature is that logging levels
can be colored in unix terminals.

The feature is turned off by default
(for compatibility, because it won't
work everywhere and also because it is a little toyish).

The API is there:
https://github.com/UnixJunkie/dolog/blob/master/log.mli
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>The HoTT book</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2013-06/msg00125.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Oliver announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The HoTT book

http://audrey.fmf.uni-lj.si/hott.html
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Anonymous sum types in functors</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2013-06/msg00131.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>David Allsopp asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I couldn't think of a better way to describe what I'm trying to do, so
forgive the possibly strange subject!

In:

module IntSet = Set.Make(struct type t = int let compare = compare end)

the resulting signature is:

sig
  type elt = int
  type t
  ...

but in:

module FlagSet = Set.Make(struct type t = A | B let compare = compare end)

the resulting signature is:

sig
  type elt
  type t
  ...

i.e. the constructors are hidden (I can see why, but presumably it is a
special case in the type checker?) and the module is essentially useless. I
don't want to define the type external to the module - the idea is that I'd
be able to write Flag1Set.add Flag1Set.CommonFlag Flag1Set.empty and
Flag2Set.add Flag2Set.CommonFlag Flag2Set.empty, etc.

I can work around this by writing:

module FlagSet =
  struct
    type flag = A | B
    include Set.Make(struct type t = flag let compare = compare end)
  end

where the resulting signature is:

sig
  type flag = A | B
  type elt = flag
  type t
  ...

but I'm wondering:

a) Is there a way to do it where you can end up with type elt = A | B (I
think the answer is no?)

b) Is there a syntactically lighter way to write the module definition?
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Xavier Leroy replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; a) Is there a way to do it where you can end up with type elt = A | B (I
&gt; think the answer is no?)

No, because that wouldn't quite respect the generativity of sum type
definitions, but you can get close, see below.

&gt; b) Is there a syntactically lighter way to write the module definition?

I would recommend naming your anonymous "struct":

module Flag = struct
  type t = A | B
  let compare = compare
  (* Other useful operations over flags, e.g. *)
  let to_string = function A -&gt; "A" | B -&gt; "B"
end

module FlagSet = Set.Make(Flag)

Then you get

FlagSet: sig
  type elt = Flag.t
  type t
  ...
end

The good thing about this solution is that it gives you a natural
place to put additional operations over flags, like "to_string" above,
shall you ever need them.

&gt; the idea is that I'd
&gt; be able to write Flag1Set.add Flag1Set.CommonFlag Flag1Set.empty and
&gt; Flag2Set.add Flag2Set.CommonFlag Flag2Set.empty, etc.

Why not "Flag1Set.add Flag1.CommonFlag Flag1Set.empty"? Flags morally
come from Flag1, not from Flag1Set.

As an aside, some ML-like module systems require functor arguments to
be module names or paths, e.g. Coq's. OCaml accepts anonymous structs
as arguments, and does the best it can with them, but if the struct
contains generative type definitions, some information is necessarily
lost.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Xavier described the official solution.
However, since 3.12 you can also do some trickery.
This is going to be heavier, so this is probably a bad idea, but if you really need it, here it is:

module FlagSet = struct
  type elt = A | B
  include (Set.Make (struct type t = elt let compare = compare end) : Set.S with type elt := elt)
end
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocaml on windows</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2013-06/msg00138.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Bikal Gurung asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am looking to use ocaml to implement a project for my employer. However, the
environment is Windows OS. I am using cygwin and so far it seems to work but
curious on experiences others have on using ocaml on windows - both as a
development and deployment platform. Also has anyone tried using opam on
windows? Does it work?
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Later in the thread, Bikal Gurung said and Jonathan Protzenko replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Thank you for your response. I have installed the official windows
&gt; port of ocaml at http://protz.github.io/ocaml-installer/ . However, it
&gt; mentions that MinGW/Msys is no longer supported. I rather use
&gt; Mingw/Msys as well.
There are quite a few things that make working with msys painful, which 
is the reason why I switched the installer to cygwin. The installer 
still is a 32-bit native windows program, and still generates 32-bit 
native windows programs. It's just that cygwin is an easy way to get a 
toolchain and a unix-like development environment, which ocaml kind of 
needs in order to work right (without it, you only get bytecode 
compilation).
- The main problem is that OCaml is, by default, configured to search 
executables from the toolchain with the i686-pc-mingw-whatever prefix, 
that is, the one that the mingw-w64 compilers have, when installed 
through cygwin.
- The second biggest problem is with flexdll which, IIRC, hardcodes the 
use of the mingw-w64 compilers (32-bit compilers from the mingw-w64 
project). Msys, on the other hand, uses the mingw compilers (the 
original mingw project), and the location of the libraries / 
executables is slightly different, or maybe flexdll doesn't auto-detect 
the right locations for crt2.o and friends, meaning it's painful as you 
have to manually export FLEXLINKFLAGS. At some point, it became almost 
impossible to have that combination working. I think flexdll started to 
hardcode the i686-pc-mingw prefix at some point, and there's no 
ready-made, easy to install mingw-w64/msys bundle available, as far as 
I know.
- OCamlbuild relies on bash being available in the path to run its 
external commands ; an easy way to have this is to have a cygwin 
development environment. This is a know issue that no one has stepped 
up to fix on windows.
- Finally, the quoting conventions, IIRC, are subtly different between 
mingw/msys and cygwin, and OCaml is tailored to cygwin.

For all these reasons, cygwin sounds like a better choice for you 
working environment on windows. But I believe msys is still possible. 
If there's something that prevents you from having it work properly, I 
think we (the team) would be happy to know about it.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Adrien Nader then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; - The second biggest problem is with flexdll which, IIRC, hardcodes the 
&gt; use of the mingw-w64 compilers (32-bit compilers from the mingw-w64 
&gt; project). Msys, on the other hand, uses the mingw compilers (the 
&gt; original mingw project), and the location of the libraries / 
&gt; executables is slightly different, or maybe flexdll doesn't auto-detect 
&gt; the right locations for crt2.o and friends, meaning it's painful as you 
&gt; have to manually export FLEXLINKFLAGS. At some point, it became almost 
&gt; impossible to have that combination working. I think flexdll started to 
&gt; hardcode the i686-pc-mingw prefix at some point, and there's no 
&gt; ready-made, easy to install mingw-w64/msys bundle available, as far as 
&gt; I know.

Well, msys doesn't really require one toolchain or another: you can have
mingw-w64 (either i686-w64-mingw32 or x86_64-w64-mingw32) with msys
afaik.
However msys comes from mingw.org which is the "main" site for
i686-pc-mingw32 so that doesn't make things very balanced.

Note that there is a very recent "MSYS2" project which is updated in
pretty much every respect (newer GCC, forked from a newer Cygwin which
has 64b support, ...). It's very very recent and might become a variant
of cygwin but so far there are differences in the behaviour wanted from
it compared to cygwin which means that having the two of them merged
will involve some work and discussions.

&gt; - OCamlbuild relies on bash being available in the path to run its 
&gt; external commands ; an easy way to have this is to have a cygwin 
&gt; development environment. This is a know issue that no one has stepped 
&gt; up to fix on windows.

Cygwin, or msys.

However with msys you need bash and coreutils (ocamlbuild uses "cp" in a
few places for instance, but that's trivial to fix) and all the deps
(regex, termcap, and several others).
An "easy" way to install msys would probably be mingw-get from
mingw.org, which for its default repos would use the toolchain from
mingw.org too (fun stuff).

Btw, the issue is that windows' exec*() functions take an array of
strings, then merges all these strings and had that new string to the
process on startup. This means that in order to have the arguments split
as you had hoped them to be, you need to apply some rules (which I don't
have at hand right now).

Generally speaking, I'd like to have some more code in mingw-w64 to
alleviate the need for bash.

&gt; - Finally, the quoting conventions, IIRC, are subtly different between 
&gt; mingw/msys and cygwin, and OCaml is tailored to cygwin.

Can you elaborate on that? I've used msys for ocaml in the past and
haven't had issues.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>David Allsopp also replied to Bikal Gurung's question</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Thank you for your response. I have installed the official windows port of 
&gt; ocaml at
&gt; http://protz.github.io/ocaml-installer/ . However, it mentions that 
&gt; MinGW/Msys is no longer supported.
&gt; I rather use Mingw/Msys as well.

I meant I use the MinGW port of the compiler rather than the MSVC port - I 
compile it using the mingw-w64 compilers provided with Cygwin. I only use 
Cygwin to compile OCaml and related libraries (again, principally for 
historical reasons, I develop using a normal command shell with GnuWin32 to 
provide Unix commands). Building using Cygwin (i.e. the supported way) has 
the benefit that when you get stuck, others are likely to (be able to) help! 
:o) Do you have a particular to want to use MSYS rather than Cygwin?

&gt; It seems ocamlbuild requires cygwin to work, has this been your experience 
&gt; too? If I build the latest
&gt; ocaml from trunk - 4.02dev+fp will ocaml and other tools/utilities still 
&gt; work on pure MingWg/Msys
&gt; environment?

Yes. Because I use GnuWin32 (which has its bin folder in my PATH) I prefer 
not to put C:\cygwin\bin in my PATH but symlink through the required 
utilities in C:\Dev\OCaml\bin (C:\Dev\OCaml is my installation root for 
OCaml) - my OCaml installation requires bash.exe (for ocamlbuild), cpp.exe 
(for ocamlnet) and i686-w64-mingw32-ar.exe + i686-w64-mingw32-as.exe + 
i686-w64-mingw32-dlltool.exe + i686-w64-mingw32-gcc.exe + 
i686-w64-mingw32-ranlib.exe for ocamlopt.

&gt; With regards to ocaml libraries, have you tried the Jane Street packages? 
&gt; Core, core_kernel ? 

No - I'd got the impression that their library was very Unix-oriented (though 
I think core_kernel may now address that?) Again, it's mainly laziness - I've 
been using OCaml for long enough that I already have my own core library so 
while switching to a supported one may be great, nothing's broken (yet!). The 
libraries I do use are: findlib, extlib, calendar, pcre, csv, batteries, 
pgocaml, camlzip, ssl, cryptokit, ocamlnet, json-wheel, json-static, 
spiderCaml, ocamlsha, ocamldap with natively compiled C libraries (for 
openssl, zlib, etc.) where appropriate.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Adrien Nader said and Gerd Stolpmann replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; I believe opam on windows is pretty far away.
&gt; 
&gt; The issues can be summarized in a few words: source-based package
&gt; manager for ocaml on pure windows.
&gt; For this to fully work, you need a perfect toolchain where everything
&gt; works wonderfully.

I can quickly report what I did to get GODI working on Windows. It is  
of course not "pure Windows": You need Cygwin for doing builds, but  
that's "only" because almost all build utilities are Unix-ish, and it  
would be very hard to build anything without having some shell and the  
usual file utilities at hand. (AFAIK the only build utility that works  
in a pure Windows environment is omake.)

So GODI assumes a mixed Windows environment, and this is in deed  
doable. ocaml and all compiled code run on native Windows here, and for  
executing build scripts there is Cygwin. This solves the utility  
question, but you get in return some new problems, like the different  
calling conventions. All GODI core utilities have e.g. built-in support  
for translating Cygwin paths forth and back, so they can operate on  
Cygwin paths although they are native Windows programs. Another problem  
are the strange Windows rules for splitting a command-line into words.  
As generic fallback when there are too many "bad characters" in the  
command line I simply generate a temporary script that is then executed  
with bash. There are probably more such tricks I currently do not  
remember.

So this mixed mode is actually doable, and works so well that many GODI  
packages can be built on Windows without any special porting effort. If  
you look at WODI, the special adaption of GODI for Windows, you will  
mostly find additional C libraries (because you cannot link against the  
libraries coming with Cygwin).

We could go further and replace Cygwin completely only if we had a  
substitute for the shell utilities. That's the core of the problem, and  
it's a hard one, because many scripts assume 100% POSIX behavior, and  
e.g. using Windows command-line conventions is out of question.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other Caml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the Caml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocaml.org/&gt;.

Forge downtime on 22/06 19:16 to 23/06 14:00 (UTC+0200):
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=879&gt;

Making it easier for beginners to learn OCaml:
  &lt;http://gallium.inria.fr/blog/making-it-easier-for-beginners-to-learn-ocaml&gt;

The HoTT book:
  &lt;http://math.andrej.com/2013/06/20/the-hott-book/&gt;

Senior software developer/Functional programmer at Vector Fabrics (Full-time):
  &lt;http://functionaljobs.com/jobs/154-senior-software-developer-functional-programmer-at-vector-fabrics&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
