<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2013.12.31</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2013.12.24</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2014.01.07</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>December 24 to 31, 2013</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml Labs activities in 2013</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2013-12/msg00202.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We've put together a review of most of the activities that we've done at
OCaml Labs in Cambridge during our first year in 2013, available at:

http://anil.recoil.org/2013/12/29/the-year-in-ocamllabs.html

This will also be mirrored at the OCaml Labs homepage:
http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/projects/ocamllabs/

Thanks again to all our collaborators for making this such a productive
and enjoyable 2013, and we wish everyone a happy and prosperous 2014.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Lablqt</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2013-12/msg00203.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this two weeks old thread, Vsevolod Velichko said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
As I was the beta-tester of the lablqml, I can share some of my
experience :)

I've written an example[1] that creates a couple of views on top of
OCaml-created data models, emits signals from OCaml, calls OCaml
callbacks from QML and so on. It can be taken into account as some proof
of concept.

At first, as Dmitry said there's some simple hardcoded startup, but it
was added on behalf of my request (I wanted one to be able to use GUI
without writing any line of C++ code). However one can still put their
own startup in C++.

Second, the developer still must deal with C++ compilation and linking
OCaml object files with C++ ones. AFAIK, Dmitry intends to improve the
process in some future, but currently it a bit tricky. I haven't tried
native OCaml build systems (such as ocamlbuild or omake) with it yet,
but using the Makefile one can see, that they have to manually resolve
all the Qt libraries to link with.

Third, there're still some issues. E.g. creating the data item object
used in view, I was unable to create a mutable property that can be used
on top level of delegate[2] so I had to expose[3] the object itself and
access its property, otherwise property changes weren't revealed to QML.

But anyway while lablqt is still to be considered as some beta release,
I claim that it is already more usable than e.g. lablgtk.

[1] https://github.com/torkve/melange-seawar
[2] https://github.com/torkve/melange-seawar/blob/master/gui.qml#L85
[3] https://github.com/torkve/melange-seawar/blob/master/gui.ml#L43
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the OCaml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocaml.org/&gt;.

Costa's minimal surface with PovRay:
  &lt;http://math.andrej.com/2013/12/30/costas-minimal-surface-with-povray/&gt;

Announcing a new OCaml library for the Adafruit Raspberry Pi RGB LCD!:
  &lt;http://gallium.inria.fr/blog/raspi-lcd&gt;

Reviewing the first year of OCaml Labs in 2013:
  &lt;http://anil.recoil.org/2013/12/29/the-year-in-ocamllabs.html&gt;

Haskell : The Problem with Integer.:
  &lt;http://www.mega-nerd.com/erikd/Blog/CodeHacking/Haskell/integer_pt1.html&gt;

OCaml EFL 1.8.0 released:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=893&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
