<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2014.06.03</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2014.05.27</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2014.06.10</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>May 27 to June 03, 2014</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>PG'OCaml 2.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-05/msg00174.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Dario Teixeira announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce version 2.0 of PG'OCaml, a library offering type-safe
access to PostgreSQL databases for OCaml applications.

This version no longer depends on Batteries, which hopefully will entice more
Core users to give it a spin. Below is the list of the remaining changes,
straight from the changelog:

  * Dario Teixeira and Jacques-Pascal Deplaix: fixing issues with arrays.
    This requires all array types to change from 'a array to 'a option array,
    which breaks backward compatibility.
  * Dario Teixeira's patch making PostgreSQL's NUMERIC type be converted
    to/from OCaml strings.  This change is not backward's compatible,
    requiring a bump in the major version number (though there seems
    to be no actual code in the wild relying on the previous behaviour).
  * Dario Teixeira's patch adding function 'uuid', which exposes the
    unique connection handle identifier.
  * Jacques-Pascal Deplaix's patches adding 'catch', 'transact', 'alive',
    'inject', and 'alter' functions.

Note that a couple of changes break backward compatibility, hence the new
major version number.  These changes were required to fix some long-standing
issues, so I trust you'll be understanding.

This new release should be hitting OPAM soon.  Alternatively,
you can grab the source from the project's homepage:
http://pgocaml.forge.ocamlcore.org/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Why AVL-tree?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-06/msg00010.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yoriyuki Yamagata asked and Xavier Leroy replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Just from the curiosity, why balanced binary trees used in Set and
&gt; Map are AVL-trees, not their alternative, say, red-black trees?  Is
&gt; there a deep reason for it, or just a historical one?

At the time Set was written, no efficient algorithms for whole-set
operations (union, intersection, difference, etc) were known for
red-black trees.  I'm not sure they are known today.

As for performance of insert/lookup operations, Jean-Christophe
Filliâtre has measurements showing that OCaml's 2-imbalance AVL trees
perform better than red-black trees.  It all depends on your ratio of
insertions to lookups, of course.  But the 2-imbalance trick makes a
big difference with textbook AVL trees.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the OCaml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocaml.org/&gt;.

OCaml 4.02.0-beta:
  &lt;http://wodi.forge.ocamlcore.org/2014/05/31/ocaml-4.02beta.html&gt;

PG'OCaml 2.0 released:
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=901&gt;

PG'OCaml 2.0 has been released:
  &lt;http://rwmj.wordpress.com/2014/05/28/pgocaml-2-0-has-been-released/&gt;

Announcing PG'OCaml 2.0:
  &lt;http://nleyten.com/post/2014/05/28/Announcing-PG-OCaml-2.0&gt;

Full Time: Software Developer (Functional Programming) at Jane Street in New York, NY; London, UK; Hong Kong:
  &lt;http://jobs.github.com/positions/0a9333c4-71da-11e0-9ac7-692793c00b45&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
