<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2014.07.08</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2014.07.01</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2014.07.15</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 01 to 08, 2014</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Toplevel and syntax extension</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00008.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Philippe Veber asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Consider the following script:

#use "topfind";;
#camlp4o;;
#require "sexplib.syntax";;

open Sexplib.Std;;

type t = int with sexp;;

Saved as script.ml, the simple call:

ocaml script.ml

fails while the call:

cat script.ml | ocaml

succeeds. Any idea how I could fix the first call?
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>David Sheets then asked and Philippe Veber replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; How does the first call fail? A difference between the two is that, in
&gt; the second, the .ocamlinit file is used. If you are using opam with
&gt; ocamlfind installed via it, this file will contain your Topdirs setup.
&gt; You can try:
&gt; 
&gt; let () =
&gt;   try Topdirs.dir_directory (Sys.getenv "OCAML_TOPLEVEL_PATH")
&gt;   with Not_found -&gt; ()
&gt; ;;
&gt; 
&gt; at the top of your script (after hashbang but before directives).

The first call fails with a syntax error on "with sexp":

[pbil:~ 18:58]$cat rien.ml
let () =
try Topdirs.dir_directory (Sys.getenv "OCAML_TOPLEVEL_PATH")
with Not_found -&gt; ()
;;

#use "topfind";;
#camlp4o;;
#require " sexplib.syntax";;

open Sexplib.Std;;

type t = int with sexp;;

[pbil:~ 18:58]$ocaml rien.ml
File "rien.ml", line 12, characters 13-17:
Error: Syntax error

It seems like the sexp syntax extension is not loaded when the script
is evaluated. But it's not really clear to me what going wrong...
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Fabrice Le Fessant then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
If I remember well, I think "ocaml" has a different behavior depending
on what it reads from: 
* From a pipe, it parses every sentence and execute each one
immediatly. 
* From a file, it tries to parse the whole file, and then executes
everything. 

In the second case, it means it will only execute the load of the
syntax extension after parsing the whole file... which will fail,
since the syntax extension is needed for that.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Philippe Veber then asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks Fabrice, this perfectly explains what I observe. Is this
behavior considered the right one? Reading from a pipe is regretfully
not an option for me, as my script has command line arguments. Hence
when I type:

cat script.ml | ocaml --foo --bar 1

the toplevel complains it knows nothing about the arguments foo and
bar. A "--" argument would be useful but it seems not available. If
it's so, I'll file a feature request on Mantis, since without it,
there seems to be no way to give a script to the toplevel that both
takes command line arguments and uses a syntax extension.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Fabrice Le Fessant replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
You might want to split your file in two different files, a loader and
the body:

peerocaml:~% cat &gt; script_body.ml
open Sexplib.Std;;
type t = int with sexp;;
peerocaml:~% cat &gt; script.ml
#use "topfind";;
#camlp4o;;
#require "sexplib.syntax";;
#use "script_body.ml"
peerocaml:~% ocaml script.ml
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Romain Bardou also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
You could write a wrapper which start the ocaml process, sends a string
containing something like:

module Sys =
struct
  include Sys
  let argv = ... (* fill this *)
end

to the ocaml process (replace the ... by the arguments given to the
wrapper, using the array syntax, and don't forget that the first cell
must contain the executable path), and then pass the contents of your
script.ml.

This does not work if your script uses other modules which themselves
use Sys.argv.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Ashish Agarwal also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Yet another option is to use ocamlscript. The following works:

$ cat script.ml
#! /usr/bin/env ocamlscript
Ocaml.ocamlflags := ["-thread"];
Ocaml.packs := ["sexplib.syntax"]
--
open Sexplib.Std
type t = int with sexp

$ ./script.ml
(* compiles without error *)
      </cwn_what>
   </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml 2014 Call for Participation</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00028.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We have now a preliminary program for OCaml 2014,
co-located with ICFP 2014 in Gothenburg, on September 5.

We invite you to register for the workshop from the ICFP site:
	http://icfpconference.org/icfp2014/

You can find the up-to-date program at: http://ocaml.org/meetings/ocaml/2014/
Note that this year we are working in close cooperation with the
ML Family workshop: http://okmij.org/ftp/ML/ML14.html

Jacques Garrigue
-----

OCaml 2014 - Preliminary Program

09:00-09:10 - Welcome

09:10-10:00 - Runtime system

Multicore OCaml, by Stephen Dolan, Leo White, Anil Madhavapeddy
(University of Cambridge)

Ephemerons meet OCaml GC, by François Bobot (CEA)

10:25-11:20 - Tools and libraries

Introduction to 0install, by Thomas Leonard (University of Cambridge)

Transport Layer Security purely in OCaml (*), by Hannes Mehnert
(University of Cambridge), David Kaloper Meršinjak (University of
Nottingham)

OCamlOScope: a New OCaml API Search (*), by Jun Furuse (Standard
Chartered Bank, Singapore)

11:40-12:30 - OCaml News

The State of OCaml (invited), Xavier Leroy (INRIA Paris-Rocquencourt)

The OCaml Platform v1.0, by Anil Madhavapeddy (C), Amir Chaudhry (C),
Jeremie Diminio (JS), Thomas Gazagnaire (C), Louis Gesbert (OCamlPro),
Thomas Leonard (C), David Sheets (C), Mark Shinwell (JS), Leo White
(C), Jeremy Yallop (C); (C = University of Cambridge, JS = Jane
Street).

12:30-14:00 - Lunch

14:00-14:55 - Language

A Proposal for Non-Intrusive Namespaces in OCaml, by Pierrick Couderc
(I), Fabrice Le Fessant (I+O), Benjamin Canou (O), Pierre Chambart
(O); (I = INRIA, O = OCamlPro)

Improving Type Error Messages in OCaml (*), by Arthur Charguéraud
(INRIA &amp; Université Paris Sud)

Github Pull Requests for OCaml development: a field report (*), by
Gabriel Scherer (INRIA)

15:10-16:30 - Joint Poster Session (with ML Family workshop)

Core.Sequence: a unified interface for sequences, by Nicolas Oury
(Jane Street)

Irminsule; a branch-consistent distributed library database, by Thomas
Gazagnaire (C), Amir Chaudhry (C), Anil Madhavapeddy (C), Richard
Mortier (University of Nottingham), David Scott (Citrix System), David
Sheets (C), Gregory Tsipenyuk (C), Jon Crowcroft (C); (C = University
of Cambridge)

A Case for Multi-Switch Constraints in OPAM, by Fabrice Le Fessant
(INRIA)

LibreS3: design, challenges, and steps toward reusable libraries, by
Edwin Török (Skylable Ltd.)

Nullable Type Inference, by Michel Mauny and Benoit Vaugon
(ENSTA-ParisTech)

16:30-17:50 - Applications

Coq of OCaml, by Guillaume Claret (Université Paris Diderot)

High Performance Client-Side Web Programming with SPOC and Js of ocaml
(*), by Mathias Bourgoin and Emmmanuel Chailloux (Université Pierre et
Marie Curie)

Using Preferences to Tame your Package Manager, Roberto Di Cosmo
(D+I), Pietro Abate (D), Stefano Zacchiroli (D), Fabrice Le Fessant
(I), Louis Gesbert (OCamlPro); (D = Université Paris Diderot, I =
INRIA)

Simple, efficient, sound-and-complete combinator parsing for all
context-free grammars, using an oracle (*), by Tom Ridge (University
of Leicester)

17:50 - Closing

(*) short presentation
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Cmdliner 0.9.5</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00030.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Daniel Bünzli announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'd like to announce the release of Cmdliner 0.9.5 which should be
available shortly in opam. See the release notes for details:

https://github.com/dbuenzli/cmdliner/blob/master/CHANGES.md

Cmdliner is an OCaml module for the declarative definition of command
line interfaces.

Home page: http://erratique.ch/software/cmdliner
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Immutable strings</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00031.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I've just posted a blog article where I criticize the new concept of
immutable strings that will be available in OCaml 4.02 (as option):

http://blog.camlcity.org/blog/bytes1.html

In short my point is that it the new concept is not far reaching enough,
and will even have negative impact on the code quality when it is not
improved. I also present three ideas how to improve it.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Anthony Tavener said and Gerd Stolpmann replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; It seems the "bytes" type would be most useful in cases where mutable and
&gt; immutable strings are used in a mixed manner... but given these practical
&gt; issues you raise, it could be less pleasant than it first appears. Your
&gt; "stringlike" solution seems reasonable, but I don't have a good use-case in
&gt; mind for mixed mutable/immutable to help me imagine the result. What are some
&gt; scenarios where this mix of types is desired? I think even Rust doesn't
&gt; support mutable strings -- which seems bold for its target audience, yet
&gt; they're fine with it?

I've mostly buffers in mind, as you need them for block-by-block I/O.
Actually, I started thinking about this issue when looking again at
OCamlnet, and how I could use "bytes" there. It's a hard case, lots of
buffers of different types, and you really run into the problems I
sketched in the article, as it is a common operation to copy the
contents of one buffer into the other.

That's also why I'm suggesting to use bigarrays - for interfacing with C
these are much easier to use as buffers, as bigarrays are just malloc'ed
memory and cannot be moved around by the GC. (And the C interface is
needed for I/O.)

So my scenario is quite low-level: I/O, and C interfaces.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Alain Frisch answered the original post and Gerd Stolpmann replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Thanks for your interesting post.  Your general point about not breaking 
&gt; backward compatibility at the source level, as long as only "basic" 
&gt; features are used, is important. ... Even if we look only at 
&gt; industrial adoption, OCaml compete with languages more recently designed 
&gt; and if we cannot touch revisit existing choices, the risk is real for 
&gt; OCaml to appear "frozen", less modern, and a less compelling choice for 
&gt; new projects.  This needs to be balanced against the risk of putting off 
&gt; owners of "passive" code bases (on which no dedicated development team 
&gt; work on a regular basis, but which need to be marginally modified and 
&gt; re-compiled once in a while).

It will create confusion even with actively maintained code bases. What
could help here is very clear communication when the change will be the
standard behavior, and how the migration will take place. Currently, it
feels like a big experiment - hey, let's users tentatively enable it,
and watch out for problems. That's quite naive. In particular, users
hitting problems will probably not try out the switch (or immediately
revert), because leaving the code base in a non-buildable state for
longer time is not an option. (And ignoring these users would not be
good, because it's exactly these users who are really doing string
mutation who could profit at most from the change.)

&gt; Concerning immutable strings, the migration path seems quite good to me: 
&gt; a warning tells you about direct uses of string-mutation features (such 
&gt; as String.set), and the default behavior does not break existing code. 

That's good for now, but I'm more expecting something like: next ocaml
version it is experimental (interfaces may still evolve). The following
version it is recommended standard and we'll emit a warning when
-safe-strings is not on. The version after that we'll make -safe-strings
the default, etc. Something like that. There could also be a section in
the manual explaining the new behavior, and how to convert code.

&gt; FWIW, it was a matter of hours to go through the entire LexiFi's code 
&gt; base to enable the new safe mode, and as always in such operations, it 
&gt; was a good opportunity to factorize similar code.  And Jane Street does 
&gt; not seem overly worried by the task ( see 
&gt; https://blogs.janestreet.com/ocaml-4-02-everything-else/ ).

With my current customer, I don't see any bigger problems either,
because string mutation doesn't play a big role there (it's a compiler
project). I see a big problem with OCamlnet, though, as it is focused on
I/O, and the issue how to deal with buffers is quite central.

&gt; As one of the problems with the current solution, you mention that 
&gt; conversion of strings to bytes and vice versa requires a copy, which 
&gt; incurs some performance penalty.  This is true, but the new system can 
&gt; also avoid a lot of string copying (in safe mode).  ...
&gt;  (Many libraries don't do such copy, and, in the good cases, 
&gt; mention in their documentation that the strings should be treated as 
&gt; immutable ones by the caller.  This is clearly a source of possibly 
&gt; tricky bugs.)

Right, that's the good side of it. (Although the danger is quite
theoretical, as most programmers seem to intuitively follow the rule
"don't mutate strings you did not create". I've never seen this kind of
bug in practice.)

&gt; Your second idea is to create a common supertype of both string and 
&gt; bytes, to be used in contexts which can consume either type.  A minor 
&gt; variantiation would be to introduce a third abstract type, with 
&gt; "identity" injection from byte and string to it, and to expose the 
&gt; "read-only" part of the string API on it.    This can entirely be 
&gt; implemented in user-land (although it could benefit from being in the 
&gt; stdlib, so that e.g. Lexing could expose a from_stringlike).

I think it would be quite important to have that in the stdlib:

 - This sets a standard for interoperability between libraries
 - The stdlib can exploit the details of the representation
 - It would be possible to use stringlike directly in C interfaces

For instance, there is one module in OCamlnet where a regexp is directly
run on an I/O buffer (generally, you need to do some primitive parsing
on I/O buffers before you can extract strings, and that's where
stringlike would be nice to have). Without stringlike, I would have to
replace that regexp somehow.

&gt;    Another 
&gt; variant of it is to see "stringlike" as a type class, implemented with 
&gt; explicit dictionaries.  This could be done with records:
&gt; 
&gt;    type 'a stringlike = {
&gt;      get: 'a -&gt; int -&gt; char;
&gt;      length: 'a -&gt; int;
&gt;      sub_string: 'a -&gt; int -&gt; int -&gt; string;
&gt;      output: out_channel -&gt; 'a -&gt; unit;
&gt;      ...
&gt;    }
&gt; 
&gt; There would be two constant records "string stringlike" and "bytes 
&gt; stringlike", and functions accepting either kind of string would take an 
&gt; extra stringlike argument.  (Alternatively, one could use first class 
&gt; modules instead of records.)  There is some overhead related to the 
&gt; dynamic dispatch, but I'm not convinced this would be unacceptable. 

The overhead is quite low. If you need to call e.g. "get" several times,
you could factor out the dictionary lookup:

let get = stringlike.get in ...

The (only) price is that the access cannot be inlined anymore.

&gt; Your third idea (using char bigarrays) would then fit nicely in this 
&gt; approach.

Right, and it would even be possible to use that for other buffer
representations (e.g. I have a non-contiguous buffer type called
Netpagebuffer in OCamlnet that could also be compatible with stringlike;
also think of ring buffers). It's a really nice idea.

The downside is that I cannot imagine any easy way to support this in C
interfaces. Well, you could have

low_level_buffer : 'a -&gt; (Obj.t * int * int)

that gets you a base address, an offset, and a length, but that could be
too optimistic. Maybe C interfaces should simply dynamically check
whether 'a is a string or bigarray, and fail otherwise. These dynamic
checks are at least possible (maybe there could be a caml_stringlike_val
function that does its very best).

Another downside of this approach is that it introduces a lot of type
variables.

&gt; Another direction would be to support also the case of functions which 
&gt; can return either a bytes or a string.  A typical case is Bytes.sub / 
&gt; Bytes.sub_string.  One could also want Bytes.cat_to_string: bytes -&gt; 
&gt; bytes -&gt; string in addition to Bytes.cat: bytes -&gt; bytes -&gt; bytes.  For 
&gt; those cases, one could introduce a GADT such as:
&gt; 
&gt;   type _ is_a_string =
&gt;      | String: string is_a_string
&gt;      | Bytes: bytes is_a_string
&gt;      (* potentially more cases *)
&gt; 
&gt; You could then pass the desired constructor to the functions, e.g.: 
&gt; Bytes.sub: bytes -&gt; int -&gt; int -&gt; 'a is_a_string -&gt; 'a.  The cost of 
&gt; dispatching on the constructor is tiny, and the stdlib could bypass the 
&gt; test altogether using unsafe features internally.  Higher-level 
&gt; functions which can return either a string or a bytes are likely to 
&gt; produce the result by passing the is_a_string value down to lower-level 
&gt; functions.

That's also a nice idea, and it will definitely save a few string copies
here and there.

&gt;   But one could also imagine that some function behave 
&gt; differently according to the actual type of result.  For instance, a 
&gt; function which is likely to produce often the same strings could decide 
&gt; to keep a (weak) table of already returned strings, or to have a 
&gt; hard-coded list of common strings; this works only for immutable 
&gt; results, and so the function needs to check the is_a_string constructor 
&gt; to enable/disable these optimizations.  The "stringlike" idea could also 
&gt; be replaced by this is_a_string GADT, so that there could be a single 
&gt; function:
&gt; 
&gt;   val sub: 'a is_a_string -&gt; 'a -&gt; int -&gt; int -&gt; 'b is_a_string -&gt; 'b
&gt; 
&gt; 
&gt; All that said, I think the current situation is already a net 
&gt; improvement over the previous one, 

Well, I wouldn't say so because I'm missing good migration paths for
some important cases.

&gt; and that further layers can be built 
&gt; on top of it, if needed (and not necessarily in stdlib).

Well, as pointed out, I'd really like to see one such layer in stdlib,
because we'll otherwise have five different solutions in the library
scene which are all incompatible to each other. (Your type class
suggestion looks easy and will already solve most of the issues; why not
just include it into the stdlib, it wouldn't need much: a new module
Stringlike defining it, the records for String and Bytes and maybe char
Bigarrays, and some extensions here and there where it is used, e.g. in
Lexing.) IMHO, it is important to really provide practical solutions,
and not only to theoretically have one.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Markus Mottl answered the original post and Gerd Stolpmann replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; I agree that the new concept has some noteworthy downsides as
&gt; demonstrated in the Lexing-example.  Your proposed solution 2
&gt; (stringlike) would probably solve these issues from a safety point of
&gt; view.  The downside is that the complexity of string-handling would
&gt; increase even more, because then we would have three types to deal
&gt; with.  I personally prefer safety over convenience, but other people's
&gt; (especially beginner's) mileage may vary.

Well, the complexity can be reduced a bit by using phantom types:

type string = [`String] stringlike
type bytes = [`Bytes] stringlike

and then just define function-by-function what is permitted:

val get : 'a stringlike -&gt; int -&gt; char
val set : [`Bytes] stringlike -&gt; int -&gt; char -&gt; unit
val sub : 'a stringlike -&gt; int -&gt; int -&gt; [`String] stringlike
val sub_bytes : 'a stringlike -&gt; int -&gt; int -&gt; [`Bytes] stringlike

etc., and the modules String and Bytes would just contain aliases of
these functions with monomorphed typing.

I don't know, though, whether we can be safe to never see the
polymorphic typing when just using string and bytes. It would be a bit
surprising for beginners to see that, and you sometimes would have to
deal with unresolved type variables.

&gt; The Bigarray-approach doesn't seem appealing to me.  Strings are much
&gt; more lightweight, since they can be allocated cheaply on the
&gt; OCaml-heap.  E.g. String.create is about 10x-100x faster than
&gt; Bigarray.create.  That seems too big to ignore.

Oh, we ignore already that Unix.read and Unix.write copy all data
through an additional buffer because we cannot pass an OCaml string
directly to the OS while another thread could relocate this string. So
that copy would be eliminated. So I'd guess you are normally even faster
with bigarrays, at least when you only look at the use as I/O buffers.
But there might be other uses where this is different.	
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Indeed. Originally the plan was to use the above scheme for strings,
and use polymorphism to allow more flexibility. However, this is not
100% compatible, even if we allow to ignore the parameters, because
of these unresolved type variables. This also becomes complicated
when you want to take functions as parameters.

The stringlike type itself is a good idea.
In the standard library, it could be implemented as:
   type string = private stringlike
   type bytes = private stringlike
However, it is only about allowing passing string and bytes arguments
to functions in an homogeneous way.
For the return case, the situation is more confused, because returning
a stringlike is actually weaker than either bytes or string.
Alain’s idea of using an extra type-only parameter (‘a is_a_type) works,
and it doesn’t really need to be a GADT.
But this is a bit strange to use an extra parameter where a phantom type
on string itself would solve the problem. I.e., using your above approach
one can be safe just writing:
  val copy : ‘a stringlike -&gt; ‘b stringlike
  val sub : ‘a stringlike -&gt; int -&gt; int -&gt; ‘b stringlike
(assuming that we are always copying in sub too)

One could try to mix the two approaches: i.e. have a type ‘a stringlike,
with explicit coercions to and from bytes and string.
Note that you can do that yourself: create your own Stringlike module,
with the coercions
   type ’a stringlike
   external from_string : string -&gt; [&gt; `String] stringlike = “%identity"
   external to_string : [`String] stringlike -&gt; string = “%identity”
   …
Note that you should not write “type +’a stringlike”, since you want to exploit
the fact any stringlike must be monomorphic.
This could of course be added to the standard library, but for compatibility
reasons I think that string itself has to stay as an abstract (or private) type with
no parameter. And the above kind of coercions is compiled away, so if your
goal is performance this should not be a problem.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Alain Frisch then replied, and Jacques Garrigue said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; I mentioned that some functions could behave differently according
&gt; to the requested result type. For instance, a function
&gt;
&gt; val of_bool: 'a is_a_string -&gt; bool -&gt; 'a
&gt;
&gt; would return string literals when 'a = String and it would copy them
&gt; when 'a = Bytes. Similarly, a function could memoize some strings it
&gt; produces in order to return them later again, but only when 'a =
&gt; String, not 'a = Bytes.

I see. But in that case we could also have different functions, since
the semantics change (at least for physical equality)

&gt; Even for functions such as "copy" or "sub", it makes sense to avoid
&gt; a copy in some cases (when both the input and the output are
&gt; immutable, and for sub, when the range covers the entire input).

Ok, but in that case you will need a flag for both input and output
strings, since there is no way to recover this information from the
string itself.

&gt; So I don't think that "'a is_a_string" can really be only a phantom
&gt; type.

I see.
I think that both approaches have interesting applications.
But from a type system point of view they are clearly advanced.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ML Family workshop: First Call for Participation</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00039.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>oleg announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Higher-order, Typed, Inferred, Strict: ACM SIGPLAN ML Family Workshop
Thursday September 4, 2014, Gothenburg, Sweden

Call For Participation         http://okmij.org/ftp/ML/ML14.html

Early registration deadline is August 3. Please register at
https://regmaster4.com/2014conf/ICFP14/register.php

This workshop specifically aims to recognize the entire extended ML
family and to provide the forum to present and discuss common issues,
both practical (compilation techniques, implementations of concurrency
and parallelism, programming for the Web) and theoretical (fancy
types, module systems, metaprogramming). We also encourage
presentations from related languages (such as Scala, Rust, Nemerle,
ATS, etc.), to exchange experience of further developing ML ideas.

The workshop is conducted in close cooperation with the
OCaml Users and Developers Workshop  http://ocaml.org/meetings/ocaml/2014/
taking place on September 5.


Program

* Andreas Rossberg
    1ML -- core and modules as one (Or: F-ing first-class modules)

* Jacques Garrigue and Leo White
    Type-level module aliases: independent and equal

* Felix Klock and Nicholas Matsakis
    Demo: The Rust Language and Type System

* Tomas Petricek and Don Syme
    Doing web-based data analytics with F#

* Thomas Braibant, Jonathan Protzenko and Gabriel Scherer
    Well-typed generic smart-fuzzing for APIs

* Ramana Kumar, Magnus O. Myreen, Michael Norrish and Scott Owens
    Improving the CakeML Verified ML Compiler

* Leo White and Frederic Bour
    Modular implicits

* Nada Amin and Tiark Rompf
    Implicits in Practice

* Anil Madhavapeddy, Thomas Gazagnaire, David Scott and Richard Mortier
    Metaprogramming with ML modules in the MirageOS

* Katsuhiro Ueno and Atsushi Ohori
    Compiling SML# with LLVM: a Challenge of Implementing ML on a Common
    Compiler Infrastructure

* Akinori Abe and Eijiro Sumii
    A Simple and Practical Linear Algebra Library Interface
    with Static Size Checking

* John Reppy
    SML3d: 3D Graphics for Standard ML


In addition, the joint poster session with the OCaml workshop will take
place in the afternoon on September 5. The session will include
posters:

* Nicolas Oury
    Core.Sequence: a unified interface for sequences

* Thomas Gazagnaire, Amir Chaudhry, Anil Madhavapeddy, Richard Mortier, 
  David Scott, David Sheets, Gregory Tsipenyuk, Jon Crowcroft
    Irminsule: a branch-consistent distributed library database

* Michel Mauny and Benoit Vaugon
    Nullable Type Inference

* Edwin Toeroek
    LibreS3: design, challenges, and steps toward reusable libraries

* Fabrice Le Fessant
    A Case for Multi-Switch Constraints in OPAM


Program Committee

Kenichi Asai             Ochanomizu University, Japan
Matthew Fluet            Rochester Institute of Technology, USA
Jacques Garrigue         Nagoya University, Japan
Dave Herman              Mozilla, USA
Stefan Holdermans        Vector Fabrics, Netherlands
Oleg Kiselyov (Chair)    University of Tsukuba, Japan
Keiko Nakata             Tallinn University of Technology, Estonia
Didier Remy              INRIA Paris-Rocquencourt, France
Zhong Shao               Yale University, USA
Hongwei Xi               Boston University, USA
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ocaml-lz4 1.0.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00035.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Peter Zotov announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'd like to announce the package ocaml-lz4, containing bindings to LZ4,
a very fast lossless compression algorithm. The package will be shortly
available in OPAM.

The source code is available at &lt;https://github.com/whitequark/ocaml-lz4&gt;.
The documentation is published at
&lt;http://whitequark.github.io/ocaml-lz4/&gt;.

Unlike JaneStreet's existing "lz4" package (which is marked as
alpha-quality, exposes only an unsafe interface and has seen virtually
no changes since 2012), this binding exposes a safe interface,
supports 4.02 Bytes and has no runtime dependencies except cstubs.

These bindings can also serve as an example for implementation of very
fast FFI bindings using cstubs.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>capnp-ocaml 1.0.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2014-07/msg00042.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Paul Pelzl announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the first release of capnp-ocaml:
https://github.com/pelzlpj/capnp-ocaml

Cap'n Proto is a multi-language serialization framework which uses
code generation techniques in a manner similar to Protocol Buffers.
Its distinguishing feature is that there is no explicit
parsing/serialization step: the on-the-wire message format is also
designed to serve as an efficient in-memory data structure
representation.

The capnp-ocaml code generator plugin emits pure OCaml code which is
functorized over the underlying message format. At present, a 'bytes'-based
message format is provided for ease of use with file and socket I/O.
In the future, a Bigarray message format could be easily provided;
this would lend itself to a straightforward method for sending and
receiving messages via an mmap'd shared memory region.

Q: Why would I want to use this over sexplib/bin-prot?
A: These projects provide superior language-level integration, but
capnp-ocaml is a better choice if you care about language portability.

Q: Why would I want to use this over Protocol Buffers?
A: Cap'n Proto has the clear advantage of first-class sum types, which
are mapped to OCaml variants in a straightforward fashion. You also
find yourself intrigued by the potential for better performance and
zero-overhead shared-memory message passing.

capnp-ocaml is available on OPAM as package "capnp".
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Peter Zotov then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I want to note that ppx_protobuf provides an efficient mapping for
OCaml's sum types, which would map to most well-designed protocols
naturally.

  https://github.com/whitequark/ppx_protobuf#variants
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the OCaml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocaml.org/&gt;.

Mirage 1.2 released and the 2.0 runup begins:
  &lt;http://openmirage.org/blog/mirage-1.2-released&gt;

Making "never break the build" scale:
  &lt;https://blogs.janestreet.com/making-never-break-the-build-scale/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=making-never-break-the-build-scale&gt;

Immutable strings in OCaml-4.02:
  &lt;http://blog.camlcity.org/blog/bytes1.html&gt;

ppx and extension points:
  &lt;http://www.lexifi.com/blog/ppx-and-extension-points&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
