<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2016.02.23</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2016.02.16</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2016.03.01</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>February 16 to 23, 2016</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>bigstring 0.1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2016-02/msg00074.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Simon Cruanes announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I released bigstring.0.1 yesterday, a small module for dealing with
bigarrays of chars. It used to be part of containers, but is useful on
its own for low level IO, mirage, etc.; hence the split.  The license is
BSD-2-clauses.

Code, issues, etc. can be found at https://github.com/c-cube/ocaml-bigstring ,
and contributions and criticism are welcome.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Coccinelle and the Dumper module</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2016-02/msg00085.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sébastien Hinderer asked and Richard Jones replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; With Coccinelle we distribute your Dumper module.
&gt;
&gt; I just noticed that the version we have is quite old and produces
&gt; warnings when compiled.
&gt;
&gt; Is it okay if we distribute a modified version of the code to fix those
&gt; warnings?

Yes.  I'm not sure if it was ever licensed properly, but I'm willing
now to (re?)license it under a liberal 3 clause, no advertising
requirement, BSD license:

  https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Licensing:BSD?rd=Licensing/BSD#New_BSD_.28no_advertising.2C_3_clause.29

This is pretty close to "do what you like with it".  I'm CC-ing this
to caml-list to put this in the public record.

&gt; Is there a more recent version of the code available?

Not as far as I know, but if you search for "dumper.mli" you will see
many copies in different places, so I suppose you'll have to go check
if people have added useful features that you want.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Sébastien Hinderer said, Gabriel Scherer replied, and Richard Jones said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Sébastien Hinderer:
&gt;&gt; Okay. I think we are fine with what we have, at the moment.
&gt;&gt;
&gt;&gt; So there were two warnings, one about an unused "open Printf" and one
&gt;&gt; about an unused variable.
&gt;&gt;
&gt;&gt; The attached version of the module fixes them.
&gt;&gt;
&gt;&gt; I may also get rid of the "open Obj" statement and qualify all the
&gt;&gt; references to this module as I fnd this style more clear.

Gabriel Scherer:
&gt; This "dump" code has lived on in Extlib (to which Richard
&gt; participated, I believe), and is also part of Batteries. I know that
&gt; ygrek, Extlib's current maintainers, has done some fixes to it (I
&gt; think we ported them into Batteries), so you may want to look there.

Richard Jones:
Ah I see you are right.  I actually checked extlib before posting
that, but forgot that it was not a standalone module but added to the
'Std' module, here:

https://github.com/ygrek/ocaml-extlib/blob/master/src/std.ml

What I said about the licensing of my contributions still applies
(also 3 clause BSD &amp; LGPL are compatible, so that's fine).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to Alp Mestan, we now include in the OCaml Weekly News the links to the
recent posts from the ocamlcore planet blog at &lt;http://planet.ocaml.org/&gt;.

Functional Jobs: Full-Stack Developer (Haskell/PureScript/ES6) at Canopy Education Inc. (Full-time)
  &lt;https://functionaljobs.com/jobs/8893-full-stack-developer-haskell-purescript-es6-at-canopy-education-inc&gt;

OCamlCore Forge News: OCaml EFL 1.17.0 released
  &lt;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=929&gt;

Github OCaml jobs: Full Time: Software Developer (Functional Programming) at Jane Street in New York, NY; London, UK; Hong Kong
  &lt;http://jobs.github.com/positions/0a9333c4-71da-11e0-9ac7-692793c00b45&gt;

Psellos: Twenty-Four Puzzle OCaml iOS App
  &lt;http://psellos.com/2016/02/2016.02.i-met-up-with-the-king.html&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
