<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2017.06.13</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2017.06.06</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2017.06.20</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>June 06 to 13, 2017</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First OCaml hacking session in Belgium -- 1-2 July</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2017-06/msg00029.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Danny Willems announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm glad to announce and invite you to the first OCaml/Reason (Compiler) Hacking
Session in Belgium which will be the first week-end of July (1-2 July) in my
appartment (yes, in my appartment for the moment. I hope I will have
a bigger place later). The registration are opened here[2]. The full location
will be given later. If you have any problem to come, we can find a solution if
you come in Brussels, don't worry about that. For info, you have to take
the train from Brussels to come and it lasts 1 hour. I will take you to the
station.

The event is opened 24/24 and the entire week-end. You can come the
entire week-end or only one day or few hours. If you want to stay to sleep, I
can host around 5 people (just take a sleeping bag). Just tell me if you come.

Thanks OCamlLabs for offering OCaml stickers to all participants!

### Motivation of the event.

I wrote an article on my blog[1] some weeks ago about the idea of organizing
some
hacking events (specially about OCaml/Reason) in Belgium.
Since last year, I learnt and had some interesting experiences in the OCaml
community and I'm still more and more interested in collaborating and meeting
other
OCaml developers I speak with on Twitter and GitHub or by email.

The main purpose of this event is to meet other people sharing the same
interests than me and sharing cultures and knowledge.

### Subjects

The subjects of this first event will be very large and will depend on coming
people. The only thing I would like to keep in mind is &lt;b&gt;hacking&lt;/b&gt;. Hack
for me is discovering and understanding new subjects and build something new or
fix some issues. I hope other hackers like me, with the same mindset, will be
interested in this event and will come.

The (non-exhaustive) list of subjects is:

- hack on OCaml compiler. It can be fix some junior issues
  (&lt;https://caml.inria.fr/mantis/my_view_page.php&gt;), understand the type system,
  improve it, learn how type systems work, improve front-end, propose some
  useful syntactic sugar, etc.

- hack on Reason front-end compiler. Reason changes the syntax of OCaml by
  giving a syntax more friendly to people coming from other
  languages like JavaScript. Reason community also builds very interesting tools
  to interact with React or JavaScript world.

- hack Ocsigen. Ocsigen is a very interesting web framework and maybe the most
  advanced web framework in terms of new ideas and concepts. The core team is
  very small and doesn't have a lot of time to develop a lot of new features. As
  there are not a lot of core developers, Ocsigen lacks some useful features
  present in most web framework. The documentation and the website must be
  updated and lots of issues must be fixed.

- hack on opam. opam is the main and the most used package manager for OCaml.
  The release of opam 2.0 is coming soon and we can look after some last issues.

- hack on Mirage. In the world of unikernels, Mirage becomes popular and a
  subject I would like to learn.

### About me

I will be able to help in the first three subjects.

- About the OCaml compiler, I work at INRIA for several months and I built
  typing and subtyping algorithms based on the type system DOT for first-class
  modules in OCaml. I think I will able to help for the type system and the front
  end. About multicore or ASM code generation, I'm not an expert and don't have a
  deep knowledge about it.
- About the Reason front-end compiler. I have some experience in lexing and
  parsing.
- About the Ocsigen project, I work on Ocsigen Start for several months and had
  some experience in Eliom.

About the two last, I don't have any hacking knowledge (I never use Mirage, but
it's on my TODO list).

### About drinks and foods.

I think drinks and food will be offered, to be confirmed depending on the number
of participants (don't trust the article on my blog). A special beer will be
offered to all participants (We are in Belgium, it's mandatory =)).

### Registration.

You can register on the Eventbrite link. Please register if you are only sure to
come.
If you have a better solution than Eventbrite, tell me (I don't think Eventbrite
is a good solution but I'm not an expert). The event is entirely free. If
Eventbrite asks you to pay something, refuse and contact me.

### About next events.

I really want to create a community in Belgium around functional programming and
specially about OCaml and Reason. I would like to create more hacking sessions.
If you want to contribute or help to the organization of such event (by hosting
for example), contact me.
I hope some institutions or companies will be interested in such events.

[1]
https://blog.danny-willems.be/ocamlreason-compiler-hacking-sessions-first-announcement/
[2]
https://www.eventbrite.fr/e/billets-ocaml-hacking-session-belgium-35217611825
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>deprecating opam 1.2.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2017-06/msg00046.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Anil Madhavapeddy said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thank you all for the helpful feedback. Since there have been no more messages
or objections, I have started the process off here:

https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/9477
&lt;https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/9477&gt;

When I merge it, I will also update opam.ocaml.org &lt;http://opam.ocaml.org/&gt; with
a deprecation notice. If you do spot any distributions packaging opam 1.2.0,
please do feel free to contact them to request an upgrade to a supported release
such as 1.2.2.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>From the OCaml discourse</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>The editor compiled this list</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are some links to messages at &lt;http://discuss.ocaml.org&gt; that may
be of interest to the readers.

- gaborigloi talks about "xapi-project packages updated to their latest stable versions"
  &lt;https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-xapi-project-packages-updated-to-their-latest-stable-versions/365/1&gt;

- Sander talks about "Create a Real World OCaml category"
  &lt;https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/create-a-real-world-ocaml-category/378/1&gt;
 
- Anil Madhavapeddy talks about "Cstruct 3.0.0, with packaging changes"
  &lt;https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-cstruct-3-0-0-with-packaging-changes/284/5&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocaml Github Pull Requests</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Scherer and the editor compiled this list</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here is a sneak peek at some potential future features of the Ocaml
compiler, discussed by their implementers in these Github Pull Requests.

- Unicode support for the Windows runtime: Let's do it!
  https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/1200
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at OCaml Planet,
&lt;http://ocaml.org/community/planet/&gt;.

Sr. Front-End Engineer at Originate (Full-time)
 &lt;https://functionaljobs.com/jobs/9020-sr-front-end-engineer-at-originate&gt;

Full Time: Software Developer (Functional Programming) at Jane Street in New York, NY; London, UK; Hong Kong
 &lt;http://jobs.github.com/positions/0a9333c4-71da-11e0-9ac7-692793c00b45&gt;
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
