<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2018.11.06</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2018.10.23</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2018.11.13</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>October 23 to November 06, 2018</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head>Sorry for the hiatus, I was offline last week.</cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>(Non-protocol-specific) binary serialization library?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/non-protocol-specific-binary-serialization-library/2768/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Brendan Long asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I've been working on several libraries that need to send and receive packets in specific binary formats ([PGX](https://github.com/arenadotio/pgx), [TDS](https://github.com/brendanlong/ocaml-tds)). Right now they both have extremely-low-level code to convert ints to bytes with the right endianness, but it seems excessively low level to put in every library I write that deals with a binary protocol.

I know there are a bunch of libraries for parsing text, or for working with defined protocols like msgpack, but is there anything for arbitrary binary encoding? I'm thinking something like [struct](https://docs.python.org/3/library/struct.html) in Python, although I'm not married to that particular implementation.

(As a side note: Another reason I'd like something like this is that all of my current implementations handle one byte at a time, and it would be nice if we could do this more efficiently).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Brendan Long then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
My current implementation of this in TDS involves adding a ~fold_bytes~ function to every type, like:

https://github.com/brendanlong/ocaml-tds/blob/master/src/uint32.ml

#+begin_src ocaml
let fold_bytes ~init ~f t order =
  order
  |&gt; List.fold_left ~init ~f:(fun acc shift_bytes -&gt;
    shift_right t (shift_bytes * 8)
    |&gt; Uint8.of_uint32
    |&gt; Uint8.fold_bytes ~f ~init:acc)

let fold_bytes_be ~init ~f t =
  [ 3 ; 2 ; 1 ; 0 ]
  |&gt; fold_bytes ~init ~f t

let fold_bytes_le ~init ~f t =
  [ 0 ; 1 ; 2 ; 3 ]
  |&gt; fold_bytes ~init ~f t
#+end_src

Although this makes things readable at the expense of most-likely being even slower than the usual implementations. Having something somwhat readable and also not horribly slow would be nice.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Matthieu Dubuget suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I used to use bitstring for such things. But it's a long time since i last had a look at it. I found it easy to use.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Brendan Long then replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Ooo nice. That looks like exactly what I was looking for:

https://bitstring.software/examples/
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Hezekiah Carty also suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
You can also check out [angstrom](https://github.com/inhabitedtype/angstrom) which provides a nice parsing API  and [cstruct](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cstruct) which includes a ppx somewhat similar to bitstring.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>James Woodyatt added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The usual companion to the [angstrom](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/angstrom/) parser combinator library is [faraday](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/faraday/) binary serialization library. These libraries are both fairly mature and they can work in combination or separately. Alas, we don't have anything quite as comprehensive as [serde](https://serde.rs) in the Rust language world.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>opam 2.0.1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-opam-2-0-1/2775/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>R. Boujbel announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are pleased to announce the release of [opam 2.0.1](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/releases/tag/2.0.1).

This new version contains mainly backported fixes, some platform-specific and some opam specific. You can find more information in this [blog post](https://opam.ocaml.org/blog/opam-2-0-1).

opam is a source-based package manager for OCaml. It supports multiple simultaneous compiler installations, flexible package constraints, and a Git-friendly development workflow.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Marek Kubica then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
FYI: ~brew~ users just have to [run upgrade](https://github.com/Homebrew/homebrew-core/pull/33355), it was added a few hours ago.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Perry E. Metzger said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Sadly, I haven't updated MacPorts yet because I'm getting a bizarre error with the result...

#+begin_example
$ opam --version
2.0.1
$ opam upgrade
opam(44003,0x112e675c0) malloc: can't allocate region
,*** mach_vm_map(size=259407338536550400) failed (error code=3)
opam(44003,0x112e675c0) malloc: *** set a breakpoint in malloc_error_break to debug
Fatal error: out of memory.
#+end_example

Help fixing this is actively solicited. I've never seen anything like it.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Perry E. Metzger later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The problem proves to be hard to reproduce, so for now, MacPorts has also been updated to supply opam 2.0.1; updating as usual will get you the new version.

If anyone else manages to reproduce the failure above, please get in touch!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Documentation about the ocaml compiler?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/documentation-about-the-ocaml-compiler/2777/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sean Talts asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm looking to get to know the ocaml compiler a bit better and I was wondering if there's any documentation about it at a high level? I'm imagining something like [Rust's guide to rustc](https://rust-lang-nursery.github.io/rustc-guide/).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Radanne replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/blob/trunk/HACKING.adoc
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[ocamlverse](https://ocamlverse.github.io/) also has a page on the [compiler](https://ocamlverse.github.io/content/compiler.html), though it's mostly incomplete.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Packaging process</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/packaging-process/2782/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>David Chemouil asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Although the state of build and release tools has contiuously improved over the years (and I deeply thank all people involved in this transition), in particular regarding the simplification of steps to perform, I still find myself having trouble releasing software in Opam. So I'd like to ask here what is the current suggested process for "basic" projects relying on Dune (like [my own pet project](https://github.com/grayswandyr/electrod/)). I was even thinking a post that would permanently be updated would be cool. I know [this post](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/experience-report-switching-to-jbuilder-and-topkg/993?u=grayswandyr) by @mmottl but now we have dune-release (BTW can it work across a proxy?) so I'd love to see an update, gather hints...
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Markus Mottl replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Incidentally, I finished rewriting my packages using ~dune~, ~dune-release~, and OPAM 2.0 just yesterday.  ~dune-release~ behaves pretty much exactly like ~topkg~ on the command line.  You can thus follow the usual process as outlined in my mentioned post and replace every occurence of ~topkg~ with ~dune-release~.  I did not need the ~CONDUIT_TLS=native~ environment setting anymore.

The only problem right now is that documentation generation does not work due to an apparent bug in ~dune-release~, which will hopefully be fixed soon.  This means that for the while being you can't just execute ~dune-release bistro~.  You should instead follow the individual steps as outlined in the previous post and skip the ~dune-release publish doc~ step.

Another small difference is that ~dune-release~ is more picky about your OPAM files and may fail during lint steps.  The best way to fix this is by addressing any problems raised by ~dune-release lint~.  It seems like a small bug, but this linting process does not currently account for ~*.descr~ files.  Though this may likely be fixed soon, just remove the file and put its contents into the ~synopsis~ and ~description~ fields in the OPAM file instead.  I actually prefer having one less file in the source tree anyway.  Note that the current OPAM repository does not have any ~descr~ files anymore.  I'm not sure whether they are discouraged now, but OPAM, too, obviously prefers the package documentation inside the specification file.

OPAM 2.0 also introduced some specification changes, e.g. when it comes to external dependencies.  You may need to update your package specifications if this affects you.  Other than that the package release process should work fine.

I'd suggest you just grab one of my recently updated and merged packages to have a template to follow.  E.g. [Lacaml](https://github.com/mmottl/lacaml) is one of the more complex ones that have been through the process.  If you need an example for how to specify external library dependencies with OPAM 2.0, you may also take a look at the still unmerged [Postgresql](https://github.com/mmottl/postgresql-ocaml).

The above small bugs and kinks will probably be solved soon.  Specifying, building, and releasing new OCaml software is certainly substantially easier, safer, and more efficient now than ever before.  I doubt you can squeeze out much more goodness at this point for the vast majority of use cases.  The combination of ~dune~, ~dune-release~, and OPAM is at least on par if not superior to anything other languages can offer.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Markus Mottl later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I've just been contacted by the Thomas Gazagnaire (the ~dune-release~ maintainer) to discuss the recent problems.  Strangely, when trying to replicate the problems to provide more details, it turned out that both the ~*.descr~ linting issue as well as the documentation publication issue have disappeared.  Since even older ~dune-release~ versions don't exhibit the issues anymore, I suspect that either used libraries or tools may have been responsible.

Anyway, the gist is that you can apparently follow the simpler release process outlined in https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/experience-report-switching-to-jbuilder-and-topkg/993, replacing ~topkg~ with ~dune-release~.  Just keep the above hints in mind in case the mentioned problems still bubble up with your installation.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Thomas Gazagnaire said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Also, the expected workflow is supposed to be:

1. add a tag in your Git repo. This should be done via ~dune-release tag [tag-name]~ and/or manually. If you don't supply a tag name, it will look into your change file to guess something.

2. run ~dune-release~. This is very similar to ~topkg bistro~ but it should handle properly repositories with multiple packages.

There are still a few fragile things in the release process, and I would be very happy to review patches and contributions :-)  For instance, we start to have a few unit/regressions tests, but we definitely need more.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml and LZMA - decompression based on xz-utils and 7zip</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-and-lzma-decompression-based-on-xz-utils-and-7zip/2802/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anton Kochkov announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Recently I needed to process a bunch of data that can be valid LZMA stream, can be invalid (e.g. damaged) LZMA stream, or just can look like it. I searched pure OCaml implementations and found none. Then I found [the old library](https://forge.ocamlcore.org/projects/ocaml-lzma/), but after a while decided to implement my own bindings. At first I tried to use liblzma from xz-utils, and created [Ctypes-based bindings](https://github.com/XVilka/ocaml-lzma/). But after working with them I found out that xz-utils implementation is not thread-safe, thus causing a heap corruption/segfaults when ran in many threads. So I switched to 7zip implementation of LZMA algorithm, and implemented bindings around them [ocaml-lzma_7z](https://github.com/XVilka/ocaml-lzma_7z).

Feel free to reuse the code any way you like, or complain in issues (or even send pull requests).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New release of odepack</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-new-release-of-odepack/2799/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Christophe announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am happy to announce the release of version 0.6.9 of [odepack](https://github.com/Chris00/ocaml-odepack).  ~Odepack~ is a library to solve Cauchy problems, that is ordinary differential equations (ODE) of the form ∂ₜy(t) = f(t,y(t)) with initial conditions y(t₀) = y₀.  It has root searching capabilities for quantities depending on the solution t ↦ y(t).  The OCaml version is a binding to the [FORTRAN code](http://netlib.sandia.gov/odepack/).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>NYC OCaml Meetup</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/nyc-ocaml-meetup/2743/3</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Brendan Long announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here's the video:

https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pItUfo6Xjj0

And the slides (note: I stopped at the Questions slide):

https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ZKtkVUEaVTB857MniEPnaNgGgz9xf0iV/view?usp=sharing
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Don't panic that your opam switches recompile from today!</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/dont-panic-that-your-opam-switches-recompile-from-today/2816/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>David Allsopp announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The ~ocaml~ package has been updated in opam-repository in [PR12832](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/12832). Since all other packages depend on it, when you next run ~opam update~, opam is going to want to rebuild all the packages in your switches. _The compiler itself will not be rebuilt as part of this, "just" packages._

The ~ocaml~ package is a virtual package which probes the configuration of the underlying OCaml compiler (either a system compiler, an opam-compiled OCaml, or an opam-compiled patched compiler).

The reason for the change is to fix the creation of switches for compilers which don't support shared libraries. The problem was that a script in the ~ocaml~ package depended on the ~Unix~ library to probe the output of ~ocamlc -where~.

Sorry for the CPU-hogging inconvenience this will cause - it's a package we aim to leave alone most of the time!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Annoucement of an OCaml book in Chinese</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2018-11/msg00002.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>陈钢 announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am happy to announce my book, "An Introduction to OCaml Language Programming" in Chinese "OCaml语言编程基础教程", published in June 1st, 2018. The amazon website for the book is
https://www.amazon.cn/dp/B07CXBXR67/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1541156503&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=ocaml

ISBN: 9787115471215
The publisher:  人民邮电出版社 (Posts &amp; Telecom Press)

I would like to take this chance to given my sincere thanks to my OCaml language teachers : Guy Cousineau &amp; Micheal Mauny.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Destructive module substitution: changed in 4.07</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/destructive-module-substitution-changed-in-4-07/2824/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Vincent Jacques asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The following code fragment compiles with OCaml 4.02.3 to 4.06.0 but not with 4.07:

#+begin_src ocaml
module Original = struct
  module X = struct
    let x = 42
  end
end

module Intermediate = struct
  include Original
end

module Final = struct
  module X = struct
    let x = 43
  end

  include (Intermediate: module type of Intermediate with module X := X)
end
#+end_src

With 4.07, it fails with this error message:

#+begin_example
Error: In this `with' constraint, the new definition of X
       does not match its original definition in the constrained signature:
       Modules do not match:
         (module X)
       is not included in
         (module Original.X)
#+end_example

If you remove the ~Intermediate~ module (and ~include (Original: module type of Original with module X := X)~, it does compile with all versions I tried.

Questions:
- is it expected to compile? (i.e. was it a bug in previous versions or is it a regression in 4.07?)
- is there a workaround to make it work with 4.07
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>octachron replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This is an intended changes in 4.07, ~module type of~ does no longer remove module aliases information. You can get back the old behavior by adding a ~[@remove_aliases]~ attribute:
#+begin_src ocaml
module type of Intermediate[@remove_aliases]
#+end_src
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First release of bwrap</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-first-release-of-bwrap/2835/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Christophe announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the first release of [bwrap](https://github.com/Chris00/ocaml-bwrap), a simple library to fork executables in a sandboxed environment — with an interface similar to ~Unix.open_process~ — thanks to [bubblewrap](https://github.com/projectatomic/bubblewrap) (Linux only).

Enjoy and do not hesitate to report issues!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocaml Github Pull Requests</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Scherer and the editor compiled this list</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here is a sneak peek at some potential future features of the Ocaml
compiler, discussed by their implementers in these Github Pull Requests.

- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/2121][Deprecate the deprecated functions]]
- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/2125][Filename.chop_suffix_opt]]
- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/2122][Signature local bindings]]
- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/2129][Stdlib: add Fun module]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=964][forge.ocamlcore.org expected downtime on 2018-11-01]]
- [[http://forge.ocamlcore.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=963][forge.ocamlcore.org expected downtime on 2018-10-30]]
- [[http://jobs.github.com/positions/9e8ba450-e72e-11e7-926f-6ce07b7015c8][Full Time: Compiler Engineer at Jane Street in New York &amp; London]]
- [[http://jobs.github.com/positions/0a9333c4-71da-11e0-9ac7-692793c00b45][Full Time: Software Developer (Functional Programming) at Jane Street in New York, NY; London, UK; Hong Kong]]
- [[https://opam.ocaml.org/blog/opam-2-0-1/][opam 2.0.1 is out!]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
