<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2018.08.21</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2018.07.24</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2018.08.28</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 24 to August 21, 2018</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head></cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Color: library to work with css color formats</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/color-library-to-work-with-css-color-formats/2328/2</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, gasche said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Would there be a chance to connect with the work on specifying colors and color
profiles in @dbuenzli's basic graphics [Gg](http://erratique.ch/software/gg)
library (see [Gg.Color documentation](http://erratique.ch/software/gg/doc/Gg.Color.html))? From the
interface that you provide, it is not completely clear to me how flexible color
computations can be -- you provide an HSLA color space, but a linearized sRGB
space would be also convenient for example, and Gg provides one.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Christophe added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
To work with colors, note there is also [Color brewery](https://github.com/Chris00/color_brewery) (not yet in opam) which is
compatible with ~Gg.color~. I concur with @gasche, it is good if all these
libraries can work together.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Anurag Soni then announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
https://github.com/anuragsoni/color/tree/0.2.0

I have updated the library with more utilities to work with colors. Some other
changes since last time is the use of ~Gg.Color.t~ as the color type. So one can
use other methods from the wonderful ~gg~ library to tweak/modify their colors,
or use color palettes like the ones from ~color-brewry~
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Derive-ocaml: a rust crate to help with ocaml FFI</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/derive-ocaml-a-rust-crate-to-help-with-ocaml-ffi/2331/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Joris Giovannangeli announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
i'm pleased to announce the first release of
[derive-ocaml](https://crates.io/crates/derive-ocaml) a set of rust macros
1.1/2.0 (similar to ppx) to generate boilerplate of writing rust stubs for ocaml
external calls.

The crate has no runtime and relies on the [ocaml](https://crates.io/crates/ocaml) for all the ocaml runtime bindings.

The macros are still a bit experimental but should make ocaml/rust ffi much easier to crawl. 
Also while here i'd like to thank @zshipko for maintaining and improve the ocaml crate !!
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Perry E. Metzger asked and Joris Giovannangeli replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; So this is to allow calling Rust from OCaml?

yes,but mostly it's helper to derive conversion from and to ocaml types to rust structures/enums. This is the main feature, it generates boilerplate code to call store_field()/field 'macros' like in C.
On top of that it has some glue to make rust functions "nice" looking by hiding CAMLparams and co macros.

You can see a very basic example here: 
- [ocaml side](https://github.com/ahrefs/rust-ocaml-derive/blob/master/example/src/stubs.ml)
- [rust side](https://github.com/ahrefs/rust-ocaml-derive/blob/master/example/src/lib.rs)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>random forests in OCaml via bindings to the R randomForest package</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-random-forests-in-ocaml-via-bindings-to-the-r-randomforest-package/2335/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>UnixJunkie announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
https://github.com/UnixJunkie/orrandomForest

Quite hackish but working.
The interface is similar to my other "R-wrapping packages".
Data are exchanged via text files.

Should land soon in opam.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml Documentation Open Thread</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-documentation-open-thread/1841/138</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Deep in this thread, Daniel Bünzli said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; but even plain text files of good documentation

We even have better than that. 

We have the [~ocamldoc~ language](https://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml/ocamldoc.html#sec351). It
allows to have your documentation exactly where it is needed, in ~mli~ files,
and will carry itself if you move your sources around.

The ocamldoc language is a fully featured document markup language with sectioning and /checked/ cross references to sections and API entry points. 

Doing manuals and tutorial inside ~.mli~ always felt a bit cumbersome but is
entirely doable as can be witnessed in many of my packages (see [this
one](http://erratique.ch/software/vg/doc/Vg.html) for example). The good news is
that nowadays we will gradually be able to write those larger pieces in seperate
~.mld~ files. Code sample extraction is not there yet but I hope we can have a
[simple design](https://github.com/ocaml/odoc/issues/130) implemented soon
rather than having these discussions.

The other good news is that as a programmer, the effort you need to provide in order to make the documentation you write in this language available to end-users is this: *approaching zero*:
- If you are using ~topkg~ or ~dune-release~ (assuming they didn't kill that workflow), publishing your docs online on github is a  ~topkg distrib &amp;&amp; topkg publish doc~ away. 
- Distributing this documentation with your package releases is also /automatically/ done if you use ~topkg+ocamlbuild~ or ~dune~: these systems compile and install the right files which ~odig~ can then pickup in order to generate cross-referenced documentation for all the packages that are installed in your ~opam~ switch and allows you to peacefully read all this wondefully produced documentation offline with the stylesheet that suits you.

One might complain that the ocamldoc language syntax is none of these
alternative document markup languages whose popularity came after ~ocamldoc~'s
initial existence but if you ever tried to write a polymorphic variant in a
markdown code span you will be glad that ocamldoc's language isn't that one.

I understand the ~ocamldoc~ language is one more thing to learn as a newcomer
but it's not hugely complex, it's there, it works with the advantages
highlighted above and an aspiring OCaml working programmer shall meet it quite
soon anyways since there are thousands of lines of documentation in hundreds of
projects that are using it.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Article: "Systems Languages: An Experience Report"</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/article-systems-languages-an-experience-report/2339/12</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Deep in this thread, Yotam Barnoy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Just wanted to plug [OCamlverse](https://ocamlverse.github.io/). Not only can anyone contribute via PR, anyone can have commit rights as well.

We already have a
[quickstart](https://ocamlverse.github.io/content/quickstart.html) page for
setting up Dune and such. I'd love to have more content there for getting OCaml
concepts like concurrent programming up and running quickly.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Opam 2.0.0 RC4-final is out!</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/opam-2-0-0-rc4-final-is-out/2341/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>R. Boujbel announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are happy to announce the opam 2.0.0 final release candidate. Hooray! :tada: 
It will be promoted to 2.0.0 proper within a few weeks, when the official repository format switches from 1.2.0 to 2.0.0.
You'll find all information about opam update &amp; repository upgrade in this [blog post](http://www.ocamlpro.com/2018/07/26/opam-2-0-0-rc4-final-is-out/).

Big thanks to all who helped test and polish the release!
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>R. Boujbel later said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The roadmap is detailed in this [blog post](https://opam.ocaml.org/blog/opam-2-0-0-repo-upgrade-roadmap).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Updated dune starter kit</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/updated-dune-starter-kit/2342/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Martin Jambon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The goal of this 3rd-party repository is to provide a minimal and idiomatic
[template for setting up an OCaml
project](https://github.com/mjambon/dune-starter). It was just updated to use
~dune~ instead of ~jbuilder~.

For those migrating, the [changes are
minimal](https://github.com/mjambon/dune-starter/commit/900625d875013d65ee2b3bb09ee6ae42d9e95284)
and detailed migration help is given by the [official
docs](http://dune.readthedocs.io/en/latest/migration.html).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Shon then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I have a dead simple, feature poor tool in this direction which I've used for my own toy purposes: https://github.com/shonfeder/nomad

Its in't updated to use the ~dune~ rebranding or to be compliant with the new release.

I'm glad to hear that the views about integrating this functionality directly into dune have changed! I'd be happy to help with that effort.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Quantitative developer position at LexiFi, Paris</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/quantitative-developer-position-at-lexifi-paris/2380/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Alain Frisch announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
LexiFi has an open position for a junior quantitative developer. The position
could be a good fit for an OCaml developer with some interest in (learning
about) numerical methods and/or financial stuff, even without a formal
background in those topics.

More information:
https://www.lexifi.com/careers/quantitative-developer/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Dune 1.1.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-dune-1-1-0/2402/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Rudi Grinberg announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
On behalf of the dune team, I'm proud to announce the 1.1.0 release of dune.
This release contains a few interesting features that I won't describe in this
post, because I've already written a dedicated blog post about this release:
http://rgrinberg.com/posts/dune-upcoming-1-1/

The change log is replicated here for your convenience:

*** 1.1.0 (06/08/2018)

- Fix lookup of command line specified files when ~--root~ is given. Previously,
  passing in ~--root~ in conjunction with ~--workspace~ or ~--config~ would not
  work correctly (#997, @rgrinberg)

- Add support for customizing env nodes in workspace files. The ~env~ stanza is
  now allowed in toplevel position in the workspace file, or for individual
  contexts. This feature requires ~(dune lang 1.1)~ (#1038, @rgrinberg)

- Add ~enabled_if~ field for aliases and tests. This field controls whether the
  test will be ran using a boolean expression language. (#819, @rgrinberg)

- Make ~name~, ~names~ fields optional when a ~public_name~, ~public_names~
  field is provided. (#1041, fix #1000, @rgrinberg)

- Interpret ~X~ in ~--libdir X~ as relative to ~PREFIX~ when ~X~ is relative
  (#1072, fix #1070, @diml)

- Add support for multi directory libraries by writing
  ~(include_subdirs unqualified)~ (#1034, @diml)

- Add ~(staged_pps ...)~ to support staged ppx rewriters such as ones
  using the OCaml typer like ~ppx_import~ (#1080, fix #193, @diml)

- Use ~-opaque~ in the ~dev~ profile. This option trades off binary quality for
  compilation speed when compiling .cmx files. (#1079, fix #1058, @rgrinberg)

- Fix placeholders in ~dune subst~ documentation (#1090, @emillon, thanks
  @trefis for the bug report)

- Add locations to errors when a missing binary in PATH comes from a dune file
  (#1096, fixes #1095, @rgrinberg)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Work-in-progress Sentry SDK</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/work-in-progress-sentry-sdk/2403/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Brendan Long announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Cross-posted-ish from: https://forum.sentry.io/t/a-work-in-progress-ocaml-sdk/4406

I've been wanting to use Sentry with OCaml, and ended up writing my own library for it. I thought other people might be interested to, so:

https://github.com/brendanlong/sentry-ocaml

It currently only works with Async and not Lwt or synchronous/stdlib only. If anyone else is interested, I'd definitely like to support those. And feedback would definitely be nice.

You basically just do this at the start of your program and it will load ~SENTRY_DSN~ (and some other things) from your environment and upload any errors in the background:

#+begin_src ocaml
Sentry.with_context  @@ fun () -&gt;
#+end_src

You can also set custom tags and upload exceptions or messages manually:

#+begin_src ocaml
Sentry.with_environment "staging" @@ fun () -&gt;
Sentry.with_tags [ "method", "POST" ; "path", "/example" ] @@ fun () -&gt;
Sentry.capture_message "this will have the environment and tags above merged with the defaults"
#+end_src

Results look like:

https://discourse-cdn-sjc2.com/standard11/uploads/ocaml/original/2X/4/40293449c4e632c7e7e6d4f55e7ced6bd8702976.png

Note that it works a lot better if you use exceptions and not ~Or_error.t~, although if someone wants to improve the ~Or_error.t~ parsing, pull requests would be welcome for that too.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>A good summary of the "multicore OCaml memory model" article</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/a-good-summary-of-the-multicore-ocaml-memory-model-article/2422/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>gasche announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[The morning paper](https://blog.acolyer.org/) is an amazing blog where the
author posts summaries of research papers. Today's edition covers the recent
(PLDI 2018) article ([PDF](http://kcsrk.info/papers/pldi18-memory.pdf)) on the
memory model proposed for the Multicore OCaml implementation:

[Bounding data races in space and time – part I](https://blog.acolyer.org/2018/08/09/bounding-data-races-in-space-and-time-part-i/)
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>gasche later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[Part II](https://blog.acolyer.org/2018/08/10/bounding-data-races-in-space-and-time-part-ii/) is now available.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Balancer 1.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-balancer-1-0/2424/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Nobody Gone announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce that Balancer 1.0 is now available on opam, it's a
collection of load balancing algorithms, such as p2c, consistent hashing + least
loaded, p2c with partial key grouping, round robin, etc.

All of the balancers are written with service discovery in mind, so you can plugin a react signal and use a watch with zookeeper or whatever. 

It also comes with some useful synchronization utils for shared mutable state. 

I think it's a useful addition to the ecosystem, just because people scale ocaml
by spawning a lot of processes and talking via tcp, domain sockets, files, etc,
and I'm actually surprised there wasn't a library for it beforehand.

https://github.com/xnukernpoll/ocaml-balancers

https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/balancer/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Interesting OCaml Articles</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/interesting-ocaml-articles/1867/24</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Yotam Barnoy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
A pair of great posts discussing @stedolan's now-famous PLDI paper! :tada:

https://blog.acolyer.org/2018/08/09/bounding-data-races-in-space-and-time-part-i/

https://blog.acolyer.org/2018/08/10/bounding-data-races-in-space-and-time-part-ii/
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
https://blog.janestreet.com/what-the-interns-have-wrought-2018/
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy also added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
http://www.dra27.uk/blog/platform/2018/08/15/dune-vendoring.html
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Opam 2.0 experimental PPAs</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/opam-2-0-experimental-ppas/2446/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I've refreshed the opam2 PPA infrastructure to make binary packages available
for Ubuntu, ahead of the stable release of opam 2.0.0. These can be used with
(e.g.) Travis CI for non-container based builds from an Ubuntu base, without
having to wait for the upstream packages to get the latest version of opam.

The packages currently sit in my experimental PPA tree at
[avsm/ppa-opam-experimental](https://github.com/avsm/opam2-ppa), so if anyone
can test them and let me know if you run into any problems, I'd appreciate it.

Sources to the scripts and more information in the README:

- https://github.com/avsm/opam2-ppa

If anyone would like to help with including opam 2 in more upstream
distributions as we approach release, please [refer to the distributions
wiki](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/wiki/Distributions) and pick your favourite
OS :)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>aws-s3 4.0.1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-aws-s3-4-0-1/2451/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anders Fugmann announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I’m happy to announce aws-s3 4.0.1

The [aws-s3](https://github.com/andersfugmann/aws-s3) library provides access to
Amazon Simple Storage Solution (S3). Operations include: get, put, head, delete,
delete_multi, ls, multipart upload and s3 to s3 copying. The library includes
functions to get machine role and security token (credentials) through AWS
Identity and Access Management service (IAM). The library supports both lwt and
async concurrency models.

Lots of changes have been made in this release, but most noticeably is the
introduction of a streaming api, which will reduce latency and memory footprint
as objects does not need to be held in memory in full during transfer.

The release contains some trivial breaking changes (module renaming), and upgrading should be strait forward.

Changes since version 3.0.0:
- Support HEAD operation on objects.
- Change signature to use string for etag rather than Caml.Digest.t
- Support Digest 0.6
- Remove dependency to Core
- Rewrite authentication code
- Switch to use Ptime for time conversion routines
- Support chunked transfer (put)
- Add streaming API
- Remove dependency on Cohttp
- Switch to dune
- Support IPv6
- Add option to use expect-100.
- Add option to limit result of ls
- Extend aws-cli
- Move region related functions to own Region module
- Fix bug when parsing multi delete reply in case of error

The package is available through opam.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocaml Github Pull Requests</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Scherer and the editor compiled this list</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here is a sneak peek at some potential future features of the Ocaml
compiler, discussed by their implementers in these Github Pull Requests.

- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/1966][Format semantic tags as extensible sum types]]
- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/1986][Add Set.disjoint]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[http://www.ocamlpro.com/2018/07/31/tzdrawit/][TzDrawIt, a decentralized drawing app on Tezos]]
- [[http://jobs.github.com/positions/0a9333c4-71da-11e0-9ac7-692793c00b45][Full Time: Software Developer (Functional Programming) at Jane Street in New York, NY; London, UK; Hong Kong]]
- [[http://jobs.github.com/positions/9e8ba450-e72e-11e7-926f-6ce07b7015c8][Full Time: Compiler Engineer at Jane Street in New York &amp; London]]
- [[https://gaiustech.wordpress.com/2018/07/29/not-learning-is-a-skill-too/][Not-learning is a skill too]]
- [[http://www.ocamlpro.com/2018/07/26/opam-2-0-0-rc4-final-is-out/][opam 2.0.0 RC4-final is out!]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
