<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2018.07.10</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2018.07.03</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2018.07.17</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 03 to 10, 2018</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head>For people receiving this by email, I'm trying to send it as a multipart/alternative email with the text and html version. Please let me know if there is an issue.</cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Sightings of OCaml around the Web</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/sightings-of-ocaml-around-the-web/1867/23</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here's a must-read article on the dev team's [Plans for OCaml 4.08](https://blog.janestreet.com/plans-for-ocaml-408/) by @lpw25 . If you're a long-time user, you'll really enjoy this.

Also, I'll just mention that [OCamlverse](https://ocamlverse.github.io/) has had
quite a few updates recently. If you haven't checked it out yet, please do --
everyone can request and receive automatic contribution rights, so if there's
something you want to fix up/contribute to, you're welcome to do so.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Looking for OCaml developers for a Tezos based Decentralised Betting Exchange!</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/looking-for-ocaml-developers-for-a-tezos-based-decentralised-betting-exchange/2236/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Suraj Tirupati announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
My team and I are working on a decentralised betting exchange called BettingWin - https://www.bettingwin.online

We want to create a platform through which users can place bets in a
decentralised environment; bettors bet, market makers create markets and
reporters report events. It's still in development and we are looking to work
with some new developers.

We are currently looking to expand our team and bring on some developers to
complete paid tasks or become a permanent member of the team depending on our
compatibility :) We are really interested in working with smart, insightful
developers who are familiar with OCaml and have experience with programming
smart contracts. Also, any developers with an interest in Tezos are very welcome
as that is the blockchain we are using.

We can arrange Skype calls to discuss things in detail. Please contact me at suraj@bettingwin.online 
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Dune 1.0.0 is coming soon, what about jbuilder projects?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/dune-1-0-0-is-coming-soon-what-about-jbuilder-projects/2237/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jérémie Dimino announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The 1.0.0 release of dune is planned for next week. It will be the first release of jbuilder as dune, so what to expect for existing jbuilder projects?

The good news is that dune is fully backward compatible with jbuilder. The ~dune~ package in opam will install both ~dune~ and ~jbuilder~ binaries and both will be usable on existing jbuilder projects.

We do want to stop supporting jbuilder projects eventually, so the plan is to
continue to support the ~jbuilder~ binary and ~jbuild~ files for another year. 6
months from now dune will start displaying warnings when using the ~jbuilder~
binary or ~jbuild~ files. A more detailied [migration plan][mp] is available in
the manual. In particular it contains a precise list of things to do to migrate
a jbuilder project to a dune project.

We hope that the new features in Dune 1.0.0 and subsequent releases will be enough of an incentive for users to eagerly switch to Dune :)

*** Important changes in Dune

This section is not an exhaustive list of changes, but it describes the important changes to expect when switching from ~jbuilder~ to ~dune~.

**** Versioning and configuration files

A big part of the work in Dune 1.0.0 was getting the versioning story right.
With jbuilder it was hard for us to make the language evolve without breaking
the build of existing projects. Dune can handle that gracefully and in the
future it will be much easier to introduce breaking changes.

The versioning of all dune files in a project is controlled via a single
~dune-project~ file at the root of the project. This file contains the version
of the dune language and extensions used in the project.

While this file is required in order to ensure compatibility with future
versions of Dune, it is not required to write one by hand every time you start a
new project or want to do a quick experiment. Dune will create and edit this
file for you as needed, so simply start by creating a ~dune~ file (the new
~jbuild~ files) and dune will take care of the rest.

Note that the syntax inside ~dune~, ~dune-project~, ... files is slightly
different from the one inside ~jbuild~ files. In particular the language
requires fewer parentheses and the syntax of variables changed from ~${...}~ to
~%{...}~ to avoid issues with shell commands. This is detailed in the [migration
plan][mp] as well.

**** Build profiles and default settings

Up to now ~jbuilder~ supported a ~--dev~ option in order to enable stricter
flags. There have been several changes regarding this. First of all you are now
able to define as many build profiles as you want: ~dev~, ~release~, ~perf~, ...
These can be selected either via the ~--profile~ command line option or via the
~dune-workspace~ file. You are also able to define what the default compilation
flags mean for each profile via an [env stanza][env].

Another important change is that the default build profile for the ~dune~ binary
is ~dev~ rather than ~release~. We found that most of the time developpers want
the development mode by default. Please remember to add ~"-p" name~ to all
invocations of ~dune~ in opam files! This is now even more important than before
in order to ensure the release profile is selected for opam builds.

**** Default target

Dune allows to configure what happens when you run ~dune build~ without any specific targets. This is done via the introduction of a [default alias][defal].

**** More parellelism by default

If you had ~(jobs N)~ in you ~~/.config/dune/config~ file, you can remove it.
Dune now automatically sets the number of jobs that can be run in parallel to
the number of processing units available. The previous default was 4. For opam
files, you should remember to add ~"-j" jobs~ in order to let opam decide.

*** Future of Dune

Now that we have a good versioning story and with the new testing tools that are
emerging, I'm hoping that at some point we will be able to declare that the
master of Dune is stable. At this point opam releases will just become a monthly
or even weekly formality. This should make the experience nicer for both
developers and users of Dune.

[mp]:    https://dune.readthedocs.io/en/latest/migration.html\\
[env]:   https://dune.readthedocs.io/en/latest/dune-files.html#env\\
[defal]: https://dune.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#default-alias
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jérémie Dimino then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
One thing I forgot to mention: if you have a ~~/.config/dune/config~ file, you
need to add the following line at the beginning of this file: ~(lang dune 1.0)~.
This line is the one we use in every configuration file that is versionned and
versioning the ~~/.config/dune/config~ file seemed natural. The ~jbuilder~
binary doesn't require it for backward compatibility reasons, but the ~dune~
binary does.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New release of craml, a tool to test command line applications</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-new-release-of-craml-a-tool-to-test-command-line-applications/2241/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Thomas Gazagnaire announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am happy to announce the first release of [craml](https://github.com/realworldocaml/craml), a toool for testing command-line applications.

To install it:

#+begin_src shell
   opam install craml
#+end_src

The tool is already used by [real-world OCaml v2](https://github.com/realworldocaml/book/blob/master/examples/code/json/build_github_atd.sh) to test shell script examples and [by merlin](https://github.com/ocaml/merlin/blob/master/tests/type-expr/test.t). Feedback is alway welcome, so feel free to open new issues on the tracker to discuss about new features.

Here is a copy of the README, with a more complete description of the project:

---

*** craml: a tool for testing command-line applications

CRAM is a is functional testing framework for command line applications. ~craml~ is freely inspired by the [Python tool](https://bitheap.org/cram/), which was itself based on Mercurial's [unified test format](https://www.selenic.com/blog/?p=663).

~craml~ is released as a single binary (called ~craml~) and supports the following syntax:

- Lines beginning with two spaces, a dollar sign, and a space are  *commands* and will be run in the shell.
- Multi-lines commands end by ~\~ and continue with two spaces and  a ~&gt;~ sign on the next line:
#+begin_src shell
  $ &lt;line1&gt; \
  &gt; &lt;line2&gt; \
  &gt; &lt;line3&gt;
#+end_src
- Lines beginning with two spaces are considered command *output*.
- Command outputs can contains *ellipsis*: ~...~. These will match any possible outputs (on zero, one or multiple lines).
- Lines starting by ~&lt;--~ are command *pre-conditions*; they will determine the conditions where the command is run. Currently, only non-deterministic modes are supported as pre-conditions (see below).
- Lines starting by ~--&gt;~ are command *post-conditions*. Currently, only exit codes are supported as post-conditions (see below).
- Anything else is a comment. It is not possible to put comments in the middle of an output as it is not clear what should be done to them when the output changes.

To run the tests described in a ~&lt;file&gt;~, use ~craml &lt;file&gt;~. This will run all
the commands in sequence and will generated ~&lt;file&gt;.corrected~ if one of the
output do not match the expected command outputs.

**** Non-deterministic Outputs

~craml~ supports non-deterministic outputs:

#+begin_src shell
&lt;-- non-deterministic
  $ &lt;command&gt;
  &lt;output&gt;
#+end_src

In that case, ~craml &lt;file&gt;~ will run the command but will not generate
~&lt;file&gt;.corrected~ if the new output differs from the one described in the file.
Use ~craml --non-deterministic &lt;file&gt;~ to come back to the default behaviour.

**** Non-deterministic Commands

~craml~ supports non-deterministic outputs:

#+begin_src shell
&lt;-- non-deterministic [skip]
  $ &lt;command&gt;
  &lt;output&gt;
#+end_src

In that case, ~craml &lt;file&gt;~ will *not* run the command. Use ~craml --non-deterministic &lt;file&gt;~ to come back to the default behaviour.

**** Exit Codes

~craml~ tests exit codes:

#+begin_src shell
  $ &lt;command&gt;
  &lt;output&gt;
--&gt; exit 10
#+end_src

If ~&lt;command&gt;~ does not exit with code 10, then ~craml &lt;file&gt;~ will generate ~&lt;file&gt;.corrected~ with the right exit code. Note that ~@@ exit 0~ will not be displayed.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Perry E. Metzger said and Daniel Bünzli replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
&gt; Just a small request: I note that the README, which many users will never see on installing from opam,

Also note that an ~odig readme craml~ will do.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>How to read/understand function signature with GADT?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/how-to-read-understand-function-signature-with-gadt/2250/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Volodymyr Melnyk asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
For example, given the code:

#+begin_src ocaml
let rec eval : type a . a term -> a = ...
#+end_src

How to read/understand this part: ~type a . a term -> a~? What does the dot here mean? Why should we define type ~a~ in the function's signature?
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>octachron</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
There is two things going on simultaneously here. The first is that GADTs can only add equation to abstract types in a pattern matching. For instance, let's consider the toy example

#+begin_src ocaml
type a = Tag_a
type b = Tag_b
type _ t =
  | A: a t
  | B: b t
#+end_src

then 

#+begin_src ocaml
let to_string = function
  | A -&gt; "a"
  | B -&gt; "b"
#+end_src
yields a type error
#+begin_example
&gt; Error: This pattern matches values of type b t
       but a pattern was expected which matches values of type a t
       Type b is not compatible with type a
#+end_example

because the type of the argument was inferred to ~a t~ in the first branch of the pattern matching.

The solution is to make the type phantom parameter of ~t~ a locally abstract type in ~to_string~. 

#+begin_src ocaml
let to_string (type t) (x: t) = match x with
  | A -&gt; "a"
  | B -&gt; "b"
#+end_src
The notation ~(type t)~ introduces a local abstract type named ~t~, since the type is abstract, it can be refined to different types in  the branches of the pattern matching.

The second point is that recursive function involving GADTs often needs to be recursive polymorphic.
For instance, with a toy langage,

#+begin_src ocaml
type _ term  =
  | Bool : bool -&gt; bool term
  | Int : int -&gt; int term
  | If : bool term * 'a term * 'a term -&gt; 'a term
#+end_src
an eval function would look like

#+begin_src ocaml
let rec eval (type t) (x:t term): t = match x with
| Bool b -&gt; b
| Int x -&gt; x
| If (cond,then',else') -&gt; if eval cond then eval then' else eval else'
#+end_src
but in the ~If~ branch ~eval~ is called with an argument of a different types, which result in a type error 

#+begin_example
&gt; Error: This expression has type t term but an expression was expected of type
         bool term
#+end_example

on the first call with a different value for the ~term~ type parameter.
The  long-winded solution here is to add an explicit polymorphic annotation and then introduce
locally abstract types

#+begin_src ocaml
let rec eval: 't. 't term -&gt; 't = fun (type t) (x: t term): t -&gt; match x with
| Bool b -&gt; b
| Int x -&gt; x
| If (cond,then',else') -&gt; if eval cond then eval then' else eval else'
#+end_src
Since this is a bit of a mouthful, there is shorter variant that directly combines explicit polymorphic annotation with locally abstract types:

#+begin_src ocaml
let rec eval: type t. t term -&gt; t = function
| Bool b -&gt; b
| Int x -&gt; x
| If (cond,then',else') -&gt; if eval cond then eval then' else eval else'
#+end_src
Here ~type t. … ~ declares ~t~ as both a locally abstract types and makes it explicitly polymorphic.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Format module from the Standard Library</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/format-module-from-the-standard-library/2254/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>cloudyhug asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello everyone. Does any of you know where I can find a decent tutorial for the
OCaml Format module ? I cannot figure out how to use it, and the few things I
have found are the documentation and the official tutorial, which are explicit
but not clear at all. I have spent the last 30 minutes trying to understand it,
in vain.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Radanne replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I would recommend reading this blog post: https://cedeela.fr/format-all-the-data-structures.html

For understanding boxes, see https://ocaml.org/learn/tutorials/format.html
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Martin Jambon also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
If that's an option for you, I'd suggest using
[easy-format](https://github.com/mjambon/easy-format). There's a [complete
example here](https://mjambon.github.io/mjambon2016/easy_format_example.html)
with various ways to format the same thing.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First release of mastodon-archive-viewer (0.1)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-first-release-of-mastodon-archive-viewer-0-1/2257/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Kate announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[Mastodon](https://joinmastodon.org/) is a decentralized social network similar to Twitter.

One of its many features is to allow people to get their archive as a way to
save their posts history in case one server is seized, crashed, or temporary
down. It is also useful in case you want to delete an old account but still want
to keep its archive.

Here I present you
[mastodon-archive-viewer](https://github.com/kit-ty-kate/mastodon-archive-viewer)
which is a tool that takes a mastodon archive, previously exported, downloaded
and extracted and gives you an offline web view of it.

If you want to give it a try, mastodon-archive-viewer is now available on opam, and comes with a filter system to view only parts of your archive.
#+begin_src shell
opam install mastodon-archive-viewer
cd &lt;archive-directory-previously-extracted&gt;
mastodon-archive-viewer outbox.json &gt; archive.html
#+end_src

For the moment this tool is in an early stage of development so don't hesitate to report bugs or feature requires on the issues tracker.

Happy tooting!

PS: if you are interested in using Mastodon, perhaps a legit choice of instance might be [functional.cafe](https://functional.cafe), for example :slight_smile:
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[https://coq.inria.fr/news/146.html][Coq 8.8.1 is out]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
