<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2018.12.11</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2018.12.04</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2018.12.18</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>December 04 to 11, 2018</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ppx_yojson 0.2.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ppx-yojson-0-2-0/3006/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Nathan Rebours announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce I just released version ~0.2.0~ of ~ppx_yojson~.

~ppx_yojson~ is a ppx rewriter that helps you work with ~Yojson~ by allowing you to write concise and expressive json expressions and patterns.

Version ~0.2.0~ comes with a set of new features which makes it much more usable and less proof-of-concepty. This includes a new extension to write Yojson patterns and anti-quotation for the expressions extension.  Hopefully it will attract more users.

Full release notes are available [here](https://github.com/NathanReb/ppx_yojson/releases/tag/0.2.0).

~ppx_yojson~ can be found on [github](https://github.com/NathanReb/ppx_yojson) and [opam](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/ppx_yojson/).

Let me know if you have some feedback or if it lacks anything for you to be able to use it!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New release of fix</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2018-12/msg00014.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>François Pottier announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I would like to announce a new release of fix, an OCaml library that provides facilities for memoization, hash-consing, and least-fixed-point computations.

The library can be installed as follows:

   opam update &amp;&amp; opam install fix.20181130

The repository's README offers some documentation and links to demos:

   https://gitlab.inria.fr/fpottier/fix/

In particular, this demo, a conversion of regular expressions to finite-state automata by Brzozowski's method, illustrates many of the facilities offered by the library:

   http://gallium.inria.fr/blog/fixin-your-automata/
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>François Pottier later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
All right, it should work now -- sorry for the noise:

   opam update &amp;&amp; opam install fix.20181206

Thanks to Tuncer Ayaz for reporting the problem and to Kate for helping me fix it.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Interesting OCaml Articles</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/interesting-ocaml-articles/1867/37</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[Presentation on Mirage OS](https://t.co/L6TyfTtQWk) by our own @dinosaure!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>bs-platform 4.0.8 is released</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-bs-platform-4-0-8-is-released/3009/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hongbo Zhang announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
A relevant post: https://bucklescript.github.io/blog/2018/12/05/release-4-0-8
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>LablGtk3 beta1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2018-12/msg00017.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jacques Garrigue announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Due to the planned deprecation of gtksourceview2 in Debian,
we have been working on a stripped down port of LablGtk2 to Gtk-3.

A first beta is available for download at the usual location:\\
	http://lablgtk.forge.ocamlcore.org\\
	https://forge.ocamlcore.org/frs/download.php/1769/lablgtk-3.0.beta1.tar.gz

There is no opam package yet, because I’m not sure how to do that:
I seem to need to add a new conf-gtksourceview3 package too, and I’m not
sure how to proceed. Help accepted.

Note that this is not the originally planned introspection based port, but
a manual port of lablgtk2, dropping widgets that are no longer
available. It is of course possible to add new widgets if people
are willing to contribute.

The main goal is to allow application using lablgtksourceview,
such as CoqIDE, to compile on top of Gtk-3. Since Gtk-2 itself
stays available, lablgtk2 will continue to be supported for other
applications.

The code is in the lablgtk3 branch:\\
	https://github.com/garrigue/lablgtk/tree/lablgtk3\\
There is an ongoing discussion\\
	https://github.com/garrigue/lablgtk/issues/2

The current status is that a modified version of CoqIDE compiles
and runs.

Please report issues on GitHub.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[http://gallium.inria.fr/blog/fixin-your-automata][Fixin' your automata]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
