<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2018.09.11</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2018.09.04</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2018.09.18</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>September 04 to 11, 2018</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>callipyge 0.2 and eqaf 0.1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-callipyge-0-2-and-eqaf-0-1/2520/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Calascibetta Romain announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce the second release of
[callipyge](https://github.com/oklm-wsh/Callipyge.git) which is an
implementation of ~curve25519~ in OCaml and
[eqaf](https://github.com/dinosaure/eqaf.git) which is an implementation of the
equal function on ~string~ in a linear time - specially to avoid timing attacks.

[digestif](https://github.com/mirage/digestif.git) will be updated with ~eqaf~ too.

The goal of ~callipyge~ is to have a good implementation of ~curve25519~ but it
should be replaced by a C stub extracted from the [HACL Star
project](https://github.com/project-everest/hacl-star) (like what Firefox does).
So, currently, we provide this implementation which is 3 times slower than the
[reference implementation](https://github.com/agl/curve25519-donna).

Then, it's a good project to introduce ~eqaf~ which provides only one function
~equal : string -> string -> bool~ (a binding to the [OpenBSD's
implementation](https://github.com/aperezdc/signify/blob/master/timingsafe_bcmp.c))
and ensure to execute this function on linear time and avoid timing attacks. So
we did some benchmarks and compare them with the current implementation of
~String.equal~ from the standard library of OCaml. Then, we get expected
results: in any situation ~eqaf~ took the same time to compare two ~string~
which is not the case with ~String.equal~.

So, happy hacking!
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>He later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
And if you are interesting by ~eqaf~ and how we can check if the function has
linear time, you should look [the first issue of
~eqaf~](https://github.com/dinosaure/eqaf/issues/1). You can find a good
explanation about expected results of benchmarks on ~eqaf~.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Be Sport is hiring (engineers, interns)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2018-09/msg00016.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Vincent Balat announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Be Sport is looking for talented developers enjoying functional programming
and teamwork. All profiles are welcome.

They will work either on data importation/analysis or on the implementation
of our mobile and Web apps. All the code is written in OCaml.

Send me a message for more information!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Sedlex moved to ocaml-community</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/sedlex-moved-to-ocaml-community/2532/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Perry E. Metzger announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
For those of you who use sedlex, it has moved to [a new repository on ocaml-community.](https://github.com/ocaml-community/sedlex)

This was done with a github transfer, so existing issues against the repository
got moved as well, and existing users should be redirected properly. That said,
I've done a pull request to fix the opam packages and hopefully it will be
merged soon.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>gasche asked and Gabriel Radanne replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
How does the regexp compilation engine compares to what is done in
[Re](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-re)? Would it be possible to build a lexer
generator on top of an independent regexp library like
[Tyre](https://github.com/Drup/tyre) or
[ppx_regexp](https://github.com/paurkedal/ppx_regexp)? (cc @Drup)
#+end_quote

That is a very good question, I have some plans in mind, but they require quite a bit of work. Basically, the current situation is the following:


| Library        | Syntax    | Composition | Refill | Unicode | Automaton               | Regexs    |
|----------------|-----------|-------------|--------|---------|-------------------------|-----------|
| ocamlex        | Custom    | No¹         | Yes    | No      | DFA, codegen to C       | Basic     |
| sedlex         | PPX       | No¹         | Yes    | Yes     | DFA, codegen to OCaml   | Limited   |
| Re/Tyre        | OCaml     | Yes         | No     | No³     | Online determinization² | Extended⁴ |
| ppx_regex/tyre | PPX+OCaml | Yes         | No     | No      | Online determinization² | Extended⁴ |

¹: Some built-in mechanism for locally defining regex exists, but no true composition. \\
²: There are some things to determinize offline, but they need refreshing \\
³: https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-re/pull/48 \\
⁴: Within regularity. Lacks full blown complementation. See also [this paper](https://www.home.hs-karlsruhe.de/~suma0002/publications/cc14-flexible-lexing-via-extended-regex.pdf).

My plans would not be to try to improve sedlex, but rather to push ~re~ (and the
related libraries) to the point where it's universally better. Ppx_regexp/tyre
provides a convenient "ocamlex" like syntax while preserving composition. The
first step would be a refill mechanism, and support for UTF (for which @nojb
made a prototype that would need revival).

Performances are a tricky question. Ocamllex is clearly faster, since it
generates a C-based DFA. I expect sedlex to be faster than re in small examples,
but it would need evaluation. Online determinization is very desirable in many
contexts.

wrt. Unicode libraries: At least for sedlex, it was designed so that bunzli's
libraries can be used before giving the stream to sedlex. Either to re-encode,
or to normalize. I think that's a decen way of doing things.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>james woodyatt then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
First off, I'm pleased to see sedlex getting some love finally. Very grateful to the community for that.

I would like to add here that my forthcoming _Orsetto_ project includes another
[alternative](https://bitbucket.org/jhw/orsetto/src/unstable/src/ucs/ucs_regx.mli)
to _sedlex_ that might be worth noting, although it
[has](https://bitbucket.org/jhw/orsetto/issues/7/unicode-regular-expression-level-2-support)
[issues](https://bitbucket.org/jhw/orsetto/issues/6/unicode-regular-expression-level-1-support)
and it remains in the "unstable" branch while I'm slowly working on it in my
copious spare time.

I would describe it here as follows:

|Library|Syntax|Composition|Unicode|Automaton|Regexs|
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
|Orsetto.UCS|OCaml|Yes|Yes|Lazy DFA|Basic¹|

¹: A subset of UTS #18, RL1 (no loose matching, word or line boundaries, etc.)

Also, I'm not sure what "refill" means here, so I didn't characterize it.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>An implementation of the Noise Protocol Framework</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-an-implementation-of-the-noise-protocol-framework/2539/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Etienne Millon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am announcing the first release of [noise](https://github.com/emillon/ocaml-noise), an implementation of the [Noise Protocol Framework](https://noiseprotocol.org/).

It contains building blocks to implement a secure protocol with confidentiality
and authentication on top of modern cryptographic primitives. This protocol
framework is used by
[WhatsApp](https://www.whatsapp.com/security/WhatsApp-Security-Whitepaper.pdf),
[WireGuard](https://www.wireguard.com/), and
[Lightning](https://github.com/lightningnetwork/lightning-rfc/blob/master/08-transport.md).

This is still a very early version:
- it contains some custom implementations of cryptographic primitives
- the interface is unstable
- most applications need a higher level protocol like [NoiseSocket](https://noisesocket.org/), which is comparable to TLS

Next on my roadmap is implementing a WireGuard client and server that can be used in [Mirage](https://mirage.io/).

If you are interested in implementing a protocol that uses Noise, please get in touch!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Release of Bindlib 5.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/release-of-bindlib-5-0/2541/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Rodolphe Lepigre announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am pleased to announce the release of Bindlib 5.0.1, which is a library for
handling structures with bound (and free) variables (typical applications
include the development of languages and proof systems). It has already been
available on Opam for several weeks, and the source code of the latest version
can be found in the [development
repository](https://github.com/rlepigre/ocaml-bindlib).

This new version provides a simpler, more concise interface. It is extensively
documented, and includes a small tutorial. An [introductory
paper](http://eptcs.web.cse.unsw.edu.au/paper.cgi?LFMTP2018.4) has also been
recently presented at the LFMTP 2018 workshop.

Bindlib has already been used in fairly big projects (from the most recent):
[Lambdapi](https://github.com/rlepigre/lambdapi),
[PML₂](https://github.com/rlepigre/pml),
[SubML](https://rlepigre.github.io/subml/),
[PML](https://lama.univ-savoie.fr/tracpml), and many other smaller prototypes.

The implementation is very efficient (in terms of substitution), and it handles renaming to avoid capture.

Feel free to give feedback!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocaml Github Pull Requests</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>Gabriel Scherer and the editor compiled this list</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here is a sneak peek at some potential future features of the Ocaml
compiler, discussed by their implementers in these Github Pull Requests.

- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/2024][Stop supporting obsolete platforms]]
- [[https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/pull/2027][{WIP} Deprecated optional arguments]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
