<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2019.01.08</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2019.01.01</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2019.01.15</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>January 01 to 08, 2019</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Opam 2 ppa available for Ubuntu Trusty/Xenial/Bionic/Cosmic now</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/opam-2-ppa-available-for-ubuntu-trusty-xenial-bionic-cosmic-now/3122/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
After a couple of requests, I’ve refreshed the opam2 PPA infrastructure to make binary packages available for more variants of Ubuntu for the latest stable release of opam (2.0.2). The new support for Ubuntu Trusty and Xenial builds means that the ppa can be used with Travis CI for non-container based builds.  Travis does not currently support Bionic, and so Xenial is the latest available there.

In order to support these older distros, I've also packaged up Bubblewrap for the older Ubuntu distributions.  This is of course an unofficial backport, so let me know if you run into any problems with it.

The packages currently sit in my PPA tree at [avsm/ppa-opam](https://launchpad.net/~avsm/+archive/ubuntu/ppa), and can be used by simple adding:

#+begin_src shell
sudo add-apt-repository ppa:avsm/ppa
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get -y install opam
#+end_src

to your CI scripts.

Sources to the scripts and more information in the README:

https://github.com/avsm/opam2-ppa

If anyone would like to help with including opam 2 in more upstream distributions, please [refer to the distributions wiki ](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/wiki/Distributions) and pick your favourite OS :slight_smile:
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Interesting OCaml Articles</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/interesting-ocaml-articles/1867/38</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
@ostera has started live-casting programming sessions on major OCaml libraries, written in Reason syntax (which is easy enough for OCamlers to understand). Highly recommended!

His twitch videos are [here](https://www.twitch.tv/ostera/videos). Make sure to show up and chat for his live streams!
For posterity (since twitch deletes old videos), his youtube channel is [here](https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC8318qJJvq1VjFVXtc75J9Q/videos).

I'd love to see more of this kind of thing from the community -- new users are much more likely to want to watch a fun programming session than to read something.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>opam 2.0.2!</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-opam-2-0-2/3046/12</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Perry E. Metzger announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
MacPorts is now updated to opam 2.0.2; sorry for the delay.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[https://tarides.com/blog.html#2019-01-03-how-configurator-reads-c-constants][How configurator reads C constants]]
- [[http://roscidus.com/blog/blog/2019/01/01/using-tla-plus-to-understand-xen-vchan/][Using TLA+ to understand Xen vchan]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
