<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2019.11.26</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2019.11.19</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2019.12.03</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>November 19 to 26, 2019</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>tiny_httpd 0.1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-tiny-httpd-0-1/4727/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Simon Cruanes announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello and good morning, I'm pleased to announce that [tiny_httpd](https://github.com/c-cube/tiny_httpd) 0.1 has been released and is on opam.

The goal is to emulate python's standard ~http.server~ by providing a 0-dependencies, minimalist, simple HTTP server for embedding in applications that are not primarily a website, with very basic routing (thanks to ~Scanf~). A binary ~http_of_dir~ is also distributed and can be used to serve a directory, with optional upload of files.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>printbox.0.3</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-printbox-0-3/4731/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Simon Cruanes announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
https://aws1.discourse-cdn.com/standard11/uploads/ocaml/original/2X/8/8e7c55c5ab69c12f53a7862d2f84dd6e0cfc0dc0.png

#+begin_src ocaml
let b =
  let open PrintBox in
  PrintBox_unicode.setup();
  frame @@ grid_l [
    [text "subject"; text_with_style Style.bold "announce: printbox 0.3"];
    [text "explanation";
    frame @@ text {|PrintBox is a library for rendering nested tables,
    trees, and similar structures in monospace text or HTML.|}];
    [text "github";
    text_with_style Style.(bg_color Blue) "https://github.com/c-cube/printbox/releases/tag/0.3"];
    [text "contributors";
     vlist_map (text_with_style Style.(fg_color Green)) ["Simon"; "Guillaume"; "Matt"]];
    [text "dependencies";
    tree empty
      [tree (text "mandatory")
         [text "dune"; text "bytes"];
       tree (text "optional")
         [text "uutf"; text "uucp"; text "tyxml"]]];
    [text "expected reaction"; text "🎉"];
  ]

let () = print_endline @@ PrintBox_text.to_string b
#+end_src

([actual link to the release](https://github.com/c-cube/printbox/releases/tag/0.3))
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>v0.13 release of Jane Street packages</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-v0-13-release-of-jane-street-packages/4735/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Xavier Clerc announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are pleased to announce the v0.13 release of Jane Street packages!

This release comes with 14 new packages, and a number of fixes and
enhancements. The documentation for this release is available on our
website:

    https://ocaml.janestreet.com/ocaml-core/v0.13/doc/

The remainder of this mail highlights the main changes since the v0.12
release; we hope it will be useful to developers in the process of
migrating to the new version. A comprehensive changelog is available
at the end.

*** Notable changes

- Changed ~Base~, ~Core_kernel~, and ~Core~ functions to raise
  ~Not_found_s~ instead of ~Not_found~.  ~Hashtbl.find_exn~ and
  ~Map.find_exn~ now include the key in their error message.

- Changed ~Core~ and ~Core_kernel~ to export ~int~ comparison rather
  than polymorphic comparison.

- Removed the "robust" float comparison operators (~&gt;.~, ~=.~, ...)
  from the default namespace.

- Replaced ~sexp_*~ types (~sexp_list~, ~sexp_option~, ~sexp_opaque~,
  ...) with preprocessor attributes (~[@sexp.list]~, ~[@sexp.option]~,
  ~[@sexp.opaque]~, ...).

- Changed ~let%map~ syntax from ~let%map.Foo.Let_syntax~ to
  ~let%map.Foo~.

- Added to ~match%optional~ support for specifying a path, so you can
  write ~match%optional.Foo foo_option~ rather than ~let open
  Foo.Optional_syntax in match%optional foo_option~.

- Improved ~Base.Backtrace~ so that it enables recording of backtraces
  in more situations, specifically when ~OCAMLRUNPARAM~ is defined but
  doesn't mention the backtrace flag, ~b~.

- Added javascript support for ~Zarith~, ~Bigint~, ~Bignum~, and
  ~Bigdecimal~.

- Changed ~Hashtbl.create~'s default ~size~ from 128 to 0.

- Changed ~Core_kernel.Command~ so that all commands accept double
  dash flags: ~--help~, ~--version~, and ~--build-info~.


*** New packages

- async_udp (https://github.com/janestreet/async_udp): UDP support for
  Async.

- async_websocket (https://github.com/janestreet/async_websocket):
  A library that implements the websocket protocol on top of Async.

- bonsai (https://github.com/janestreet/bonsai): A library for building
  dynamic webapps, using Js_of_ocaml.

- postgres_async (https://github.com/janestreet/postgres_async):
  OCaml/async implementation of the postgres protocol (i.e., does not
  use C-bindings to libpq).

- ppx_cold (https://github.com/janestreet/ppx_cold): Expands ~[@cold]~
  into ~[@inline never][@specialise never][@local never]~.

- ppx_pattern_bind (https://github.com/janestreet/ppx_pattern_bind):
  A ppx for writing fast incremental bind nodes in a pattern match.

- ppx_python (https://github.com/janestreet/ppx_python):
  ~[@@deriving]~ plugin to generate Python conversion functions.

- ppx_yojson_conv (https://github.com/janestreet/ppx_yojson_conv):
  ~[@@deriving]~ plugin to generate Yojson conversion functions.

- ppx_yojson_conv_lib (https://github.com/janestreet/ppx_yojson_conv_lib):
  Runtime lib for ~ppx_yojson_conv~.

- pythonlib (https://github.com/janestreet/pythonlib): A library to
  help writing wrappers around OCaml code for python.

- sexp_select (https://github.com/janestreet/sexp_select): A library
  to use CSS-style selectors to traverse sexp trees.

- timezone (https://github.com/janestreet/timezone): Time-zone handling.

- toplevel_backend (https://github.com/janestreet/toplevel_backend):
  Shared backend for setting up toplevels.

- zarith_stubs_js (https://github.com/janestreet/zarith_stubs_js):
  Javascript stubs for the Zarith library.


*** Deprecations / Removals

~Async_kernel~:

- Deprecated monadic ~ignore~ functions in favor of ~ignore_m~.

~Base~:

- Deleted ~Array.replace~ and ~replace_all~ functions, which have been
  deprecated since before the last public release.

- Deprecated ~Result.ok_unit~; use ~Ok ()~.

- Removed the ~Monad~ and ~Applicative~ interfaces' ~all_ignore~
  function; it was previously deprecated and replaced by ~all_unit~.

- Removed ~List.dedup~, which has been deprecated since 2017-04.

- Removed ~String~ mutation functions, which have been deprecated in
  favor of ~Bytes~ since 2017-10.

- Deprecated ~Array.truncate~, ~Obj_array.unsafe_truncate~, and
  ~Uniform_array.unsafe_truncate~.

- Deprecated ~Sys.argv~, which has been superseded by ~get_argv~,
  which is a function, reflecting the fact that ~argv~ can change (as
  of OCaml 4.09).

~Core_kernel~:

- Removed ~Core_kernel.Std~, which had been deprecated for a year.

- Deprecated type ~Command.Spec.param~ in favor of ~Command.Param.t~.

- Removed ~Hashtbl~ functions that had been deprecated for years.

- Removed ~Float.to_string_round_trippable~, which has been deprecated
  in favor of ~to_string~ since 2017-04.

- Deprecated ~Fqueue~ functions where one should use ~Fdeque~ instead:
  ~bot~, ~bot_exn~, and ~enqueue_top~.

- Deleted ~Bus.unsubscribes~, which will be obviated by a performance
  improvement to ~Bus.unsubscribe~.

~Timing_wheel~:

- Removed the ~alarm_upper_bound~ function, which has been deprecated
  for 6 months, and superseded by ~max_allowed_alarm_time~.


*** Moves

~Core_kernel~:

- Moved ~Bounded_int_table~ to a standalone library.

- Moved the ~Pool~ and ~Tuple_type~ modules to a standalone library,
  ~Tuple_pool~.

~Async_unix~:

- Moved ~Unix.Fd.replace~ into a ~Private~ submodule.


*** Changelog

Please visit https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-v0-13-release-of-jane-street-packages/4735
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>opam2nix (v1)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-opam2nix-v1/4741/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Tim Cuthbertson announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Anouncing opam2nix (v1)

[opam2nix](https://github.com/timbertson/opam2nix) generates [nix](https://nixos.org/) expressions from the [opam](https://opam.ocaml.org/) OCaml package repository. It works similarly to [bundix](https://github.com/nix-community/bundix), [node2nix](https://github.com/svanderburg/node2nix), etc:

You run an (impure) command to resolve all transitive dependency versions using the current opam repository, generating a .nix file that locks down the exact package sources and versions. Then this file can be imported to provide ~buildInputs~ for building your ocaml project in nix.

*What is nix and why would I care?* Well, that's a long story but the headline benefits of nix are:

- reproducible builds (if it builds for me, it builds for you)
- stateless (you don't set up switches and then install packages, each expression specifies everything it needs, and anything you don't have is fetched/built on demand)
- language agnostic (takes care of non-ocaml dependencies)

It's sadly not a shallow learning curve, but those benefits are hard to find elsewhere, so I obviously think it's worthwhile. So if you use nix (or would like to), please give it a try and provide feedback. I'll (slowly) start working on upstreaming it into nixpkgs.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>GitHub Actions for OCaml / opam now available</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/github-actions-for-ocaml-opam-now-available/4745/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I was in the [GitHub Actions](https://github.com/actions) beta program and forward ported my code to the latest version that just went public.  It's a pretty simple way to get your OCaml code tested on Linux, macOS and Windows, without requiring an external CI service.  The action attempts to provide a homogenous interface across all three operating systems, so invoking 'opam' from subsequent actions should "just work".

You can find it here:
- In the GitHub Marketplace at https://github.com/marketplace/actions/setup-ocaml
- Source code on &lt;https://github.com/avsm/setup-ocaml/&gt;
- Hello World usage on &lt;https://github.com/avsm/hello-world-action-ocaml&gt;
- Usage in ocaml-yaml:
  - https://github.com/avsm/ocaml-yaml/blob/master/.github/workflows/test.yml
  - An [example ocaml-yaml run](https://github.com/avsm/ocaml-yaml/runs/314055554)

This should be considered fairly experimental as GH Actions is so new.  If you do use it, then consider [updating this issue with your usage](https://github.com/avsm/setup-ocaml/issues/4).  It does not current supporting caching yet, but is pretty fast to bootstrap (~4minutes).

It also doesn't have any higher level purpose other than to set up an opam environment, since most of the additional functionality such as revdeps testing is planned for addition to the [ocurrent DSL](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocurrent-0-1-ci-cd-pipeline-edsl/4742/2).   Nevertheless, this GH feature will hopefully be useful for smaller projects without a lot of computational requirements.   Let me know how it goes!

Windows is currently supported through @fdopen's excellent fork that uses Cygwin.   As Windows support is being mainlined into opam itself at the moment, I'm hoping that we will gradually move over to that.  That should eventually remove the need for two separate opam-repositories, so I won't be adding any features that are Linux or macOS-specific and do not work on the Cygwin version.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCurrent 0.1 (CI/CD pipeline eDSL)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocurrent-0-1-ci-cd-pipeline-edsl/4742/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Thomas Leonard announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[OCurrent](https://github.com/ocurrent/ocurrent) 0.1 has just been released to opam-repository.

OCurrent is an OCaml eDSL intended for writing build/test/deploy pipelines. It is being used as the engine for [ocaml-ci](https://github.com/ocurrent/ocaml-ci/) and the [docker-base-images](https://github.com/ocurrent/docker-base-images) builder (used to build the OCaml Docker images, such as ~ocurrent/opam:alpine-3.10-ocaml-4.08~). Other good uses might be building and redeploying a Docker service or a unikernel whenever its source repository changes. It can be run locally as a single Unix process.

An OCurrent pipeline is written as an OCaml program, but the OCurrent engine ensures that it is kept up-to-date by re-running stages when their inputs change. A web UI is available so you can view your pipeline and see its current state.

OCurrent can statically analyse the pipelines before they have run, allowing it to run steps in parallel automatically and to display the whole pipeline. It does this using a light-weight alternative to arrows, which doesn't require programming in an awkward point-free style. See
[CI/CD Pipelines: Monad, Arrow or Dart?](https://roscidus.com/blog/blog/2019/11/14/cicd-pipelines/) for more about that.

The basic functionality can be extended using "plugins" (just normal OCaml libraries). Plugins are available for interacting with Docker, Git, GitHub and Slack. These are in separate packages (e.g. ~current_github~) to avoid having the base package pull in too many dependencies).

There is also an optional Cap'n Proto RPC interface, in the ~current_rpc~ opam package. This is used, for example, by [citty](https://github.com/ocurrent/citty) to provide a TTY interface to ocaml-ci.

[The OCurrent wiki](https://github.com/ocurrent/ocurrent/wiki) contains examples, and documentation on the various plugins.

Here's an example pipeline (from the base image builder):

https://roscidus.com/blog/images/cicd/docker-base-images-thumb.png
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
For those curious about the relation to the existing CI used in opam-repository, then it is no coincidence that @talex5 is the author of both :-)

This DSL is the next iteration of the [datakit-ci](https://github.com/moby/datakit), but specialised to be faster and simpler for extending with OCaml and more complex workflows that our OCaml Platform tools need these days (like ocamlformat linting, or dune expect promotion, or odoc cross-referenced doc generation).  We are planning a smooth migration next year over to the new system, but wanted to release this early to show you some of the pieces going into this new iteration.  I am particularly excited about the new tty-based interface that saves an awful lot of clicking around on web UIs for CI results...
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New pages for OCaml API</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/new-pages-for-ocaml-api/4720/13</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, sanette announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I have uploaded a new version (same link https://sanette.github.io/ocaml-api/)
- background color for links in the TOC @Maelan
- more indentation for value descriptions @Maelan,  @grayswandyr
- word wrapping long ~&lt;pre&gt;~ codes @grayswandyr
- type table: remove ~(*~ and ~*)~, give more space to code wrt comments, diminish comment's color @grayswandyr

searching is not ready yet... please wait
suggestions for dark theme welcome
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>sanette later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I have just uploaded a new version with a basic search engine.
- for each page, you can search values/modules
- in the general index page, the search includes also the descriptions
- search results are ranked by relevance

the downside is that each page now comes with an index of about 570Kb in the form of an index.js file. I'm kind of hoping that the browser will cache this, but I'm not sure. It would be maybe better to only load the index file on demand.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Irmin 2.0.0 release</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-irmin-2-0-0-release/4746/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Thomas Gazagnaire announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
On behalf of the Irmin development team, I am very happy to announce the release of Irmin 2.0.0, a major release of the Git-like distributed branching and storage substrate that underpins [MirageOS](https://mirage.io/). We began the release process for all the components that make up Irmin [back in May 2019](https://tarides.com/blog/2019-05-13-on-the-road-to-irmin-v2), and there have been close to 1000 commits since Irmin 1.4.0 released back in June 2018. To celebrate this milestone, we have a new logo and opened a dedicated website: [irmin.org](https://irmin.org/).

More details here: https://tarides.com/blog/2019-11-21-irmin-v2
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Tail cascade: a new indentation style for some OCaml constructs</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/tail-cascade-a-new-indentation-style-for-some-ocaml-constructs/4736/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>gasche announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I recently decided to change my indentation style for certain OCaml constructs in a way that I'm going to describe below. I just coined a name for this approach, "tail cascade". I'm creating this topic to convince everyone that this is a cool idea you should adopt as well. Or at least tolerate it when you review other people's code.

*** Problem

Programs that heavily use ~match~ often see a shift to the right due to nested indentation.

#+begin_src ocaml
match foo with
| Foo -> ...
| Bar x ->
  match bar x with
  | FooBar -> ...
  | Blah y ->
    match f y with
    | Some z ->
      ...
#+end_src

Another problem with this style is that it suffers from the "dangling bar" issue: if you try to add a new case for one of the exterior ~match~, it is parsed as belonging to the innermost ~match~. People have been recommending (rightly) to use ~begin match .. end~ for all nested match constructs to avoid this issue.

#+begin_src ocaml
match foo with
| Foo -> ...
| Bar x ->
  begin match bar x with
  | FooBar -> ...
  | Blah y ->
    begin match f y with
    | None -> ...
    | Some z ->
      ...
    end
  (* now this is safe *)
  | FooBlah -> ...
  end
#+end_src

But still the unpleasant shift to the right remains.

*** Proposal: cascading tail case

We should in general use ~begin match .. end~ for nested matches. But the "cascading tail case" proposal is to *not* do it for the *last* case of the pattern-matching, and instead *de-indent* (dedent) this last case -- tail case.

#+begin_src ocaml
match foo with
| Foo -> ...
| Bar x ->
match bar x with
| FooBar -> ...
| Blah y ->
match f y with
| None -> ...
| Some z ->
...
#+end_src

Note that with this indentation style, the "dangling match" problem is also avoided: unlike with the original, non ~end~-protected program, the indentation makes it immediately obvious that any further case will be attached to the innermost match, and not any of the exterior ones.

A program using this "cascading tail" approach should always use ~begin match .. end~ for nested matches, except for a nested match returned within the last branch of an outer match, which can (optionally) be dedented instead.

The choice to dedent the last case corresponds to encouraging a sequential reading of the program, where the other cases are "auxiliary cases" checked first and dispatched quickly, and the last case is the "main part" where the "rest" of the logic of the program lies. This pattern is typical of nested pattern-matching on the ~option~ or ~result~ type for example:

#+begin_src ocaml
match foo x with
| Error err ->
  fail_foo_error err
| Ok y ->
match bar y with
| Error err ->
  fail_bar_error err
| Ok () ->
...
#+end_src

Remark: it is *not* always the case that the ~Error~ constructor is the auxiliary case, and the ~Ok~ constructor is the main case; sometimes we implement fallback logic like "if ~foo~ work then we are good, but otherwise we have to do this and that", and the error case is the most salient (and longer) part of the program logic. I would recommend being mindful, when you write code, of whether there is a most convincing way to "sequentialize" it (distinguish auxiliary and main/tail case), and avoid using cascading tails when there is no clear sequentialization choice.

Remark: some cases of tail cascades can be linearized by using a good definition of "bind" and a monadic style. This tends to be very limited however: it fixes one of the constructors to always be the "tail" constructor (always ~Some~, always ~Ok~), and it only works when the handling of the other constructors is very homogeneous (typically: return directly). In real code, many situations occur where the monadic style doesn't fit the problem, but tail cascade does help writing a readable program.


*** Generalization: tail cascade

While I have never seen cascading tail cases in real-world OCaml code before (I'm happy to be given pointers; I think that the idea is not new, but I'm not aware of previous attempts to give it a catchy name and spread the cascade love), this is in fact a new (to me) instance of a common technique that is used for other OCaml constructs:

#+begin_src ocaml
if foo x then ...
else if bar x then ...
else ... (* this `tail else` was dedented *)

let x = foo in
let y = bar in (* this `tail let` was dedented *)
...            (* and the rest as well *)

bind foo @@ fun x ->
bind bar @@ fun y -> (* this "tail function body" was dedented *)
...                  (* and the rest as well *)
#+end_src

I would call "tail cascade" (or maybe: "cascading tail") the idea of dedenting the "rest" of an OCaml expression (compared to a strict tree-nesting-based approach) when it morally describes the "rest" of the expression. I use the name "tail" because those expressions are almost always in tail-position in the sense of tail-calls.

This general approach legitimizes some styles that I have seen, and sometimes used, in the wild, while at the same time considering that I may have been doing something improper, for example:

#+begin_src ocaml
if foo then blah else
... (* dedented *)


Fun.protect
  ~finally:(...)
@@ fun () ->
... (* dedented *)


try simple_approach with exn ->
... (* dedented *)


1 +
2 + (* dedented *)
... (* dedented *)
#+end_src

Remark: after a ~then~ or ~else~, many people share the reasonable view that any expression containing imperative constructs (~foo; bar~) should be enclosed in a ~begin .. end~ block to avoid surprising-precedence issue. Just as for nested ~match~, this recommendation should be lifted for "tail else" constructs.

Remark: The last example is a case where the dedented expressions are *not* in tail-position from a runtime-evaluation point of view. I am not sure as whether the two notions should be made to coincide more strongly, but in any case I'm not fond of the style in this particular example, I prefer to move the infix operator to the beginning of the next line instead, following a different style and justification.

The possibility this "cascading tail" style today crucially relies on the nesting properties of open-ended syntactic constructs, notably ~let~ (commonly cascaded), and now ~match~ and ~if ... else~. Proposals to transition to a syntax where ~match~ and ~else~ are forced to take a closing marker are incompatible with the cascading style. I have not made my mind on whether this should be considered a blocker for those proposals, but at least it shows that having the open-ended form available has value for certain programs.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Louis Gesbert then said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
@gasche I prototyped a dedicated option in ~ocp-indent~, if you're interested in trying it out :)
#+begin_src shell
opam pin git+https://github.com/OCamlPro/ocp-indent#match-tail-cascade
echo "match_tail_cascade=true" >> ~/.ocp-indent
#+end_src
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
