<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2020.10.20</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2020.10.13</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2020.10.27</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>October 13 to 20, 2020</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Dialo is hiring frontend and backend OCaml developers (Remote)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/dialo-is-hiring-frontend-and-backend-ocaml-developers-remote/6604/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Wojtek Czekalski announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[Dialo](https://dialo.ai) is an early stage company with an experienced founding team. Assembling a
team that consists of the best and brightest is our top priority. In the immediate term we are building
a visual programming language for conversational AI. Our long term vision is that personalized contact
we are enabling will cause deeper relationships between users and businesses and turn all interactions
into a unified long term customer journey.

The work is quite demanding when it comes to both ideation and implementation. We are aiming to provide
a room for growth both technically and/or as a leader. For current open source maintainers we are
willing to sponsor your work on OSS for 20% of time.

We use OCaml for frontend and backend (along with Python for machine learning, natural language
processing). We are hiring people for different positions. Both people with extensive experience and
newcomers are encouraged to apply. We try to find the sharpest people rather than checking boxes with
particular skills.

The official job posting:
https://dialo.recruitee.com/o/software-developer-ocamlreason
We are also hiring for two other (related) positions:
- https://dialo.recruitee.com/o/software-developer-frontend
- https://dialo.recruitee.com/o/software-developer-backend
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Progress 0.1.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-progress-0-1-0/6607/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Craig Ferguson announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the first release of [~Progress~](https://github.com/CraigFe/progress/), now
available on Opam.

#+ATTR_HTML: :fallback https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CraigFe/progress/main/.meta/example.svg
https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CraigFe/progress/main/.meta/example.svg

~Progress~ is a small library for quickly defining and using progress bars in OCaml programs. It aims
to provide the following:

- support for rendering multiple progress bars simultaneously;
- responds dynamically to changes in terminal size;
- allows user-defined progress bar layouts.

*** Defining your own progress bars

The example animation above uses a pre-provided progress bar layout that should meet many needs
([~Progress_unix.counter~](https://craigfe.github.io/progress/progress/Progress_unix/index.html#val-counter)),
but it's fairly easy to re-define it ourselves using the low-level
[~Progress.Segment~](https://craigfe.github.io/progress/progress/Progress/Segment/index.html) API:

#+begin_src ocaml
let counter filename =
  let proportion i = Int64.to_float i /. 1_000_000. in
  let open Progress in
  Segment.(
    list
      [
        const filename;
        Units.bytes of_pp;
        Progress_unix.stopwatch ();
        bar ~mode:`ASCII proportion;
        using proportion (Units.percentage of_pp);
      ]
    |> box_winsize ~fallback:80  (* Dynamically scale to window size *)
    |> periodic 100              (* Re-render once every 100 updates *)
    |> accumulator Int64.add 0L  (* Accumulate progress updates *))
  |> make ~init:0L
#+end_src

The ~Segment~ combinators are similar to those of general-purpose pretty-printing libraries (e.g.
[~pp~](https://github.com/ocaml-dune/pp) and [~fmt~](https://erratique.ch/software/fmt)), but are
equipped with extra logic for "stateful" segments and segments that can have dynamic width. Together,
these make for a convenient way to express common patterns when pretty-printing progress bars. For
instance, the stateful segment ~periodic~ seen above can be used to ensure that very frequent updates
from a hot-loop do not result in too much time spent re-rendering the output.

The library is not yet feature-complete, but should still be reasonably useful :slightly_smiling_face:
Happy hacking!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Brr 0.0.1, a toolkit for programming browsers</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-brr-0-0-1-a-toolkit-for-programming-browsers/6608/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Daniel Bünzli announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'd like to announce the first release of Brr.

The TL; DR is:
#+begin_quote
If you are looking for a productive way to program browsers with js_of_ocaml but without ppx and
ghost OCaml objects, give Brr a try.
#+end_quote

The details:

#+begin_quote
Brr is a toolkit for programming browsers in OCaml with the [~js_of_ocaml~](https://ocsigen.org/js_of_ocaml) compiler. It provides:
- Interfaces to a [selection](https://erratique.ch/software/brr/doc/index.html#supported_apis) of browser APIs.
- Note based reactive support (optional and experimental).
- An [OCaml console](https://erratique.ch/software/brr/doc/ocaml_console.html) developer tool for live interaction with programs running in web pages.
- A JavaScript FFI for idiomatic OCaml programming.

Brr is distributed under the ISC license. It depends on [Note](https://erratique.ch/software/note) and on the ~js_of_ocaml~
compiler and runtime – but not on its libraries or syntax extension.
#+end_quote

- Homepage: https://erratique.ch/software/brr
- API Docs &amp; manuals: https://erratique.ch/software/brr/doc/ or ~odig doc brr~
- Install: ~opam install brr~

Brr is essentially what I need to be productive for browser programming with js_of_ocaml: an obvious
FFI with JavaScript objects as abstract data types without OCaml object phantom types and binding
documentation precisely linking into MDN.

The OCaml console is the hack on the cake. In the past I often found it frustrating to  have OCaml
programs running in my webpages and be greeted with a JavaScript  prompt in the browser dev tools.
Quite a bit of polishing could be done on that  though. Some of which should likely directly be done
upstream in the toplevel  machinery (e.g. identifier completion, a better toploop API and support for
easy pretty printer installation). It would also be nice if we could cut down on ~js_of_ocaml~'s
toplevel compilation times ;--)

Parts of Brr have been seriously dogfooded in the past but that new incarnation is largely untested for
now and certain APIs might need adjustements. Early adopters should study actual binding coverage,
expect glitches and little breakages in the future.

The Note reactive functionality was also seriously used in the past but Note itself needs a new design
round and I don't have the ressources to do it right now, expect breakage, don't pay too much attention
to it for now.

My thanks to the ~js_of_ocaml~ developers for the nice ocaml to javascript compiler and a special
shootout to Hugo Heuzard for not getting mad at me when pinging him directly for questions.

Happy browser compatibility bug hunting,
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>gasche asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It's not really released, but I'm curious about [Note](https://erratique.ch/software/note) now: this is
a new FRP library from you, the author of [React](https://erratique.ch/software/react) (the FRP library
for OCaml, not the Javascript framework of the same name).

Would you say a few words on why you went for a different library? My guess would be that React depends
on runtime mechanisms (weak pointers) that are not well-supported in Javascript-lang; but even if the
guess is right, I'm not sure what would be the impact on the API or properties of the library.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Daniel Bünzli replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
Would you say a few words on why you went for a different library?
#+end_quote

~Note~ is the result from seeing people (and myself) struggling to use ~React~/FRP "correctly" over the
years.

Some of this, I largely attribute to ergonomic problems with the API. It's my hope for ~Note~ to
address most of these points (one thing that still needs to be done is replace fix points by a simple
lazy infinitesimal delay combinator).

I don't think I could have made all these changes in ~React~ itself so I found it better to start a new
library. Also I lost the trademark on the name :--)

~Note~ also tries to provide a much simpler implementation. ~React~'s implementation was based on the
[FrTime Phd thesis](http://cs.brown.edu/people/ghcooper/thesis.pdf). It's quite subtle and involved
and, as you suggested, uses weak pointer. ~Note~ tries to avoid them since those are not available in
the browser (but you have things like
[MutationObservers](https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/MutationObserver) which I use as
gc in Brr's Note-based [reactive dom
support](https://erratique.ch/software/brr/doc/Brr_note/Elr/index.html)).

However not using weak pointers has a semantic uncleanness cost whose impact I'm unsure yet – without
discipline from the programmer it may lead to subtle and hard to track bugs when the reactive graph
changes dynamically, which I'm a bit wary of.

When my brain dumped ~Note~ I wrote a few more technical points in the readme you can read them
[here](https://github.com/dbuenzli/note#history).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New release of Conduit</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-new-release-of-conduit/6611/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Calascibetta Romain announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
*Conduit 3.0.0*

Hello everyone,

We're glad to announce the new release of [~conduit~](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-conduit), a framework  that allows to _abstract_
over transfer protocols. One of its main advantages  is allowing the implemententation of
_free-dependencies_ protocols.

*** Introduction

There are several ways to abstract over an implementation in OCaml. However, those solutions are often
lost deep in the stack of protocols and allowing the user to choose the implementations of the
sub-procotols implies growing complexity as we move up through the stack. (For example, allowing to
abstract over the implementation of the TLS protocol from the implementation of the HTTP protocol)

One of those solutions, the _functors_, can rapidly become a hellish nightmare for the end-user. This
is especially true in the case of MirageOS, which literally wants to abstract over everything!

This is why Conduit was implemented: it aims to provide to the user a cleaner abstraction mechanism
which would allow the protocol developers to get rid of most of the responsibilities concerning the
choice of sub-protocols (Like which TLS implementation use between OpenSSL or our great
[ocaml-tls](https://github.com/mirleft/ocaml-tls) library), while giving the end-users an easy way to compose the protocols of
their choice and inject them in the stack via conduit.

*** Usage of Conduit

Such a framework allows us to separate the logic of a protocol from underlying implementation needed to
communicate with a peer. The distribution of Conduit comes with [a simple tutorial](https://mirage.github.io/ocaml-conduit/conduit/howto.html) which
explains step by step how to implement a _ping-pong_ client &amp; server and, most importantly, how to
upgrade them with TLS.

With Conduit, we ensure the compatibility with MirageOS (and specially [mirage-tcpip](https://github.com/mirage/mirage-tcpip))
while being useful for others. Of course, Conduit is not mandatory to ensure this compatibility, but it
helps us for _higher_ libraries such as [ocaml-git](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-git)/[Irmin](https://github.com/mirage/irmin) or [Cohttp](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp).

*** Specific improvements

**** Abstract and destruct it!

The most requested feature on the new version of Conduit is the ability to _destruct_ the
[Conduit.flow][conduit-flow]. The ability to abstract the protocol comes with the _abstract_ type
~Conduit.flow~. The new version permits to _destruct_ it to a well-known value (such as an UNIX
socket):

#+begin_src ocaml
let handler flow = match flow with
  | Conduit_lwt.TCP.T (Value file_descr) ->
    let peer = Lwt_unix.getpeername file_descr in
    ...
  | flow -> ... (* other kind of protocol *)

let run =
  Cohttp_lwt_unix.serve ~handler
    { sockaddr= Unix.inet_addr_loopback }
#+end_src

**** The dispatch of the protocol

The second most interesting feature of Conduit is the full control over the dispatch between protocols
by the end-user. From a concrete information such as an ~Uri.t~, the end-user is able to describe how
Conduit should choose the protocol (and with which value it should try to initiate the connection):

#+begin_src ocaml
let my_tls_config = Tls.Config.client ...

let connect uri =
  let edn = Conduit.Endpoint.of_string
    (Uri.host_with_default ~default:"localhost" uri) in
  let resolvers = match Uri.scheme uri with
    | Some "https" ->
      let port = Option.value ~default:443 (Uri.port uri) in
      Conduit_lwt.add
        Conduit_lwt_tls.TCP.protocol
        (Conduit_lwt_tls.TCP.resolve ~port ~config:my_tls_config)
        Conduit.empty
    | Some "http" | None ->
      let port = Option.value ~default:80 (Uri.port uri) in
      Conduit_lwt.add
        Conduit_lwt.TCP.protocol
        (Conduit_lwt.TCP.resolve ~port)
        Conduit.empty in
  Conduit_lwt.resolve ~resolvers edn >>= fun flow ->
  ...
#+end_src

**** An explicit way to launch a server

Conduit comes with a new API for the server-side, where everything becomes explicit: no dispatch, no
hidden choice. It proposes now a simple function to start the usual server loop:

#+begin_src ocaml
let run handler =
  Conduit_lwt.serve ~handler
    Conduit_lwt.TCP.service
    { Conduit_lwt.TCP.sockaddr= Unix.(ADDR_INET (inet_addr_loopback, 8080)
    ; capacity= 40 }
#+end_src

*** Reverse-dependencies

Conduit is used by many libraries (~150 packages) and we spend 2 months to track this breaking-change.
Currently, it's mostly about [Cohttp](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp) and [Irmin](https://github.com/mirage/irmin) and both have a PR according the new
version of Conduit. These packages will be released as soon as we can with the new version of Conduit.

*** Conclusion

Conduit is a piece required by many libraries but nobody really uses it. This new version wants to
replace and redefine more concretely what Conduit is. The update is [huge](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-conduit/pull/311) for us but small
for people where we tried to keep the same global idea of the abstraction.

I would like to thank many people (MirageOS core team, Cohttp peoples, some not so famous guys of the
Reason/OCaml eco-system) who followed us on this deep development (and tried and iterated on our
version). It does not change too much our world, but it paves the way for a better MirageOS/OCaml
eco-system.

As a french guy, I just would like to say: Conduit est mort, Vive Conduit!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Easy cross compilation using esy</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-easy-cross-compilation-using-esy/6612/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>EduardoRFS announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I've been working on this for a couple of months now, and now it is ready for an initial announcement
of my tools to cross compiling OCaml and ReasonML Native.

https://github.com/EduardoRFS/reason-mobile

*** What it can do

Out of box it can cross compile most dune and topkg, packages available on opam for a couple of
platforms, there is also patches for popular packages.

You can also compile opam packages by making an wrapper, like

https://github.com/mirage/mirage-crypto/pull/84/files

*** Limitations

Your package should build with OCaml 4.10, and all the packages that are built for the ~host~ will also
be build for the ~target~, so sometimes you need to fix a package that you will not use directly.

Some packages you will need to pin to a ~dune-universe~ fork version

*** How to use it

#+begin_src shell
## compile your project
esy

## generate the wrapper
esy add -D generate@EduardoRFS/reason-mobile:generate.json
esy generate android.arm64

## build for android.arm64
esy @android.arm64
#+end_src

*** Platforms

All of the following are tested from Linux and macOS, but I would suppose that FreeBSD should be also
working as a build system.

| Targets |
|-|
| android.arm64 |
| android.x86_64 |
| ios.arm64|
| ios.simulator.x86_64|
| linux.musl.arm64|
| linux.musl.x86_64|

*** What I tested

In the past I was able to build ~Revery~ the UI framework for ~Android~ and ~iOS~

But recently I did compile ~esy~ the package manager itself for all of the following platforms above
from an ~Arch Linux x86_64~ and ~macOS Catalina x86_64~. Including ~iOS~, with the right version of
OCaml it will run inside of the new ~macOS ARM64~ and inside of a jailbroken iPhone.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml User Survey 2020</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocaml-user-survey-2020/6624/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>gasche announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are happy to announce the [OCaml User Survey 2020](https://forms.gle/MAT7ZE7RtxTWuNgK7). We are trying to get a better picture of the
OCaml community and its needs. It would be very useful if you could fill the survey (10-15 minutes),
and share it widely with other OCaml programmers!

The survey is run by the [OCaml Software Foundation](https://ocaml-sf.org/). Thanks in particular to
our sponsors OCamlPro (@MuSSF) for preparing many of the questions, Jane Street (@Yaron_Minsky) for
excellent feedback, and to Kim @K_N Nguyễn for his technical help.

This is our first year running the survey, we hope to continue in following years. There are many
things to improve; please feel free to give us feedback! (There is a feedback question at the end of
the survey, or you can post here, or send me a message/email.)

The survey was inspired by programming-language surveys ran by other communities. See for example past
survey results for [Go](https://blog.golang.org/survey2019-results), [Haskell](https://taylor.fausak.me/2019/11/16/haskell-survey-results/), [Rust](https://blog.rust-lang.org/2020/04/17/Rust-survey-2019.html), and [Scala](https://scalacenter.github.io/scala-developer-survey-2019/).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
