<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2020.06.16</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2020.06.09</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2020.06.23</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>June 09 to 16, 2020</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First release of monolith</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-first-release-of-monolith/5946/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>François Pottier announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It is my pleasure to announce the first release of Monolith.

Monolith offers facilities for testing an OCaml library (for instance, a data
structure implementation) by comparing it against a reference implementation.
It uses a form of black-box testing, and relies on ~afl-fuzz~ for efficiency.

The user must describe what types and operations the library provides. Under
the best circumstances, this requires 2-3 lines of code per type or operation.
The user must also provide a reference implementation of the library.

Then, like a monkey typing on a keyboard, Monolith attempts to exercise the
library in every possible way, in the hope of discovering a scenario where the
library behaves incorrectly. If such a scenario is discovered, it is printed
in the form of an OCaml program, so as to help the user reproduce the problem.

At this time, a tutorial is not yet available. There is however an API
documentation and a number of demos.

Repository:
  https://gitlab.inria.fr/fpottier/monolith

API Documentation:
  http://cambium.inria.fr/~fpottier/monolith/doc/monolith/Monolith/index.html

Installation:
#+begin_example
  opam update
  opam install monolith
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Sylvain Conchon joined OCamlPro's team</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/sylvain-conchon-joined-ocamlpros-team/5956/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>OCamlPro announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Sylvain Conchon joined OCamlPro's team as Formal Methods CSO. He created Alt-Ergo and has been teaching OCaml in
universities for about 20 years. He shares thoughts on interactions between industry and research labs, and his
vision of Formal methods and OCaml as language for the industry. Read his interview on our blog:
https://www.ocamlpro.com/2020/06/05/interview-sylvain-conchon-cso-on-formal-methods/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First release of streaming</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-first-release-of-streaming/5961/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Rizo announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It is my pleasure to announce the first public release of ~streaming~ – a library for building efficient, incremental
data processing pipelines that compose and don't leak resources.

I built streaming as a result of many experiments with different streaming and iteration models for OCaml. There are
multiple packages on OPAM that share some of the goals of ~streaming~ (we even have ~Stdlib.Seq~ now!), but none of
them combine (1) excellent performance, (2) safe resource handling and (3) pure functional style for combinators.
Streaming solves these problems by implementing three basic and independent models: _sources_, _sinks_ and _flows_ –
they represents different parts of the pipeline that correspond to producing, consuming and transforming elements.
These models can be defined and composed independently to produce reusable "streaming blocks".

The library defines a central ~Stream~ model that relies on sources, sinks and flows. This model is a push-based
iterator with performance characteristics similar to the ~iter~ iterator, which has type ~('a -&gt; unit) -&gt; unit~, and
is known for being very efficient. But unlike ~iter~, it has a pure functional core (no need to use mutable state and
exceptions for flow control!) and can handle resource allocation and clean up in a lazy and deterministic way. All of
this while having a slightly better performance for common stream operations.

For those who are curious about the performance characteristics of ~streaming~ and other models, I created a
dedicated repository for stream benchmarks: https://github.com/rizo/streams-bench. In particular, it includes a few
simple benchmarks for ~Gen~, ~Base.Sequence~, ~Stdlib.Seq~, ~Iter~, ~Streaming.Stream~ and ~Streaming.Source~.

The library should soon be published on opam. In the meantime, I invite you to read the docs and explore the code:

- Library documentation: https://odis-labs.github.io/streaming
- Github project: https://github.com/odis-labs/streaming
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Guillaume Bury askec</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
That's great ! From the benchmarks, it looks like you hit a really good implementation !

I've looked (maybe a bit fast) at the API documentation, and it is admittedly a bit outside the scope of
streams/iterators, but I was wondering if there was some proper way to:
- connect a sink to a source to create some loop
- have some kind of fixpoint on streams

I guess it would always be possible to use some references and/or some complex functions to encode these into the
provided API, but I was wondering if there was a clean way to do it.

For a bit of context and explanation, what I have in mind is the case of a program (let's say a type-checker or
something close to the idea) with a *persistent state*, that should operate over a stream of inputs, which are
top-level phrases, and produce some outputs, for instance print some result for each correctly type-checked statement
(and an error otherwise).
The type-checker would basically be a function of type ~(`input * `state) -&gt; (`output * `state)~, and starting
from an initial state, it would process an input element (giving the output to some sink), and then the next input
element would be processed with the state that was reached after processing the previous element: the state would
reach the sink of the flow, and then be inserted back into the source.
Separately, imagine the language being type-checked has a notion of include, then one of the step of the flow would
be to expand each include into a stream of inputs/phrases, but each of the phrases in this stream would need to be
expanded, so a simple ~flat_map~/~flatten~ is not enough.

I already have a custom implementation that handle these features, but I was wondering whether I could use
~streaming~ to handle most of the code linking all of the steps, ^^
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Rizo replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
if there was some proper way to:
- connect a sink to a source to create some loop
- have some kind of fixpoint on streams
#+end_quote

Regarding the first point: yes! That's exactly the point of the ~Stream~ module. You see, sources are pull-based
abstractions, while sinks are push-based. Source's type essentially says something like _"I might give you some data,
if you ask"_, while sink's type is the opposite _"I might take some data, if you give it to me"_. They are completely
and intentionally decoupled; it is Stream's role to drive the computation by pulling data from sources and pushing it
into sinks. So the easiest way to connect them is:

#+begin_src ocaml
Stream.(from srouce |> into sink)
#+end_src

Of course, that's not very useful per se, but it illustrates my point. Take a look at the
[~Stream.from~](https://github.com/odis-labs/streaming/blob/0.8.0/lib/Stream.ml#L42) code to see the implementation
of the loop you're asking for. It does some extra work to ensure that resources are correctly handled, but it should
be clear what the loop is doing.

The stream types in the library are currently abstract because I didn't want to commit to a particular representation
just yet. If this is a problem for your use case, let me know, I'll expose them in a ~Private~ module.

Regarding the second point: I'm not sure what you mean in practice by "fixpoint on streams". I guess the one thing
that could help implement something like that is the
[~Stream.run~](https://odis-labs.github.io/streaming/streaming/Streaming/Stream/index.html#val-run) function. It
allows you to continue reading elements from a source even after a sink is filled by returning a leftover stream.
This stream can be used with ~Stream.run~ repeatedly.

Alternatively there's also
[~Flow.through~](https://odis-labs.github.io/streaming/streaming/Streaming/Flow/index.html#val-through), which
consumes input trying to fill sinks repeatedly and produces their aggregated values as a stream. Super useful for
things like streaming parsing. Might even help with your use-case for top-level phrases.

On a more general note though, the type ~('input * 'state) -&gt; ('output * 'state)~ looks a lot like a [mealy
machine](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mealy_machine). ~Streaming.Sink~ is a [moore
machine](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore_machine), which is slightly less general because the output values do
not depend on input values, only on the state.

I thought about exposing different kinds of sinks in streaming, but wanted to make sure that the common use cases are
covered first. I'll keep your case in mind for future versions of the library.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Senior software engineer at Asemio in Tulsa, OK</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/senior-software-engineer-at-asemio-in-tulsa-ok/5979/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Simon Grondin announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are Asemio and our team of data scientists, software engineers, architects, and management consultants are working
together to achieve a nationwide data ecosystem for social good.

You’ll be working on the Asemio Community Integration Platform. It features state-of-the-art privacy-preserving,
pre-processing and pipeline management, as well as record linkage technology.

The back end is written in OCaml. The front end is compiled from OCaml to JavaScript and uses a modern MVC framework.
The work you’ll be doing will touch numerous technical disciplines, including cryptography, distributed systems,
language design and implementation, data analytics, and data visualizations.

We prefer candidates willing to relocate, but we could make an exception for an exceptional candidate.

For more information or to apply, please refer to our SE listing:
https://stackoverflow.com/jobs/401383/ocaml-senior-software-engineer-asemio
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[http://frama-c.com/index.html][Frama-C 21.0 (Scandium) is out. Download it here.]]
- [[http://math.andrej.com/2020/06/09/epigram-2-autopsy-obituary-apology/][Every proof assistant: Epigram 2 - Autopsy, Obituary, Apology]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
