<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2021.03.30</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2021.03.23</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2021.04.06</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>March 23 to 30, 2021</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Theorem Proving with Coq and Ocaml</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/theorem-proving-with-coq-ocaml/7524/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Gregory Malecha announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I lead the formal methods team at Bedrock Systems (https://bedrocksystems.com) and we are looking to hire a  full-time
engineer working on automation in the Coq proof assistant (which is written in Ocaml). We're very interested in
candidates with strong Ocaml background especially in topics related to automated theorem proving, e.g. SAT/SMT
solvers, datalog, superposition, resolution, etc. While Coq experience is great, you do not need to be a Coq expert
to apply to this position, we're happy to marry your Ocaml expertise with our Coq expertise.

Formal methods are at the core of BedRock's business and we are deeply committed to solving problems of system
verification at industrial scale. We get FM techniques and insights into the code early on and use them to build,
maintain, and evolve code. This includes developing more agile techniques to keep evolving verified systems once
they're built.

We have eight folks on the formal methods team today, hailing from MPI-SWS, MIT CSAIL, Princeton, and other leading
research groups. If you're interested, send me an email or you can inquire more broadly at jobs@bedrocksystems.com.

*Company overview:*

BedRock is building a *trustworthy compute base for mission-critical applications* . The foundation of the platform
is an open source, multi-core, capability-based micro-hypervisor that we are developing and verifying. On top of
these deep specifications we are writing and verifying applications to provide an extensible and configurable core.

Our contention is that the *time is ripe for verifiably trustworthy systems*, for everything from secure phones
and industrial IoT to autonomous systems and financial infrastructure. With significant seed funding, great
investors, and commercial projects underway, we are growing our team in Boston, the Bay Area, DC, and Germany.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ocaml-aws 1.2</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocaml-aws-1-2/7526/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Tim Mc Gilchrist announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the release of [ocaml-aws](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/aws/) 1.2.

ocaml-aws aims to provide generated bindings to many AWS services using the botocore specifications. In this version
we've bumped version bounds on a bunch of depedencies and also added new bindings for:
- RDS
- Route53
- SDB
- SQS

Please check it out and report any issues.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Release of ~fmlib.0.2.0~</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-release-of-fmlib-0-2-0/7527/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hbr announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am pleased to announce the second release (0.2.0) of fmlib, a functional
library with managed effects.

The library has up to now 4 components:

- [Some standard datatypes](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib/Fmlib_std/index.html)
- [Pretty printing functions](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib/Fmlib_pretty/Print/index.html)
- [Parsing combinator library](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib/Fmlib_parse/index.html)
- [Primitives to compile to javascript](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_js/index.html)

The last component is the new one in version 0.2.0. Internally it uses
~js_of_ocaml~ to compile to javascript. It is an easy to use library of
primitive functions to access mainly browser functionality from ocaml and some
rudimentary functions to access nodejs functionality.

It can be installed via opam by

#+begin_example
    opam update
    opam install fmlib
    opam install fmlib_js
#+end_example

It is located at [github](https://github.com/hbr/fmlib)
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Hbr added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hint: ~fmlib~ is still a bundle of three libraries i.e. three toplevel modules ~Fmlib_std~, ~Fmlib_pretty~ and
~Fmlib_parse~. Therefore they have to be used in a ~dune~ file with

#+begin_example
    (libraries fmlib.fmlib_std fmlib.fmlib_pretty fmlib.fmlib_parse ...)
#+end_example

while the new library can be used with

#+begin_example
    (libraries fmlib_js ...)
#+end_example

This inconvenience will be corrected in the next release.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>soupault: a static website generator based on HTML rewriting</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-soupault-a-static-website-generator-based-on-html-rewriting/4126/14</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Daniil Baturin announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[soupault 2.5.0](https://soupault.app/blog/soupault-2.5.0-release/) offers some features that are unique among SSGs.

There are two new built-in widgets for rewriting internal links, which is useful if you don't host your website at
the server root. For example, if you host it at ~example.com/~user~, you cannot just write ~&lt;img src="/header.png"&gt;~:
it will point to ~example.com/header.png~ while you want ~example.com/~user/header.png~ instead.

The ~relative_links~ widget will convert all internal links to relative links according to their depth in the
directory tree. For example, suppose you have ~&lt;img src="/header.png"&gt;~ in your page template. Then in
~about/index.html~ that link will become ~&lt;img src="../header.png"&gt;~; in ~books/magnetic-fields/index.html~ it will
be ~&lt;img src="../../header.png"&gt;~ and so on. This way you can move the website to a subdirectory and it will still
work.

The ~absolute_links~ widget prepends a prefix to every internal link. Conceptually similar to the site URL option in
other SSGs and CMSes, but works for all links, not only links generated by the SSG itself.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Timere-parse 0.0.2, natural language parsing of date, time and duration</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-timere-parse-0-0-2-natural-language-parsing-of-date-time-and-duration/7532/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Darren announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce the release of Timere-parse 0.0.2, the natural language parsing component of Timere, a date
time handling and reasoning library. Both packages are under the [Timere
repo](https://github.com/daypack-dev/timere).

Timere-parse allows interpretation of common descriptions of date, time and duration.

*** Date time examples

Input strings are in ~""~, indented lines are pretty printed output.

#+begin_example
"2020 jun 6 10am"
  Ok 2020-06-06T10:00:00Z
"2020 jun 6th 10:15"
  Ok 2020-06-06T10:15:00Z
"Australia/Sydney 2020 jun 6 10am"
  Ok 2020-06-06T10:00:00+10:00
"01-06-2020 10:10"
  Ok 2020-06-01T10:10:00Z
"2020/06/01 10am"
  Ok 2020-06-01T10:00:00Z
"jul 6 2021 9:15am"
  Ok 2021-07-06T09:15:00Z
"2020/06/01"
  Ok 2020-06-01T00:00:00Z
#+end_example

*** Duration examples

#+begin_example
"24h"
  Ok 1 days 0 hours 0 mins 0 secs
"16.5 hours"
  Ok 16 hours 30 mins 0 secs
"1h20min"
  Ok 1 hours 20 mins 0 secs
"1 hour 2.5 minutes"
  Ok 1 hours 2 mins 30 secs
"100 seconds"
  Ok 1 mins 40 secs
"2.25 minutes 1 seconds"
  Ok 2 mins 16 secs
"5 days 6.5 hours"
  Ok 5 days 6 hours 30 mins 0 secs
#+end_example

*** Timere object examples

#+begin_example
"2020 jun"
  Ok (pattern (years 2020) (months Jun))
"jan"
  Ok (pattern (months Jan))
jan 6 12pm to 2pm"
  Ok (bounded_intervals whole (duration 366 0 0 0) (points (pick mdhms Jan 6 12 0 0)) (points (pick hms 14 0 0)))
"12th, 13 to 15, 20"
  Ok (pattern (month_days 12 13 14 15 20))
"16th 7:30am"
  Ok (pattern (month_days 16) (hours 7) (minutes 30) (seconds 0))
"16th 8am to 10am, 11am to 12pm"
  Ok (inter (pattern (month_days 16)) (union (bounded_intervals whole (duration 1 0 0 0) (points (pick hms 8 0 0))
(points (pick hms 10 0 0))) (bounded_intervals whole (duration 1 0 0 0) (points (pick hms 11 0 0)) (points (pick hms
12 0 0)))))
"2020 jun 16th 10am to jul 1 12pm"
  Ok (bounded_intervals whole (duration 366 0 0 0) (points (pick ymdhms 2020 Jun 16 10 0 0)) (points (pick mdhms Jul
1 12 0 0)))
#+end_example

*** Corpus

For the full corpus/examples, see [corpus/](https://github.com/daypack-dev/timere/tree/main/corpus)  for code and
[corpus-outputs/](https://github.com/daypack-dev/timere/blob/main/corpus-outputs) for generated outputs.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ocamlnet-4.1.9</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2021-03/msg00028.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
there is now ocamlnet-4.1.9 available:

- compatibility with upcoming OCaml-4.12
- some fixes regarding TLS (https)
- a few build-related details

See the project page for download, documentation, a detailed changelog,
and the mailing list:
http://projects.camlcity.org/projects/ocamlnet.html

The repository is at

https://gitlab.com/gerdstolpmann/lib-ocamlnet3/

opam follows soon.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Release of cohttp 4.0.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-release-of-cohttp-4-0-0/7537/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Marcello Seri announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are glad to announce the [upcoming release](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/18385) of [~cohttp
4.0.0~](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp), a low-level OCaml library for HTTP clients and servers.

This release comes with a big update of the documentation and the examples, both in the
[README](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp) and in the codebase, and improvements and bug fixes from many
contributors 🙇 which you will find listed below.

A huge thank you to all the people that helped to get this release ready by raising issues, participating in
discussions, sending PRs, and otherwise using our library.

*** The future of cohttp

To quote @avsm from [another
post](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/defining-standard-ocaml-development-lifecycle-processes/7486/5)

#+begin_quote
The development process [...] is driven by a simple principle that is inspired by OCaml itself: don't needlessly
break backwards compatibility without good reason, and when it is necessary, justify it. Our tools are embedded in
projects that have lifespans measured in the decades, and we take compatibility seriously. That’s why we take pains
to provide migration paths [...] that are as invisible as possible.
#+end_quote

Since in this release we have decided to include a number of fixes and improvements which modified Cohttp module
signatures, we decided to signal the potential breackage by bumping the major version of the library. In most cases,
however, you don't need to do anything and your code will keep working with the latest cohttp.

Moving forward, we have agreed to start working on the API and the internals of cohttp to modernize it and get it
ready for multicore support and also for eventual unification with the h2 stack that offers HTTP2/3 support.

To be able to move forward and avoid stalling improvements for months, we will be less shy of major releases.
However, to remain true to the principle above, we will be careful to introduce one breakage at a time, carefully
justify its need and provide a clear upgrade path in the changelog.

The version history is:
- cohttp 2.5.5: security backports (changelog below)
- cohttp 3.0.0: skipped (explained below)
- cohttp 4.0.0: the next release (changelog below)
- cohttp 5.0.0: will include a long-awaited change in [how headers are treated](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp/pull/747): which fixes a multitude of past issues and simplifies the internals of the module.

For the people that need stability, *we have decided to keep backporting important security fixes to the ~2.5.x~
branch of the project*. In fact, ~cohttp 2.5.5~, released just a few days ago was the first release with the
backport of a security issue.

*** What happened to 3.0.0?

The release of ~cohttp 3.0.0~ has been long awaited, and we are extremely grateful to @dinosaure for the enormous
work that went into designing and implementing ~conduit 3.0.0~ and ~cohttp 3.0.0~ (part of which remained in ~4.0.0~
as bug fixes and API improvements).

However, a discussion started soon after the release pointing out that there could be further room of improvement
also with the new design, particularly with respect to backwards compatibility. Since the design discussion did not
reach consensus, these changes were reverted to preserve better compatibility with existing cohttp users and ~cohttp
3.0.0~ was [marked as unavailable](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp/issues/736) on the opam repository.  As
maintainers, our "lesson learnt" is to not do releases incrementally when they span multiple libraries: we were
caught in an awkward spot when conduit 3 was released, but without cohttp 3.

The work on the new conduit is steadily progressing and will be integrated in a new major release of cohttp in the
future, once we will be confident that the API is settled. If you want to try using it immediately, then it is
available as the [mimic](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-git/tree/master/src/mimic) library in ocaml-git.

*** Change Log

**** v4.0.0

- cohttp.response: fix malformed status header for custom status codes (@mseri @aalekseyev #752)
- remove dependency to base (@samoht #745)
- add GitHub Actions workflow (@smorimoto #739)
- ~cohttp-lwt-jsoo~: Forward exceptions to caller when response is null (@mefyl #738)
- Use implicit executable dependency for generate.exe (@TheLortex #735)
- cohttp: update HTTP codes (@emillon #711)
- cohttp: fix chunked encoding of empty body (@mefyl #715)
- cohttp-async: fix body not being uploaded with unchunked Async.Pipe (@mefyl #706)
- cohttp-{async, lwt}: fix suprising behaviours of Body.is_empty (@anuragsoni #714 #712 #713)
- refactoring of tests (@mseri #709, @dinosaure #692)
- update documentation (@dinosaure #716, @mseri #720)
- fix deadlock in logging (@dinosaure #722)
- improve media type parsing (@seliopou #542, @dinosaure #725)
- [reverted] breaking changes to client and server API to use conduit 3.0.0 (@dinosaure #692). However, as the design discussion did not reach consensus, these changes were reverted to preserve better compatibility with existing cohttp users. (#741,  @samoht)

*Potentially breaking changes*

- remove ~wrapped false~ from the codebase (@rgrinberg #734)
- cohttp: add Uti.t to uri scheme (@brendanlong #707)
- cohttp-lwt-jsoo: rename Cohttp_lwt_xhr to Cohttp_lwt_jsoo for consistency (@mseri #717)
- cohttp: fix transfer-encoding ordering in headers (@mseri #721)
- lower-level support for long-running cohttp-async connections (@brendanlong #704)
- add of_form and to_form functions to body (@seliopou #440, @mseri #723)
- cohttp-lwt: partly inline read_response, fix body stream leak (@madroach @dinosaure #696).
  Note: there is a new warning that may show up in your logs when bodies are leaked, see also [#730](https://github.com/mirage/ocaml-cohttp/issues/730).
- add comparison functions for Request.t and Response.t via ppx_compare (@msaffer-js @dinosaure #686)

**** v2.5.5

- ~Cohttp_async.resolve_local_file~, ~Cohttp_lwt.resolve_local_file~ and ~Cohttp_lwt_unix.resolve_file~ are now the same code under the hood (~Cohttp.Path.resolve_local_file~). The old names have been preserved for compatibility, but will be marked as deprecated in the next release. This changes the behavior of ~Cohttp_lwt_unix.resolve_file~: it now percent-decodes the paths and blocks escaping from the docroot correctly. This also fixes and tests the corner cases in these methods when the docroot is empty. (@ewanmellor #755)

  *Double check your code base for uses of ~Cohttp_lwt_unix.resolve_file~: it is unsafe with respect to path handling*. If you cannot upgrade to ~cohttp 2.5.5~, you should modify your code to call ~Cohttp_lwt.resolve_local_file~ instead.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New Try-Alt-Ergo website</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-new-try-alt-ergo-website/7555/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>OCamlPro announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are pleased to announce the new version of the [Try Alt-Ergo website](https://try-alt-ergo.ocamlpro.com/)!

As a reminder, Try Alt-Ergo allows you to write and run your problems in your browser without any server computation.
It was designed to be a powerful and simple tool to use.

Updates concern these parts of the site:
- A new back end in JavaScript
- Front end with news features (Ace editor, top panel, right panel, etc.)

Take a look at [our blogpost](https://www.ocamlpro.com/2021/03/29/new-try-alt-ergo/) to read how we have updated the
Try Alt-Ergo website and what's new! You can also visit the [Try Alt-Ergo
website](https://try-alt-ergo.ocamlpro.com/) directly. As usual, do not hesitate to report bugs, to ask questions, or
to give your feedback.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[https://www.ocamlpro.com/2021/03/29/new-try-alt-ergo/][New Try-Alt-Ergo]]
- [[https://seb.mondet.org/b/0012-tzcomet-token-viewer.html][TZComet's New Token Viewer]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
