<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2021.09.07</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2021.08.31</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2021.09.14</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>August 31 to September 07, 2021</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head></cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Just reinvented OOP</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/just-reinvented-oop/8399/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yawar Amin said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_src ocaml
let ( .![] ) obj f = f obj

type person = { id : int; name : string }

let id { id; _ } = id

let bob = { id = 1; name = "Bob" }
let next_id = bob.![id].![succ]
#+end_src

==&gt; 2
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Kiran Gopinathan replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Haha, what a coincidence, just did the same very recently while translating a rust library to
OCaml:
https://github.com/Gopiandcode/ego/blob/5daf312f8a444f9abcde5996c671b9282727a972/lib/generic.ml#L211
#+begin_src ocaml
let eclasses = eg.@[eclasses] in
let cost_map = Id.Map.create 10 in
let node_total_cost node =
  let has_cost id = Id.Map.mem cost_map (eg.@[find] id) in
  if List.for_all has_cost (L.children node)
  then let cost_f id = fst @@ Id.Map.find cost_map (eg.@[find] id) in Some (E.cost cost_f
node)
  else None in
  (* ... *)
#+end_src
with ~.@[]~ defined as:
#+begin_src ocaml
  let (.@[]) self fn = fn self [@@inline always]
#+end_src

for bonus(?) points, you can name the first parameter self:
#+begin_src ocaml
let add_enode self (node: Id.t L.shape) =
  let node = self.@[canonicalise] node in
  (* ... *)
#+end_src
I don't normally write code like this in OCaml, but in this case, it made porting from rust
easier, because the code mostly looked the same.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>hyphenrf also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
You can use the multiple-indexing syntax to implement slicing (well, technically subs) sugar:
#+begin_src ocaml
let (.:[;..]) s = function
  | [|start; finish|] -> String.sub s start (finish - start)
  | _ -> raise (Invalid_argument "slice takes exactly two indexes")
#+end_src
#+begin_example
# "hello world".:[1;5];;
- : string = "ello"
#+end_example
The new indexing syntax is quite versatile :>
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Kiran Gopinathan added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Oh wow, this is perfect! brb, off to reimplement the python slicing semantics in OCaml:
#+begin_src ocaml
let (.@[;..]) ls = function[@warning "-8"]
  | [| start; -1 |] ->
    List.to_iter ls
    |> Iter.zip_i
    |> Iter.drop_while (Pair.fst_map ((>) start))
    |> Iter.map snd
  | [| start; finish |] ->
    List.to_iter ls
    |> Iter.zip_i
    |> Iter.drop_while (Pair.fst_map ((>) start))
    |> Iter.take_while (Pair.fst_map ((>) finish))
    |> Iter.map snd
  | [| start; finish; step |] ->
    List.to_iter ls
    |> Iter.zip_i
    |> Iter.drop_while (Pair.fst_map ((>) start))
    |> Iter.take_while (Pair.fst_map ((>) finish))
    |> Iter.filter (Pair.fst_map (fun ind -> (ind - start) mod step = 0))
    |> Iter.map snd
#+end_src
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>v3.OCaml.org: A roadmap for OCaml's online presence</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/v3-ocaml-org-a-roadmap-for-ocamls-online-presence/8368/19</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Anil Madhavapeddy replied to many comments</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Many thanks for all the constructive comments and suggestions so far, and also for those who
have gotten in touch to contribute. Please do keep them coming (either on this thread or on
the various issue trackers that @jonludlam and @patricoferris have pointed to).  I'll answer
some earlier questions here:

#+begin_quote
Having said that, the colors on the [packages landing page ](https://v3.ocaml.org/packages)
feel very aggressive to me. Might be my setup here, but I would like to have a slightly less
harsh contrast.

Also, there is a bit of an overlap in content with [https://ocamlverse.github.io/
](https://ocamlverse.github.io/) for some things (eg best practices, community) but the (to
me) most valuable feature is missing: The ecosystems overview, where I can find packages
sorted thematically. Could such a section also have a place in the packages subpage
somewhere?
Alternatively, maybe opam can allow to “tag” packages in the future so one could see all
packages for graphics, databases etc.
#+end_quote

The styling of the /packages sub-URL does indeed differ from the main design, but this is
simply due to a temporary technical detail. The majority of the site uses React/NextJS to
generate the frontend, and this uses the now-trendy medium-contrast colours and also features
like fast-page-switching that NextJS offers.  However, the documentation portion generated
around 2.7 million individual pages when run across the full opam repository, and so we
restored to dynamic generation of the content for that. What's going to happen next is a
rationalisation of the code across the ReScript and OCaml frontends so that there will be no
observable difference in the colour schemes across the full site.

Regarding creating a categorised list of recommendations, that is absolutely in scope for the
v3 iteration of the site. However, this metadata should ideally live in the opam-repository
(for example, using ~tags~ as you suggest, which opam already supports). If anyone would like
to have a go at this, I'd encourage PRs to the opam-repository to add the relevant tag
metadata for a codex. Meanwhile, @lambda_foo @tmattio and @patricoferris are working on the
core OCaml Platform workflow information for the guides section of the website which will
cover opam, merlin, lsp-server, dune and so on.

#+begin_quote
Do we have access to all of the previous years’ workshops to add to [watch.ocaml.org](http://watch.ocaml.org)?
I can see pieces of 2015, 2017, 2020 and this year. @avsm

Is it possible to add the ML Workshop as well?
#+end_quote

Absolutely. The watch.ocaml.org has held up nicely after the OCaml Workshop, so I think it's
in good shape to populate with more videos. This needs a volunteer to help us upload the past
[nine years](https://ocaml.org/meetings/ocaml/2012/) of videos from YouTube to
watch.ocaml.org. If anyone wants to have a go, please message me and I'll create you an
account.

#+begin_quote
It’s a bit unclear what you meant in this paragraph. Does that mean that you plan to kill the
ocaml planet ? I would find it a little bit sad.

One of the reason why you may feel it doesn’t work well may be that it has been constantly
broken in the current version of the site…
#+end_quote

I'm not sure why you think the current ocaml.org new feed has been broken -- it's been
working fairly reliably for the past decade. The only real problem came up a few times when a
feed's domain expired and got taken over by domain squatters, at which point we got spam into
the main page of ocaml.org.

What I meant with that part of the announcement is that the syndication feed should not be
mistaken with original news on the website. Right now it's difficult to distinguish official
announcements (such as compiler or opam releases) as they are a little scattered (e.g. on
opam.ocaml.org). The plan is to combine the
[platform-blog](https://github.com/ocaml/platform-blog) with the new website directly. I've
also been considering just having a special tag on this forum so that nice announcement posts
could also be syndicated to the website easily (for example, @gasche's compiler newsletters).

My general desire is to _grow_ the planet feed and syndication system, but to clearly
demarcate them as not being published by ocaml.org and to manage them via more modern
decentralised techniques that feature spam, moderation and archival. PeerTube is a good
example of this for videos that is working well, and I'd welcome suggestions for Atom/RSS
(there must be something in this space, ideally ActivityPub-based).

Depending on how the experiments go, it's very likely that we'll have a Matrix homeserver for
ocaml.org where CI bots can report status information (see this [prototype
PR](https://github.com/ocurrent/ocaml-ci/pull/362)) for ocaml-ci that will also apply to
opam-repository. The goal here is to for ocaml.org to publish its data using an open
protocol, which can then be syndicated into whatever technologies are in vogue (e.g. Discord,
Slack, Teams, ...).

So if you spot some decentralised syndication system that you think might be interesting for
OCaml, please do let me know.  Even better, if you'd like to develop one to tailor it to our
needs, let me know even sooner ;-)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Become an Outreachy Mentor: support the growth and diversity of the OCaml community</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/become-an-outreachy-mentor-support-the-growth-and-diversity-of-the-ocaml-community/8213/3</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
There's been a very disappointing response to this call for mentors to increase the diversity
of our community. Precisely *noone* has been in touch for the winter call, leaving the burden
of mentorship on the same people that did all the work this summer.

Before making [new calls for programs like
GSoC](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/v3-ocaml-org-a-roadmap-for-ocamls-online-presence/8368/16?u=avsm),
let's get Outreachy onto more sustainable ground please. We are purely limited by mentorship
time at present. This can be as simple as organising new first issues for projects in the
ecosystem, and all the way to pair programming with a mentee. You can chose how to be
involved.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Generating static and portable executables with OCaml</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/generating-static-and-portable-executables-with-ocaml/8405/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>OCamlPro announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It has been a few times now that we have been tasked to generate portable binaries for
different projects. Over time, we have gathered quite some know-how and, seeing the question
frequently arise in the community, we decided to share this experience.

You can find the article written by Louis Gesbert on[ the OCamlPro
blog](https://www.ocamlpro.com/2021/09/02/generating-static-and-portable-executables-with-ocaml/)


#+begin_quote
 Distributing OCaml software on opam is great (if I dare say so myself), but sometimes you
 need to provide your tools to an audience outside of the OCaml community, or just without
 recompilations or in a simpler way.

 However, just distributing the locally generated binaries requires that the users have all
 the required shared libraries installed, and a compatible libc. It's not something you can
 assume in general, and even if you don't need any C shared library or are confident enough
 it will be installed everywhere, the libc issue will arise for anyone using a distribution
 based on a different kind, or a little older than the one you used to build.

 There is no built-in support for generating static executables in the OCaml compiler, and
 it may seem a bit tricky, but it's not in fact too complex to do by hand, something you may
 be ready to do for a release that will be published. So here are a few tricks, recipes and
 advice that should enable you to generate truly portable executables with no external
 dependency whatsoever. Both Linux and macOS will be treated, but the examples will be based
 on Linux unless otherwise specified.
#+end_quote

Don't hesitate to share your thoughts with us, have a good reading!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml quant-developer at Bloomberg. London or New York</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-quant-developer-at-bloomberg-london-or-new-york/8409/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Philip Craig announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Extend a financial contracts DSL that is implemented in OCaml.

It's London or New York based. It's not a remote position.

Please see details and/or apply at (https://careers.bloomberg.com/job/detail/93825)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>HTTP client library</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-http-client-library/8428/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hannes Mehnert announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
we just released to the opam-repository the
[~http-lwt-client~](https://github.com/roburio/http-lwt-client) package, which consists of
both a library doing HTTP requests and a binary (~hurl~) that does HTTP requests.

The code is based on [HTTP/AF](https://github.com/inhabitedtype/httpaf) and
[H2](https://github.com/anmonteiro/ocaml-h2), and uses
[tls](https://github.com/mirleft/ocaml-tls) for HTTPS connections. Both HTTP/1(.1) and HTTP/2
protocols are supported. The motivation behind this package is to have a http client that has
a reasonably small dependency cone, is purely implemented in OCaml, and uses the asynchronous
task library lwt.

This package uses [happy-eyeballs](https://github.com/roburio/happy-eyeballs) to connect to a
remote host via IPv4 and IPv6, as proposed by IETF [RFC
8305](https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8305): on any computer with either IPv4 or IPv6
connectivity, a remote IPv6 or IPv4 server will be connected. Preference is given to IPv6.

If a https url is provided, the server certificate is verified using the
[ca-certs](https://github.com/mirage/ca-certs) package.

If you experience any issues or have further needs for this package, please report an issue
on the GitHub issue tracker.

The installation is just an ~opam install http-lwt-client~ away :)
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Hannes Mehnert later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
now [0.0.2](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/19410) is released that unifies the
response type and API (previously it was a variant and clients had to write code for both
HTTP1 and HTTP2). Now, a single record and Status/Headers/Version module aliases are provided
(very close to HTTP/AF). Enjoy.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocamlcore planet blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[http://ocaml.org/community/planet/][OCaml Planet]].

- [[https://blog.janestreet.com/goodbye-Core_kernel/][Goodbye Core_kernel]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2021-08-26-tarides-engineers-to-present-at-icfp-2021][Tarides Engineers to Present at ICFP 2021]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2021-08-26-benchmarking-ocaml-projects-with-current-bench][Benchmarking OCaml projects with current-bench]]
- [[https://blog.janestreet.com/what-the-interns-have-wrought-2021/][What the interns have wrought, 2021 edition]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
