<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2021.05.25</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2021.05.18</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2021.06.01</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>May 18 to 25, 2021</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head></cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Applied PL research at Jane Street</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/job-applied-pl-research-at-jane-street/7877/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yaron Minsky announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This isn't exactly news, but we're (still) actively looking to hire people to do applied PL research, with a
particular focus on type-level work. Follow this link if you want to see how to apply.

https://blog.janestreet.com/applied-PL-research/

Please share it around with anyone who you think might be on the market!

*About the job*

Part of our ambition is to grow OCaml into a language that does an ever better job of being convenient and expressive
by default, while allowing for the kind of precise control you need when building high performance systems, where
it's needed.

That's led us to do research on stack-allocation, unboxed types, algebraic effects, type-level resource tracking, and
more. We think it's an exciting direction for the language, and there's a lot of challenging and novel work to be
done, and the main thing that could speed us up is having more of the right people to work on it!

Jane Street is an excellent laboratory for this kind of work: big enough to have serious and demanding use-cases, but
small and nimble enough to be able to try out new language features, and then back out of them or change them in
incompatible ways if need be.

And all the work we do on the compiler is in the open, with the goal of getting the final results into a state where
they can be upstreamed.

Also, it's a great team! Full of serious experts who have collectively contributed a lot to OCaml and PL research
over the years, and also a really nice set of people to work with. And I think the team has a good balance of the
practical and theoretical: working hard to do the right thing, but also finding practical ideas that can make forward
progress in the near term.

*Who are we looking for*

We're looking for people with a good balance of theoretical and engineering backgrounds, since the work is demanding
on both fronts.

We're happy to hire people at a range of experience levels: people who have just finished a post-doc or PhD, up to
experienced academics and people in industry.

The team has a presence in New York and London, and we're hiring in both offices. No remote work, I'm afraid.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>IRC channels available on libera.chat</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2021-05/msg00022.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Adrien Nader announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Due to the recent troubles on freenode[1][2], I've connected to
irc.libera.chat early in order to create and register the same channels
that I know and take care ofa on freenode (i.e. #ocaml and #ocaml-fr).

I am not stating libera.chat is better than freenode.net although the
amount of staffers moving makes me think freenode.net will not be
running fine for a much longer time.

At the moment I believe it is better to keep both channels running and
to encourage people to connect on libera.chat too. In the future, I
might force migration by progressively silencing the channel that should
be abandoned.

If you maintain a relay bot, can you please add it on libera.chat too?

As far as I know, there is no Matrix bridge available currently. It
seems the discussion/process for bridge additions occurs at [3].

A good news is that I've gotten the full rights on the channel,
something which was requiring paperwork on freenode (which I had already
mentioned but never got around to doing and for which I never even remotely
got time for).

[1] https://lwn.net/Articles/856543/ (this still constantly changes) \\
[2] https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freenode#2021_ownership_change_and_conflict \\
[3] https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-appservice-irc/issues/208
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>B Trees in Ocaml via Fmlib 0.3.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/b-trees-in-ocaml-via-fmlib-0-3-0/7880/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hbr announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am pleased to announce the release (0.3.0) of fmlib, a functional
library with managed effects.

The main new feature of release 0.3.0 are B trees. B trees can be used to
implement finite sets and finite maps. Fmlib's  B trees have functionality
similar to the modules ~Set~ and ~Map~ of the standard library.

The modules ~Set~ and ~Map~ of the standard library are based on AVL trees. B
trees offer the same functionality but have on modern processors a better cache
performance and have better data locality.

The current B tree implementation in ~Fmlib~ implements B trees by using arrays
which are guaranteed to fit into a cache line. The design of B trees is
described [here](https://fmlib_ocaml.readthedocs.io). The API can be found [here](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_std).

The library ~Fmlib~ has four main components:

- [Standard Datatypes](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_std): This component offers some modules from ~Stdlib~
  with additional functionality. E.g. ~Fmlib_std.Array~ offers functions to
  insert elements into arrays, remove elements from an array and binary search
  in a sorted array. It has the modules ~Result~ and ~Option~ which can be used
  to avoid exceptions and use exceptions in a more structured way. The modules
  ~Result~ and ~Option~ in ~Fmlib~ offer a complete monadic interface and offer
  the ~let*~ operator to write well readable monadic code.

- [Pretty Printing](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_pretty): Print tree like structures in a nice way and use
  the library completely functional. The library does not assume a specific IO
  method. The pretty printer generates a lazy stream of characteres which can be
  written by all io functions.

- [Combinator Parsing](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_parse): Easily parse textual input by the use of
  combinators. The library supports indentation sensitivity and can therefore be
  used to parse yaml files, haskell, python, etc. Furthermore no input method is
  assumed. The generated parsers are sink of tokens (or characters). You can
  choose any input method and push the tokens/characters into the parsers. The
  generated parsers are fully incremental. Parser can be stored at any position
  of the input stream and in case of interactive editing, parsing can be resumed
  from any point of the stream.

- [Interface to Javascript](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_js): This components contains primitives to
  interface to javascript via ~js_of_ocaml~.

~Fmlib~ can be installed via opam:

#+begin_example
    opam update
    opam install fmlib
    opam install fmlib_std
    opam install fmlib_pretty
    opam install fmlib_parse
    opam install fmlib_js
#+end_example

The source code of the library is located at [github](https://github.com/hbr/fmlib)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>GitHub Actions for OCaml: now stable and on the ocaml org</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/github-actions-for-ocaml-now-stable-and-on-the-ocaml-org/7889/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I [announced a beta](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/github-actions-for-ocaml-opam-now-available/4745) of OCaml/opam
support for GitHub Actions back in Nov 2019, and the functionality has turned out to be popular. A number of projects
in our community have been using the Action, and it can be found in the [GitHub
Marketplace](https://github.com/marketplace/actions/set-up-ocaml).

It has been sufficiently popular that it's definitely time to get it off my personal GitHub account, and so I have
transferred it to its new home at https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml.  I am also very pleased to announce that
@smorimoto and @dra27 are also now maintainers -- they have both made significant improvements to it, and @smorimoto
in particular has been working with the GitHub ecosystem to further improve the efficiency of the Action (such as by
adding reliable caching).  Thank you to them both and [all the other
contributors](https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml/graphs/contributors) for your help improving the CI experience
around OCaml.

If anyone else wishes to contribute to improving the action, please do get involved on [the issue
tracker](https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml/issues).  And of course, if you are still referencing
~avsm/setup-ocaml~ in your own workflow definition, this is a good time to change it to ~ocaml/setup-ocaml~.

This is probably a good time to note that the other [ci-scripts](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-ci-scripts)
repository on the ocaml/ GitHub organisation is in sore need of either new maintainers (for the Travis CI), or being
retired due to lack of support (primarily due to the shift to GitHub Actions). I'm immensely grateful to Travis CI
for the decade of mostly free builds they have provided our community to date.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Set up OCaml 2.0.0-alpha</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-set-up-ocaml-2-0-0-alpha/7895/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sora Morimoto announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This is the announcement of the first alpha release of setup-ocaml v2. This includes quite a few changes, including
reliable cache, as described in a recent
[post](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/github-actions-for-ocaml-now-stable-and-on-the-ocaml-org/7889).

There are so many changes, so I would like to list only the notable changes. (The full changelog can be found at the
bottom of the post.)

*** The "ocaml-version" input is now named "ocaml-compiler"

This was changed because calling it "OCaml Version" is not appropriate enough, e.g. to use the new variant naming
convention introduced from 4.12.

*** 32 bits compiler support

*** Semver-style version matching support

With the naughty exception of ~4.02.2~ , point releases are meant to be strictly compatible, so once OCaml dev team
release a new point release, upgrading should be a no-brainer. With that in mind, it's obviously not smart to rewrite
every workflow every time a new point release is released, so you can now specify versions in the style like
~4.12.x~.

*** Reliable cache feature

The action supports not only the compiler cache, but also the [dune
cache](https://github.com/ocaml/dune/blob/2.8.5/doc/caching.rst). However, note that it is not available on the macOS
runners until opam 2.0.9 is released. The dune cache is actually quite powerful for large projects, if you're
interested in it, check out the comparison section of
[ocaml/setup-ocaml#66](https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml/pull/66). The reliable cache feature uses the
[@actions/cache](https://github.com/actions/toolkit/tree/main/packages/cache) package internally, and I worked with
the GitHub team to make it fast enough for setup-ocaml to be up to 4x faster. For the Ubuntu runners, you can set up
your environment with cache in about 30~40 seconds at the fastest.

*** Automatic pinning and depext handling of local packages
For example, if you have a very large number of local packages, like the [Irmin](https://github.com/mirage/irmin)
project, it can be quite a pain for a human to have to write a script to pin them all in your workflow. The action
pins and depext the local packages if they exist in the repository by default. You can also use the glob pattern to
select which local packages to handle, as described
[here](https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml/blob/master/examples.md#using-glob-patterns-to-filter-local-packages).

https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml/releases/tag/v2.0.0-alpha
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>FrontC 4.1.0 (Vingt ans après)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-frontc-4-1-0-vingt-ans-apres/7906/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Ivan Gotovchits announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
More than twenty years after its original release [FrontC](https://github.com/BinaryAnalysisPlatform/FrontC) is still alive and getting new updates. Mostly it
started with my frustration with its Makefiles that ended up in switching to menhir and dune and adding cram tests
that finally enabled us to safely touch the grammar definitions and introduce a few c99 ... c11 language features as
well as more GNU extensions. Our end goal is to get a robust and easy-to-use C parser that is capable of taking a C
program on a modern Linux distribution and get it parsed into a C abstract tree. It is not that trivial as it may
sound as modern C library headers (especially GNU libc) use non-standard or standard but very modern C features, and
most of the OCaml parsers that I have seen are still unable to parse them, including parsers from FramaC, C11parser,
and even compcert parser (mostly they do not handle complex floating-point types and various extension types and some
GCC attributes).

Therefore, FrontC is still useful, especially if all that you want is to start doing program analysis with minimal
initial effort, just do (but wait until it is [merged](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/18736))

#+begin_example
opam install FrontC
#+end_example

and start hacking!

With that said, FrontC is mostly maintained at leisure time by volunteers, so the pull requests are very welcome.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
