<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2022.08.09</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2022.08.02</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2022.08.16</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>August 02 to 09, 2022</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>pyml_bindgen: a CLI app to generate Python bindings directly from OCaml value specifications</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-pyml-bindgen-a-cli-app-to-generate-python-bindings-directly-from-ocaml-value-specifications/8786/8</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Ryan Moore announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
*** New release

Version 0.4.1 is now available from [GitHub](https://github.com/mooreryan/ocaml_python_bindgen/releases/tag/0.4.1)
and [Opam](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/pyml_bindgen/).  The [change
log](https://github.com/mooreryan/ocaml_python_bindgen/blob/main/CHANGELOG.md) has more details.

*** New stuff

**** New attributes

There is a new attribute you can use: ~py_arg_name~. It allows you to use different argument names on the OCaml side
from those that are used on the Python side.

One use case is for Python functions that have an argument name that is the same as some reserved OCaml keyword. In
this case, you can use ~py_arg_name~ to map it to something else on the OCaml side.

#+begin_src ocaml
val f : t -> method_:string -> unit -> string
[@@py_arg_name method_ method]
#+end_src

The attribute is followed by two items, the first is the argument name on the OCaml side, and the second is the
argument name on the Python side.

See the [attributes example](https://github.com/mooreryan/ocaml_python_bindgen/tree/main/examples/attributes) on
GitHub for more info.

**** Helper scripts

I added a couple of scripts to help in cases where you need to run ~pyml_bindgen~ on a lot of different input files
in one go.  I have been using them when writing bindings for bigger Python libraries, and in cases where there are a
lot of cyclic python classes to bind.

[This](https://github.com/mooreryan/ocaml_python_bindgen/tree/main/examples/recursive_modules) example has more info
about using the helper scripts.

**** Other stuff

- Added an option to split generated modules into ~ml~ and ~mli~ files.
- Added a dev package for (hopefully) easier installation of development dependencies.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Interesting OCaml Articles</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/interesting-ocaml-articles/1867/99</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Calascibetta Romain announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi, I would like to share my recent article about GADTs and state machines: [GADTs and state machine](https://blog.osau.re/articles/gadt_and_state_machine.html)

It's another introduction about GADTs and it explains a bit what I did for [robur.io](https://robur.io). Eenjoy it
and happy hacking!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Logs to a file (a primitive way)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/logs-to-a-file-a-primitive-way/10262/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>🌍 Marcus Rohrmoser asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I found https://github.com/oxidizing/sihl/blob/c6786f25424c1b9f40ce656e908bd31515f1cd09/sihl/src/core_log.ml#L18 and
wonder what a primitive way to log to a file would be.

I need to keep ~stdout~ clean and not show any log message under all circumstances.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>🌍 Marcus Rohrmoser later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I do a cgi and ~stdout~ is the response – logging has to go to a separate file. Not even ~stderr~ as I want debug
logs not to taint the webserver error log in case. And I would like to funnel logging through ~Logs~.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yawar Amin suggested and 🌍 Marcus Rohrmoser replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
I don't know about ~logs~ but it should be relatively easy to keep an open file handle and print log messages there.
#+end_quote

https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/logs/ - I like the loglevel approach. But maybe I will do without and pass around the
channel, yes.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Jean Michel suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I believe logs support logging to a file via Format. See
https://erratique.ch/software/logs/doc/Logs/index.html#val-format_reporter
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Shon also suggested</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I’ve found logs very ergonomic and easy to work with. I tend to pull it in via
[Bos](https://erratique.ch/software/bos), which has a very nice interface to OS interactions. Opening the ~Bos_setup~
module also does default logs configuration, and I find all quite painless and pleasant.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>🌍 Marcus Rohrmoser said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
thanks @yawaramin @beajeanm @shonfeder, I took a [middle
ground](https://codeberg.org/mro/seppo/src/branch/develop/lib/logr.ml) and went along the lines of
https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/logs/ (using the loglevels and logging call style) but base writing almost directly
on [out_channel](https://ocaml.org/api/Stdlib.html#TYPEout_channel). (I need a log rotation on top)

I was struggling with lost messages however – the logfile remained empty until I flushed after each log message.

Is that known behaviour that writing to a channel (with [Printf.fprintf](https://ocaml.org/api/Printf.html)) doesn't
necessarily end up in the file? Even when closed quickly.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>UnixJunkie replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
You must Printf.printf with "%!" at the end of your format string,
 to be sure that the log is flushed to file.

That's what I do in dolog:
https://github.com/UnixJunkie/dolog
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Timedesc 0.8.0 - modern date time handling</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-timedesc-0-8-0-modern-date-time-handling/10138/2</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Darren announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Tiny update: Timedesc 0.9.0 has been released, moving ~sexplib~ dependency into ~timedesc-sexp~ and moved from
~mparser~ to ~angstrom~ for some date time text parsers since angstrom is a strict necessity for some binary
(de)serialization already.

This overall means Timedesc is about as slim as it can get as a date time handling lib, depending only on: ~seq~,
~angstrom~, ~result~, and ~ptime~ (~ptime~ is not a strict dependency, but it's nice to have timedesc &lt;-&gt; ptime
convertors).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Florent Monnier asked</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Is this a lib that targets to process dates and time in a programmatically way?
(this is what the provided example make me think)
Or is it also supposed to be used to print something readable for a user else than a programmer?

If there is no end-user goal in this lib, please just ignore my message, and sorry to make you lose some time.

In the other case if you consider printing for end users, it's maybe worth to mention that there is the
[DateLocale-ocaml](https://github.com/fccm/DateLocale-ocaml) module that is available and which provides the name for
the months, and days for more than 200 languages. It also provides abbreviated versions for both months and days,
which are often used.

The [ocaml-community/calendar](https://github.com/ocaml-community/calendar) was not designed with localisation in
mind, it just does ~String.sub d 0 3~ to provide short names, which will not work with languages that need UTF8.

There is this PR that is still waiting for some review since 2 years to make it compatible with localisation:
[ocaml-community/calendar/pull/33](https://github.com/ocaml-community/calendar/pull/33/commits/9fcd7386e287f8841e503fb1d1e0547295aeb0c9).

(At least the patch is available there for someone who could be interested.)

I don't know if it could interest some one but I see that the example outputs a list of dates, that look like some
kind of logs. In case some one would like to visualise it in a way similar than the unix command ~cal~ you can just
create empty files where the file name follows the pattern YYYY-MM-DD like for example  "dir/2022-08-06.txt", you
will then be able to visualise it in the console with [detri](https://github.com/fccm/detri).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Darren replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
Is this a lib that targets to process dates and time in a programmatically way?
(this is what the provided example make me think)
Or is it also supposed to be used to print something readable for a user else than a programmer?
#+end_quote
Development has been primarily focused on former, mostly because solving it properly was already (very) involved.

Now that Timedesc has stabilised, the latter reads like a very nice next TODO to match feature parity of other date
time libs.

#+begin_quote
In the other case if you consider printing for end users, it’s maybe worth to mention that there is the
[DateLocale-ocaml](https://github.com/fccm/DateLocale-ocaml) module that is available and which provides the name for
the months, and days for more than 200 languages. It also provides abbreviated versions for both months and days,
which are often used.
#+end_quote

Looks neat! I believe there have been requests of locale sensitive pretty printing/conversion functions, so I
definitely would be interested in incorporating your work (if that was the intention).

#+begin_quote
I don’t know if it could interest some one but I see that the example outputs a list of dates, that look like some
kind of logs. In case some one would like to visualise it in a way similar than the unix command `cal` you can just
create empty files where the file name follows the pattern YYYY-MM-DD like for example “dir/2022-08-06.txt”, you will
then be able to visualise it in the console with [detri](https://github.com/fccm/detri).
#+end_quote

I was interested in something like this for another small utility cmd I've written, neat!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml website: Owl book not listed</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-website-owl-book-not-listed/10274/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Andreas Poisel said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It would be nice to add [OCaml Scientific Computing](https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-030-97645-3) to the
list on https://ocaml.org/books.

This is a great book and it would be a shame not to promote it.
Maybe anyone responsible for the website reads this or can point me in the right direction.

I'm not in any way affiliated with the authors of this book.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Application-specific Improvements to the Ecosystem</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/application-specific-improvements-to-the-ecosystem/10223/49</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Deep in this thread, Kay-Uwe Kirstein said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Personally, I often use the monadic Result type together with a polymorphic variant for the actual errors. This makes
dealing with errors from different "levels" of my software (library, command-line tool, and GUI) quite comfortable
(and type-safe!).
@keleshev has written a nice blog post on this: https://keleshev.com/composable-error-handling-in-ocaml with a recent
follow up: https://keleshev.com/advanced-error-handling-in-ocaml
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[https://ocaml.org/blog/][the ocaml.org blog]].

- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2022-08-02-irmin-in-the-browser][Irmin in the Browser]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
