<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2022.01.25</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2022.01.18</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2022.02.01</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>January 18 to 25, 2022</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>wu-manber-fuzzy-search 0.1.0 (new library)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-wu-manber-fuzzy-search-0-1-0-new-library/9173/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Ifaz Kabir announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to introduce wu-manber-fuzzy-seach, my library for doing fuzzy searches using the Wu and Manber fuzzy
search algorithm.

The novel part of this library particularly, when compared to ~agrep/ocamlagrep~, is that I additionally provide a
right-leaning variant of the algorithm. The variant reports better matches and error counts when looking at the first
match. Here's an example of the differences.

#+begin_src ocaml
# open Wu_Manber;;
# StringSearch.(search ~k:2 ~pattern:"brown" ~text:"quick brown fox" |> report);;
- : string = "Pattern matched with 2 errors at character 9 of text"
# StringSearch.(search_right_leaning ~k:2 ~pattern:"brown" ~text:"quick brown fox" |> report);;
- : string = "Pattern matched with 0 errors at character 11 of text"
#+end_src

It's a pure OCaml implementation, using ~Optint.Int63.t~ as bit-vectors. I don't current support all the extensions
that ~agrep/ocamlagrep~ supports, and will definitely not match the performance: OCaml+C vs pure OCaml.

The documentation for the library can be found [here](https://ifazk.github.io/wu-manber-fuzzy-search/).

It's not on ~opam~ yet, but there is a [PR](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/20479).

Expect more bitvector, Levenshtein distance, and fuzzy search shenanigans in the near future!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>findlib-1.9.2</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2022-01/msg00040.html</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Gerd Stolpmann announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
findlib-1.9.2 is out. The only change is a fix for a build problem
regarding the OCaml-5 trunk.

For manual, download, manuals, etc. see here:

http://projects.camlcity.org/projects/findlib.html

An updated OPAM package will follow soon.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Signals and Threads on Memory Management</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/signals-and-threads-on-memory-management/9190/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>gasche said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I just had an excellent time listening to the last Signals and Threads podcast episode on [Memory
Management](https://signalsandthreads.com/memory-management/), with Stephen Dolan (@stedolan) as the guest and Yaron
Minsky (@Yaron_Minsky) as the host discussing:
- memory management in programming languages in general
- memory management in OCaml
- ongoing research by Stephen and Leo White (@lpw25) on memory-management and data-representation features for OCaml (unboxed types, local values on the stack).

The link https://signalsandthreads.com/memory-management/ contains both the audio and a full text transcript.

I would warmly recommend giving it a try if you are interested in programming language implementation. There is new
stuff to learn for everyone, and I also liked the presentation of the parts I was already familiar with.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yaron Minsky replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks for the nice words. Interviewing Dolan was fun and I learned a lot.

Local types are still very new: we're hoping to start rolling it out in a limited way internally in the next few
weeks, and I expect we'll learn a lot from that. We plan on discussing it more publicly as well, but that's a bit
farther out. In the meantime, the source is all available [on Github](https://github.com/ocaml-flambda/ocaml-jst) if
anyone wants to poke around.

The approach to stack allocation is different and simpler than the one in Rust, as Dolan explained in the episode.
Instead of having implicit, polymorphic lifetime variables, function arguments can be marked as local, which prevents
the function in question from stashing a reference to those types. This avoids the need to deal with higher-rank
polymorphism, which Rust's lifetime approach requires, and as a result makes inference work nicely.

Another neat trick is that you can create functions that can allocate on the parent stack frame (by dint of not
having their own stack frame). This lets you build smart constructors for stack-allocated values.

Local types are apparently an example of modal types, though I don't really know enough type theory to have a deep
sense of what that means. But it's a powerful thing, and local types appear to be useful for more than just stack
allocation, as we're just starting to discover.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Yaron Minsky then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
And, I suppose as I should always mention: we're looking for people to come and work with Dolan and Leo and the rest
of the team on this kind of stuff.

More here:

https://blog.janestreet.com/applied-PL-research/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml 4.14.0, first alpha release</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-4-14-0-first-alpha-release/9191/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>octachron announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The set of new features for the future version 4.14.0 of OCaml has been (finally) stabilized, three months after the
release of OCaml 4.13.1. I am thus happy to announce the first alpha release for OCaml 4.14.0 .

This alpha version is here to help fellow hackers join us early in our bug hunting and opam ecosystem fixing fun (see
below for the installation instructions). You can see the progress on this front at
https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/issues/20501 .

If you find any bugs, please report them here:

  https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues

Most major OCaml developer tools are already supported with this alpha (from odoc to merlin), thus I expect us to
switch to beta releases in the beginning of February. The full release is expected to happen in late February.

This early release will give us time to focus on the release of OCaml 5.0.

If you are interested by the list of new features and the ongoing list of bug fixes, the updated change log for OCaml
4.14.0 is available at:

  https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/blob/4.14/Changes

Happy hacking,
Florian Angeletti for the OCaml team.

*** Installation instructions
The base compiler can be installed as an opam switch with the following commands
#+begin_example
opam update
opam switch create 4.14.0~alpha1 --repositories=default,beta=git+https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-beta-repository.git
#+end_example
With opam 2.1, the previous command line can be simplified to
#+begin_example
opam update
opam switch create 4.14.0~alpha1
#+end_example
If you want to tweak the configuration of the compiler, you can switch to the option variant with:
#+begin_example
opam update
opam switch create &lt;switch_name&gt; --packages=ocaml-variants.4.14.0~alpha1+options,&lt;option_list&gt;
--repositories=default,beta=git+https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-beta-repository.git
#+end_example
or with opam 2.1:
#+begin_example
opam update
opam switch create &lt;switch_name&gt; ocaml-variants.4.14.0~alpha1+options &lt;option_list&gt;
#+end_example

where ~&lt;option_list&gt;~ is a comma separated list of ocaml-option-* packages. For instance, for a flambda and
no-flat-float-array switch:
#+begin_example
opam switch create 4.14.0~alpha1+flambda+nffa ocaml-variants.4.14.0~alpha1+options ocaml-option-flambda
ocaml-option-no-flat-float-array
#+end_example
All available options can be listed with ~opam search ocaml-option~.

If you want to test this version, it is advised to install the alpha opam repository

https://github.com/kit-ty-kate/opam-alpha-repository

with
#+begin_example
opam repo add alpha git://github.com/kit-ty-kate/opam-alpha-repository.git
#+end_example
This alpha repository contains various fixes in the process of being upstreamed.

The source code for the alpha is also available at these addresses:

- https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/archive/4.14.0-alpha1.tar.gz
- https://caml.inria.fr/pub/distrib/ocaml-4.14/ocaml-4.14.0~alpha1.tar.gz
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>A brief survey for Learn-OCaml Community</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/a-brief-survey-for-learn-ocaml-community/9193/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Erik Martin-Dorel announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[This post is just a follow-up of an earlier message on
[caml-list](https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/caml-list/2021-12/msg00007.html), intended to reach more learn-ocaml
instructors, so you can ignore this one if you already replied!]

The OCaml Software Foundation is developing the teaching platform Learn-OCaml that provides auto-graded exercises for
OCaml, and was initially authored by OCamlPro for the OCaml MOOC: https://ocaml-sf.org/learn-ocaml.

The platform is free software and easy to deploy; this is great, but as a result we keep learning of
users/deployments that we had no idea of. We would be interested in having a better view of our user-base.

If you use Learn-OCaml as a teacher, could you fill *[this Evento
survey](https://evento.renater.fr/survey/learn-ocaml-community-survey-vsn3yc7j)* to let us know?
(the survey will be closed on 2022-02-07)

→ It contains these questions:
- Where are you using Learn-OCaml? (in which university (a specific course?), which company, online community or…?)
- Would you like to see your university/company added in [github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml-places](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml-places#readme)?
- How many students/learners use your deployment in a year?

And just to recall, a few links:

- For an example of Learn-OCaml instance, see https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/interesting-ocaml-exercises-from-francois-pottier-available-online/7050
- Last October we had a 0.13.0 release with several new features: https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-release-of-ocaml-sf-learn-ocaml-0-13-0/8577
- For any question related to Learn-OCaml, feel free to create a discussion topic on https://discuss.ocaml.org, category *~Community~*, tag *~learn-ocaml~* (/similarly to this discussion topic!/ :slight_smile:)
- And if need be, opening an issue in https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml/issues if of course warmly welcome as well.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Blog post: Js_of_ocaml, a bundle size study</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/blog-post-js-of-ocaml-a-bundle-size-study/9211/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Javier Chávarri announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi all, I hope your Monday is going great. :slight_smile:

I wanted to analyze bundle size performance in Js_of_ocaml, so I rewrote an existing ReScript web app to compare both
outputs.

Here is the blog post with all the data, conclusions, and takeaways:

https://www.javierchavarri.com/js_of_ocaml-bundle-size-study/

It has been a very interesting experiment, that helped me learn more about Js_of_ocaml and the way it generates
JavaScript code, and also improve some small things along the way in the libraries I was using for the project.

The conclusions, while maybe already known by others, are also quite exciting to me, as the experiment confirms my
suspicion that Js_of_ocaml bundle size scales just fine as applications get more complex, so it is suitable for a
quite significant number of real world scenarios.

I hope you find it interesting and exciting as well. Please share any feedback you might have! Or any questions if
anything is unclear.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Interesting OCaml Articles</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/interesting-ocaml-articles/1867/94</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Yotam Barnoy said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
https://blog.darklang.com/first-thoughts-on-rust-vs-ocaml/#tooling-musing
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
