<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2023.04.25</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2023.04.18</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2023.05.02</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>April 18 to 25, 2023</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Dream development stream + OCaml office hours</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/dream-development-stream-ocaml-office-hours/11977/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Anton Bachin announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Chat with me while I develop [Dream](https://github.com/aantron/dream#readme), but
also ask any questions at all about OCaml!

#+begin_quote
[*https://www.twitch.tv/antron_ML*](https://www.twitch.tv/antron_ML)
#+end_quote

I'll be streaming Dream development on Twitch at 14:00 CEST (Paris time) on most
weekdays, and definitely on every Thursday. Each time, I'll stream for at least one
hour.

Tomorrow, on Wednesday, April 19th, at 14:00 CEST, I will be continuing to review the
[Dream Eio PR](https://github.com/aantron/dream/pull/254) by @talex5 and
@Willenbrink, adding more detail to and revising the [Dream 1.0
roadmap](https://github.com/aantron/dream/wiki/1.0-Roadmap-Draft), and generally just
be available to talk about anything related to OCaml. We can build toy projects,
demos, work out concepts, etc. If you'd like to contribute to Dream, we can discuss
good first issues, review your PRs, and collabarote otherwise!

Outside the stream, I can be reached in #webdev on the [OCaml
Discord](https://discord.gg/neFgQbsH) or #dream on the [Reason
Discord](https://discord.gg/reasonml). My nickname on both is *antron*.

In the future, I'd be happy to consider something more interactive than a Twitch
stream -- something where people can talk back, probably some sort of developer or
contributor meeting. But it seems that Twitch is the right place to get started.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Anton Bachin later said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to everyone for coming to the stream today! We had a pretty good viewership!
The next stream is tomorrow, Thursday, April 20th, at the same time: 14:00 CEST.

Today, we got the Eio PR building, and found some problems with it -- fixing those
problems offline and during the next stream will be a good way to start reviewing the
internal changes in detail! We also talked about plans for Dream and discussed some
of Dream's dependencies and developer tools.

I post the next stream time and its topic in the banner image of the
[stream](https://www.twitch.tv/antron_ML), so you can easily find out when it's
planned even when the stream is offline. Planned streams are also in the
[schedule](https://www.twitch.tv/antron_ML/schedule). For weekdays besides Thursday,
I'll decide about streaming a few days in advance.

Suggestions for how to make the stream nicer are welcome :) I try to maintain a good
look for my windows and use some goofy VSCode extensions. If we start doing long,
boring builds, we can maybe add games for viewers to play or even a cat cam, though I
think that is a stretch at this point :) So far, I've been able to do all the very
slow stuff offline.

As the stream becomes more of a regular occurrence, I'll stop posting about it here,
but I'll probably continue to announce it in the
[Reason](https://discord.gg/reasonml) and [OCaml
Discords](https://discord.gg/neFgQbsH), once I figure out what channels are
appropriate for that. Probably #dream and #webdev, respectively.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New release of Menhir (20230415)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-new-release-of-menhir-20230415/11983/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>François Pottier announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It is my pleasure to announce a new release of Menhir, with a number of minor
improvements.

The change log appears below. The main point of notice is that (when using the code
back-end) the default optimization level has been changed from ~-O 2~ to ~-O 1~. So,
if you need to keep identical generated code and performance, you should now
explicitly pass ~-O 2~ to Menhir.

#+begin_example
  opam update
  opam install menhir.20230415
#+end_example

*** 2023/04/15

- When using the code back-end, the default optimization level is now ~-O 1~
  instead of ~-O 2~. Some users reported that ~-O 2~ is too aggressive and
  can cause a blow-up in the size of the code.

- Tweak the code for compatibility with OCaml 5.1. (Contributed by
  Florian Angeletti.)

- The new function ~MenhirLib.LexerUtil.tabulate~ makes it easy to run
  the lexer and parser in two separate phases. This can be useful when
  one wishes to benchmark them separately.

- To use the interpreter and print a concrete syntax tree, it used to be
  necessary to pass both ~--interpret~ and ~--interpret-show-cst~. It is
  now sufficient to pass just ~--interpret-show-cst~. (If both are passed,
  then only the last one is obeyed.) This fixes the assertion failure that
  would be observed when ~--interpret-show-cst~ alone was used.
  (Reported by Reed Mullanix.)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Functional web applications running in the browser</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-functional-web-applications-running-in-the-browser/11984/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Helmut announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am pleased to announce the first release of the  library
[fmlib_browser](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_browser/).

If you want to write functional web applications running in the browser the library
[fmlib_browser](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_browser/) might interest you.
It allows web applications in the [elm](https://elm-lang.org/) style using the much
more powerful language ocaml.

I have discovered the elm language some years ago and I am convinced that this kind
to write web applications is one important future way to develop web applications. So
I wanted to have the same in the ocaml language. Therefore I have developed this
library (and of course using js_of_ocaml as the compiler to javascript) and I am
quite happy that it works well.

Some [simple examples](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/webapp/index.html) of web
applications and the corresponding [source
code](https://github.com/hbr/fmlib/blob/master/src/examples/browser/webapp.ml)
written by using the library
[fmlib_browser](https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_browser/).

Install the library via opam by issuing the command

#+begin_example
    opam install fmlib_browser
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Benjamin Thomas asked and Helmut replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
Hello @hbr, thanks for sharing your project :)

Did you know about ocaml-vdom before creating this lib?

https://github.com/LexiFi/ocaml-vdom

If yes, why did you create it? How does it differ?
#+end_quote

@benjamin-thomas: I know the project ~ocaml-vdom~ and the basic idea with respect to
virtual dome is very similar. However I wanted to have something more generic.

If you look into the interface of ~ocaml-vdom~ you see that e.g. the event handlers
are limited to the definitions in the library. With ~Fmlib_browser~ you can customize
your event handlers completely. My event handlers use elm's generic concept of
decoders to suck any information you want from the events.

The properties in my library are generic. You can create arbitrary javascript value
including objects and arrays. In ~ocaml-vdom~ you are limited to primitive values
like ~int~, ~float~, ~string~ and ~bool~.

Furthermore I wanted to have a pretty generic interface between the javascript world
and the ocaml world.

The concept of ~Fmlib_browser~ is extendible. In the future I want to add features
e.g. to start web workers, integrate custom elements to have access e.g. to ~code
mirror~.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Timmy 1.0.0, a high level time and calendar library</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-timmy-1-0-0-a-high-level-time-and-calendar-library/11986/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>mefyl announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the availability on OPAM of the first stable version of
[Timmy](https://github.com/mefyl/timmy), the library that powers all the time and
calendar operations we perform at Routine.

It provides amongst other things:

- Higher level types for time and calendar values.
- Uncompromising timezone safety.
- Timezone with DST support.
- ISO weeks support.
- Quality of life operators and common computations on most objects.
- JavaScript back and forth conversions.

The philosophy and rationale for the library is [explained at length in its root
module documentation ](https://mefyl.github.io/timmy/timmy/index.html). Comments and
contributions very welcome.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Wed, Apr 19 @ 7pm U.S. Central: Jonah Beckford on "What distributing OCaml on Windows gave me (and you)”</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/wed-apr-19-7pm-u-s-central-jonah-beckford-on-what-distributing-ocaml-on-windows-gave-me-and-you/11926/6</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, jbeckford said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks. Reminds me to share the slides:
https://diskuv.gitlab.io/books/DkPresentations/Presentations/2023-04-19-hfpug/

I think the recording will be available in several days.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Claude Jager-Rubinson later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The video is now available on the HFPUG website at
https://hfpug.org/2023/04/21/jonah-beckford-what-distributing-ocaml-on-windows-gave-me-and-you/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>The OCaml Changelog</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/the-ocaml-changelog/11998/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Thibaut Mattio announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The OCaml.org team is happy to announce the [OCaml
Changelog](https://ocaml.org/changelog): a feed of the latest releases and feature
highlights of the OCaml Compiler, OCaml Platform tools, and other core projects.

Beyond being the easiest way to stay up to date with the activity of official
projects, the Changelog serves as a way to discover important new features that might
otherwise go unnoticed. For instance, did you know that Dune 3.7 introduced native
polling mode for Windows, effectively making watch mode available on Windows
(contributed by @nojb and [@yams-yams](https://github.com/yams-yams))? Or that we
recently released Mdx 2.3.0 with support for running code blocks in mld files
(contributed by @jonludlam)? Or that we added new options in OCamlFormat for more
consistent vertical formatting of if-else and match statements (contributed by
@gpetiot)?

To that end, we're highlighting important features from the releases with visual
demos and explanations of how to use them.

I'll note that the Changelog is still experimental at this point. We've talked with
some maintainers of the projects featured on the Changelog, but we'll need to agree
with everyone on what the release process of the tools will look like if we commit to
maintaining the Changelog in the long term. Until we've reached a consensus, the
OCaml.org team will be monitoring the activity of the projects and create the
changelog entries, eventually reaching out to maintainers to write announcements and
feature highlights.

In the meanwhile, let us know what you think and how we can improve the Changelog,
we're excited to get your feedback!

Happy reading!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OUPS meetup may 2023</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/oups-meetup-may-2023/11999/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>zapashcanon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The next OUPS meetup will take place on *Thursday, 11th of May* 2023. It will start
at *7pm* at the *4 place Jussieu* in Paris.

:warning: :trumpet: It will be in the in the *Herpin amphitheater* in the
*Esclangon building*. :trumpet: :warning:

Please, *[register on meetup](https://www.meetup.com/fr-FR/ocaml-paris/events/292972153)* as soon as possible to
let us know how many pizza we should order.

For more details, you may check the [OUPS’ website ](https://oups.frama.io).

This month will feature the following talks :

*Retrofitting OCaml Modules -- Clément Blaudeau*

ML modules offer large-scale notions of composition and modularity. Provided as an
additional layer on top of the core language, they have proven both vital to the
working OCaml and SML programmers, and inspiring to other use-cases and languages.
Unfortunately, their meta-theory remains difficult to comprehend, and more recent
extensions (abstract signatures, module aliases) lack a complete formalization.
Building on a previous translation from ML modules to Fω, we propose a new
comprehensive description of a significant subset of OCaml modules, including both
applicative and generative functors and transparent ascription -- a useful new
feature. By exploring the translations both to and from Fω, we provide a complete
description of the signature avoidance issue, as well as insights on the limitations
and benefits of the path-based approach of OCaml type-sharing.

*Formal reasoning rules for the OCaml FFI --* *Armaël Guéneau* (@Armael)

OCaml provides an FFI mechanism (Foreign Function Interface) allowing OCaml programs
to call external functions implemented in C, typically by writing "glue code" helping
bridge the two languages.
This "glue code" needs to be carefully written and obey a number of rules when
interacting with the OCaml runtime (cf chapter 22 of the manual). Failure to follow
one of these rules typically result in silent corruption of the program memory,
resulting in fatal and hard to debug crashes.
This presentation will present ongoing research on *formalizing* the rules one need
to follow to correctly use the OCaml FFI. We will see how a small number of
*permissions* can capture the requirements one must obey in order to write bug-free
glue code.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>3-year engineering position in Deducteam, Inria Paris-Saclay, France</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/3-year-engineering-position-in-deducteam-inria-paris-saclay-france/12001/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Frédéric Blanqui announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Deducteam is offering a 3-year engineering position to help develop, test and
maintain tools for proof system interoperability (continuous integration, proof
libraries management, searching tools, VSCode interface, etc.). Net taxable monthly
salary between 2148 and 4412 euros depending on experience, including social security
and 9 weeks holidays/year.

Interested people should send me their CV before *30 July 2023*. Applications will
be examined over time.

Best regards, Frédéric Blanqui, chair of EuroProofNet.
https://blanqui.gitlabpages.inria.fr/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>RFC for a distributed process/actor model library</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/rfc-for-a-distributed-process-actor-model-library/12004/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Darren announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I recently wrote down what's been brewing in my mind for a bit: a Erlang style
process/actor model library in the new OCaml 5 landscape. It is beginning to resemble
something I'd use, but I'm curious about what others think.

The repo of the prototype is available at
[here](https://github.com/darrenldl/distrproc)

The library is built on top of Eio and should place nicely with Eio primitives.
Snippet of a runnable example is shown below (~debug/main.ml~ in the repo).

Overview:
- ~Gateway~ plays roughly the role of Erlang's BEAM VM.
  - Intention is user can establish TLS tunnels to other gateways to allow distribution.
- ~Mailbox.Local~ API allows skipping the serialization cost when sending things internally
  - ~Mailbox.Global.t~ (when implemented) conversely demands serialization procedures during construction.
- Process *a* uses selective receive interface (~Selective.recv~ and ~Selective.Recv.*~) to handle timeout and guards/message filtering.
  - A save queue is used underneath per mailbox for messages rejected (for now), following Erlang's design.
  - Doesn't seem possible to have a global save queue without also serialising everything.
- Process *b* sends a bunch of things *a* does not care about, wait, then finally sends something *a* is looking for.
- Process *controller* is just largely there to demonstrate one can redirect processes.

*** Code snippet
(~debug/main.ml~ on repo)

#+begin_src ocaml
let () =
  let pid_mailbox : Proc.Pid.t Mailbox.Local.t =
    Mailbox.Local.make ()
  in
  let Mailbox.Local.{ send = send_pid; recv = recv_pid } = Mailbox.Local.interface
pid_mailbox in
  let x_mailbox  : x Mailbox.Local.t =
    Mailbox.Local.make ()
  in
  let Mailbox.Local.{ send = send_x; recv = recv_x } = Mailbox.Local.interface
x_mailbox in
  let a =
    Gateway.spawn (fun h ->
        Fmt.epr "a: my pid is %a@." Proc.Pid.pp (Proc.Handle.pid h);

        let _, send_to = recv_pid h in
        Fmt.epr "a: received instruction to send to %a@." Proc.Pid.pp send_to;
        send_x h (send_to, A);
        send_x h (send_to, A);
        send_x h (send_to, A);

        let rec aux () =
          let success =
            Selective.recv h
              ~timeout:(1.0, fun () ->
                  Fmt.epr "a: I haven't received anything useful yet@.";
                  false
                )
              Selective.Recv.[
                case_local x_mailbox
                  [
                    entry ~guard:(fun (from, x) -> x = A)
                      (fun (from, msg) ->
                         Fmt.epr "a: received %a from %a@." pp_x msg Proc.Pid.pp
from;
                         true
                      );
                    entry ~guard:(fun (from, x) -> x = B)
                      (fun (from, msg) ->
                         Fmt.epr "a: received %a from %a@." pp_x msg Proc.Pid.pp
from;
                         true
                      );
                  ]
              ]
          in
          if not success then
            aux ()
        in
        aux ()
      )
  in
  let b =
    Gateway.spawn (fun h ->
        Fmt.epr "b: my pid is %a@." Proc.Pid.pp (Proc.Handle.pid h);
        let _, send_to = recv_pid h in
        Fmt.epr "b: received instruction to send to %a@." Proc.Pid.pp send_to;

        let clock = Eio.Stdenv.clock (Proc.Handle.env h) in

        send_x h (send_to, C);
        send_x h (send_to, C);
        send_x h (send_to, C);
        send_x h (send_to, C);
        send_x h (send_to, C);
        send_x h (send_to, C);

        Eio.Time.sleep clock 5.0;

        send_x h (send_to, A);

        let from, msg = recv_x h in
        Fmt.epr "b: received %a from %a@." pp_x msg Proc.Pid.pp from;
      )
  in
  let _controller =
    Gateway.spawn (fun h ->
        Fmt.epr "controller: my pid is %a@." Proc.Pid.pp (Proc.Handle.pid h);
        send_pid h (a, b);
        Fmt.epr "controller: sent instructions to a@.";
        send_pid h (b, a);
        Fmt.epr "controller: sent instructions to b@.";
      )
  in
  Eio_main.run Gateway.main
#+end_src

*** Example output
#+begin_example
  a: my pid is (0, 3)
  b: my pid is (0, 4)
  controller: my pid is (0, 5)
  a: received instruction to send to (0, 4)
  controller: sent instructions to a
  b: received instruction to send to (0, 3)
  controller: sent instructions to b
  a: I haven't received anything useful yet
  a: I haven't received anything useful yet
  a: I haven't received anything useful yet
  a: I haven't received anything useful yet
  b: received A from (0, 3)
  a: I haven't received anything useful yet
  a: received A from (0, 4)
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>cfgen preview release v1.0.0-alpha.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-cfgen-preview-release-v1-0-0-alpha-0/12016/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Chris Armstrong announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce the first pre-release of
[*cfgen*](https://github.com/chris-armstrong/ocaml-cfgen), a library for writing
AWS CloudFormation definitions in OCaml and generating working CloudFormation
templates.

It is usable in its current form, but still under development. This release is to
gather feedback and gauge community interest in its continued development.

Please see the
[tutorial](https://chris-armstrong.github.io/ocaml-cfgen/cfgen/tutorial) and
[documentation](https://chris-armstrong.github.io/ocaml-cfgen/cfgen/index.html) to
get an understanding of how it works and its current feature set.

You can currently install it directly from git using opam with the tag
~v1.0.0-alpha.0~

https://github.com/chris-armstrong/ocaml-cfgen
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[https://ocaml.org/blog/][the ocaml.org blog]].

- [[https://blog.janestreet.com/building-reproducible-python-environments-with-xars/][Building reproducible Python environments with XARs]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
