<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2023.03.14</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2023.03.07</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2023.03.21</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>March 07 to 14, 2023</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head></cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>My experience contributing to the LLVM bindings</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/my-experience-contributing-to-the-llvm-bindings/11599/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>alan announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Over the past few months, I've been contributing patches to the LLVM bindings. In particular, I ported the bindings
to OCaml 5, which involved removing naked pointers. I wrote about what I learned
[here](https://alan-j-hu.github.io/writing/llvm-ocaml.html).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Which binding should i use for sqlite , for mariadb and for postgresql</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/which-binding-should-i-use-for-sqlite-for-mariadb-for-postgresql/11605/2</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Alain De Vos asked and Nicolas Ojeda Bar replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
Which binding should i use for sqlite , for mariadb &amp; for postgresql ?
#+end_quote

At LexiFi we have used https://github.com/mmottl/postgresql-ocaml for PostgreSQL and
https://github.com/mmottl/sqlite3-ocaml for SQLite for a long time and found them solid.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Kim Nguyễn also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
If you are looking for a unified API, there is [Caqti](https://github.com/paurkedal/ocaml-caqti). It uses the lower
level bindings mentioned by @nojb (and also supports MariaDB using
[mariadb-ocaml](https://github.com/andrenth/ocaml-mariadb). It feels like the "jdbc for OCaml" but with much more!

It provides three high-level API, either a standard blocking interface, or asynchronous with Lwt or asynchronous
with Janestreet's Async).
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Frédéric Loyer then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Caqti is nice and can be completed nicely with ppx_rapper which transforms a commented SQL string into a typed
wrapper.

See https://github.com/roddyyaga/ppx_rapper
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Monday, 6th March - Outreachy Intern Presentation (Dec '22 Round)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/monday-6th-march-outreachy-intern-presentation-dec-22-round/11564/5</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Patrick Ferris announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The presentation is now online: https://watch.ocaml.org/w/pQSAfZ9kDSsSnr8Bxzocn3

Thank you @Prisca for the talk and everybody for joining live. We took this opportunity to reupload everything to
the OCaml Outreachy channel under the ~bactrian~ user: https://watch.ocaml.org/c/outreachy_ocaml/videos
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Anil Madhavapeddy asked and Prisca replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
Your slides look great, with lots of nice OCaml/TopoJSON code fragments; might you consider making them available
online somewhere? Making yourself a homepage, or using something like Speakerdeck are both good options.
#+end_quote

@avsm Thank you very much for the kind words. I just did. This is the link
https://speakerdeck.com/priceless/presentation

#+begin_quote
I noticed you published a release of the library to opam – you should add yourself to the authors list in
~dune-project~, so that you are credited in [the documentation page for TopoJSON
](https://ocaml.org/p/topojson/latest).
#+end_quote

Thank you for pointing that out as well. @patrickferris and I will correct it.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First release of ppx_subliner, a ppx deriver and rewriter for Cmldliner sub-command</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-first-release-of-ppx-subliner-a-ppx-deriver-and-rewriter-for-cmldliner-sub-command/11610/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Boning announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I am very pleased to announce the first release of [~ppx_subliner~](https://github.com/bn-d/ppx_subliner)! The
package is now available through [OPAM](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/ppx_subliner/).

I am always a big fan of [~ppx_deriving_cmdliner~](https://github.com/hammerlab/ppx_deriving_cmdliner). It helps
you construct ~Cmdliner.Term.t~ from record types and makes writing cli parsing intuitive and painless. But it
lacks the ability to generate values for sub-command groups and the final ~Cmdliner~ evaluations. Therefore,
~ppx_subliner~ comes to life.

~ppx_subliner~ can work with ~ppx_deriving_cmdliner~ to generate sub-command groups. You can do so by simply
tagging the extension to a variant type.

#+begin_src ocaml
type foo = { my_arg : string } [@@deriving cmdliner]

type params =
  | Foo of foo
  | Bar
[@@deriving_inline subliner]
include
  sig
    [@@@ocaml.warning "-32"]
    val params_cmdliner_group_cmds : (params -> 'a) -> 'a Cmdliner.Cmd.t list
  end[@@ocaml.doc "@inline"]
[@@@end]
#+end_src

It will generate a function which takes in a handle function and return the sub-command list. Here is a simple
handle function.

#+begin_src ocaml
let handle = function
  | Foo { my_arg } -> print_endline ("Foo " ^ my_arg)
  | Bar -> print_endline "Bar"
#+end_src

From here, you either construct the final evaluation manually:

#+begin_src ocaml
let cmd =
  let open Cmdliner in
  let doc = "Some docs" in
  let info = Cmd.info ~doc "foobar" in
  Cmd.group info (params_cmdliner_group_cmds handle)

let () = exit (Cmdliner.eval cmd)
#+end_src

or use the ~[%%subliner.cmds]~ rewriter, which reuses the setfield syntax:

#+begin_src ocaml
(* {eval function}.{type name} &lt;- {function expression&gt; *)
#+end_src
#+begin_src ocaml
[%%subliner.cmds eval.params &lt;- handle]
[@@name "foobar"] [@@version "3.14"]
(** Some docs *)
#+end_src

#+begin_example
$ foobar.exe foo --my-arg 123
Foo 123
#+end_example

Both the deriver and rewriter will respect the OCaml docstring. You can also use ~[@name]~, ~[@man]~, ~[@envs]~ etc
to configure all aspects of the underlying ~Cmdliner.Cmd.info~ value.

You can also use different evaluation function and set optional arguments:

#+begin_src ocaml
[%%subliner.cmds (eval_result ~catch:false).params &lt;-
  (function
    | Foo { my_arg } -> print_endline ("Foo " ^ my_arg) |> Result.ok
    | Bar -> print_endline "Bar" |> Result.ok)]
#+end_src

Please see more details in the [documentation](https://boni.ng/ppx_subliner/ppx_subliner/index.html).

*** What's next
I want to support inline record and enum as arg in the future, and maybe replicate some of
~ppx_deriving_cmdliner~'s functionality, but better support for ~deriving_inline~, lists (ie. ~-I liba -I libb~
instead of ~-I liba,libb~), positional arguments and more compile time validation. We shall see.

Hope this is helpful. Happy hacking!

https://github.com/bn-d/ppx_subliner
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Cross-compiling for Embedded arm32 Target (RP2040 / Cortex-M0+)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/cross-compiling-for-embedded-arm32-target-rp2040-cortex-m0/11585/8</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Deep in this thread, Calascibetta Romain said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Note that you probably should take a look on [gilbraltar](https://github.com/dinosaure/gilbraltar) which is a full
OCaml runtime for Rasperry Pi 4 (arm64).  We already did several works on this _ocaml toolchain_, a ["guirlande
OS"](https://twitter.com/Dinoosaure/status/1471128595154231300) or a [music player OS via Jack](https://tarides.com/blog/2022-10-28-the-mirageos-retreat-a-journey-of-food-cats-and-unikernels#implementing-a-jack-port-driver-or-how-to-make-a-unikernel-sing-bare-metal).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>VOCaml: add and remove type annotations in VS Code</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/vocaml-add-and-remove-type-annotations-in-vs-code/11618/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Lukasz Stafiniak announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce [a VS Code extension
VOCaml](https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=lukstafi.vocaml) ([GitHub
release](https://github.com/lukstafi/vocaml/releases/tag/1.0.0)) where I'll be putting my OCaml coding helpers.
Currently, it has three commands:

- /VOCaml: Add Type Annotations/ inserts type annotations around let bindings.
- /VOCaml: Remove Type Annotations/ removes type annotations from let bindings.
- /VOCaml: Visit File from Current Line/ triggers a *Quick Open* dialog populated with a file and line number retrieved from the line at cursor position.

VOCaml is a companion to [~ppx_minidebug~](https://github.com/lukstafi/ppx_minidebug), but it can be used for its
own merits. It has some limitations, report issues if you try it!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Sunsetting opam-repository-mingw</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/sunsetting-opam-repository-mingw/11632/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>David Allsopp announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
As [previously announced](https://fdopen.github.io/opam-repository-mingw/2021/02/26/repo-discontinued),
"opam-repository-mingw" is no longer receiving updates.

We're actively working on getting the Windows compiler packages into
[ocaml/opam-repository](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository). There are two issues which are taking (me) a
little while to finish solving, but more on that further below.

In the gap - of hopefully only a month or so - for this being ready, there's is an issue that new releases are of
course not available when opam-repository-mingw is being used with
[~ocaml/setup-ocaml@v2~](https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml) GitHub actions workflows. I'm hoping here to set out
what's happening, and what steps you may need to take to keep your GitHub Actions Windows workflows running
smoothly over the next few months.

*** What's happening right now?

We've updated setup-ocaml to use
[ocaml-opam/opam-repository-mingw](https://github.com/ocaml-opam/opam-repository-mingw) instead of
[fdopen/opam-repository-mingw](https://github.com/fdopen/opam-repository-mingw) (see
[ocaml/setup-ocaml#651](https://github.com/ocaml/setup-ocaml/pull/651)). This clone has been augmented with:
- OCaml 4.14.1 packages, in the same style as the 4.14.0 forked packages (the "pre-compiled" package variants exist, but they're not pre-compiled)
- Changes to the constraints for _existing_ packages only

If you're using setup-ocaml in its default configuration, you should notice no change except that ~4.14.x~ builds
should now use 4.14.1 and the initial build will be a little slower as it builds from sources (GitHub Actions
caching will then take over for subsequent runs).

For new releases of packages, it's necessary to _add_ opam-repository to the repositories selections for the
switches. It's important that opam-repository is at a _lower priority_ than opam-repository-mingw for existing
packages, so it's better to use these lines in your ~ocaml/setup-ocaml@v2~ step than to issue ~opam repo add
--rank=1000~ later:

#+begin_example
uses: ocaml/setup-ocaml@v2
with:
  opam-repositories: |
    opam-repository-mingw: https://github.com/ocaml-opam/opam-repository-mingw.git#sunset
    default: https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository.git
#+end_example

*** What do I do when things are broken?

There's an issue tracker on
[ocaml-opam/opam-repository-mingw](https://github.com/ocaml-opam/opam-repository-mingw/issues), and this is a very
good place to start.

If a version of a package isn't building, there are three possible remedies:

- Previous versions of the package may have carried non-upstreamed patches in opam-repository-mingw.
opam-repository's policy is not to carry such patches. In this case, the package actually doesn't work on Windows.
  - opam-repository should be updated to have ~os != "win32"~ added to the ~available~ field for the package
  - An issue on the package's upstream repo should be opened highlighting the need to upstream patches (or even a pull request with them!)
  - The patches in opam-repository-mingw make changes which may not necessarily be accepted/acceptable upstream in their current form, so the issue may be a better starting point than simply taking a patch and opening a pull request for it (for example, the ~utop~ package contains patches which may require further work and review)
- The package relies on environment changes in "OCaml for Windows". For example, the Zarith package works in "OCaml for Windows" because the compiler packages unconditionally set the ~CC~ environment variable. This change is both not particularly desirable change to upstream (it is _very_ confusing, for example, when working on the compiler itself) and also extremely difficult to upstream, so the fix here is instead to change the package's availability with ~(os != "win32" | os-distribution = "cygwinports")~ and constrain away OCaml 5 on Windows (~"ocaml" {&lt; "5.0" | os != "win32"}~)
- Package constraints on _existing packages_ need updating in ocaml-opam/opam-repository-mingw. For example, the release of ppxlib 0.29 required some existing packages to have upperbounds added.

*** What about OCaml 5.0.0?

OCaml 5.0.0 was released with support for the mingw-w64 port only, however, there's a quite major bug which wasn't
caught by OCaml's testsuite, but is relatively easily triggered by opam packages. I've [previously
announced](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/pre-ann-installing-windows-ocaml-5-0-0-in-opam/11150) how to add OCaml 5 to
a workflow. For the time being, the packages for OCaml 5 aren't automatically made available.

*** What's next?

The ultimate goal is to be using an upstream build of ~opam.exe~ with ocaml/opam-repository, just as on Unix. Once
opam 2.2 is generally available (we're aiming for an alpha release at the end of March) and the compiler packages
in opam-repository support the Windows builds, we will recommend stopping use of opam-repository-mingw completely.
The default in setup-ocaml won't change straight away, since that risks breaking existing workflows.

With upstream compiler support, we'll be able to extend some of the existing bulk build support already being done
for Linux to Windows and start to close the gap of patches in opam-repository-mingw.

*** Windows compiler packages

I mentioned earlier the problems with moving the compiler packages into opam-repository, and just for general
interest this elaborates on them.

The first issue affects the use of the Visual Studio port ("MSVC") and is a consequence of the somewhat strange way
that the C compiler is added to the environment when using the Visual Studio C compiler. "OCaml for Windows" (as
well as Diskuv) use a wrapper command (it's ~ocaml-env~ in "OCaml for Windows" and ~with-dkml~ in Diskuv). Those
commands are Windows-specific, which is an issue for upstream opam. There's an alternate way which sets the
environment variables in a more opam-like way. Doing it that way, though, requires an improvement to opam's
environment handling which is in opam 2.2, otherwise there's an easy risk of "blowing" the environment.

The second issue is selecting the C compiler. On Unix, this is easy
with ~ocaml-base-compiler~ because there is only one "system" C compiler. Windows has two ports of OCaml, and the
configuration requires it to be explicitly selected. That requires input from the user on switch creation for a
Windows switch.

"OCaml for Windows" solves this by packaging the Windows compilers with the variant name appended, just as
opam-repository used to, so ~ocaml-variants.4.14.1+mingw64~ selects the the mingw-w64 port and
~ocaml-variants.4.14.1+msvc64~ selects the MSVC64 port. The problem, as we already had in opam-repository, is that
this adds 4 packages for each release of OCaml in ~ocaml-variants~, and leads to a combinatorial explosion when we
start considering flambda and other relevant compiler options.

opam-repository switched to using the ~ocaml-option-~ packages to solve the combinatorial explosion which was
already present in opam-repository. The demonstration repo for OCaml 5 on Windows is already using an adapted
version of this so that ~ocaml-option-mingw~ selects the mingw-w64 port (by default 64-bit, with
~ocaml-option-32bit~ then selecting the 32-bit port).

This work is all in progress and being tested alongside changes in  opam 2.2 to support the _depext_ experience on
Windows. The only reason that's not being upstreamed piecemeal is that changes to the compiler packages in
opam-repository trigger switch rebuilds all over the world, so we don't want to that until we're sure that the
packages are correct. The intention is to do this around the time of the alpha release of opam 2.2, once the work
in opam itself has settled down.

Thanks for getting to the end, and happy Windows CI testing!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Outreachy Summer 2023</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/outreachy-summer-2023/11159/10</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Paul-Elliot announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Just wanted to say that I also submitted an OCaml Outreachy project!

The goal of the project is to improve the error reporting in the PPXs ecosystem. This includes both modifying
ppxlib's behavior when catching an exception raised by a rewriter; and modify existing PPXs to better report error
(by embedding them inside the AST when relevant, allowing for both multiple error reporting, and creation of a
partial AST that contains all information that could be created).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>VS Code extension Alcotest Test Explorer 0.4.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-vs-code-extension-alcotest-test-explorer-0-4-0/11636/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Roland Csaszar announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to @Muqiu-Han a severe bug has been fixed: an exception
raised by ~failwith~ wasn't recognized as failure and the test result had been set to  'passed'.

Changelog:
*** Version 0.4.0 (2023-03-10)

- Mark a test case as failed if a ~[FAIL]~ tag is present, even if the actual error message can't be parsed.

*** Bugfixes

- Make the error parser recognize the exception generated by ~failwith~. (Fix [#1](https://github.com/Release-Candidate/vscode-ocaml-alcotest-test-adapter/issues/1))

*** Internal Changes

- Add test cases to check that the changes actually work.
- Fix typo in issue template.
- Correct the job name in the ~release~ GitHub workflow.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
