<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2023.11.07</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2023.10.31</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2023.11.14</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>October 31 to November 07, 2023</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>A second article about Miou</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://mastodon.social/@dinosaure/111295328688421482</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Dinosaure announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I finally made my second article about #Miou (#OCaml 5 &amp; #multicore) and its notion of rules. It's available here: https://blog.osau.re/articles/miou_rules.html (enjoy the reading).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>atddiff: report incompatibilities after modifying a typed interface</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/new-atddiff-report-incompatibilities-after-modifying-a-typed-interface/13347/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Martin Jambon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
*** Background
ATD stands for "Adjustable Type Definitions". The [ATD project](https://github.com/ahrefs/atd) consists of a
language for specifying types and their JSON representation and code generators that make it safe and easy to read
and write JSON data. It currently offers interoperability for 6 programming languages (D, Java, OCaml, Scala,
TypeScript, Python/Mypy).

*** Tracking incompatibilities with atddiff

Atddiff takes two versions of an ~.atd~ file, which is a collection of type definitions, compares them and reports
incompatibilities. Here's a simple example:

#+begin_src ocaml
(* example.v1.atd  *)
type t = {
  x: string;
}
#+end_src

#+begin_src ocaml
(* example.v2.atd *)
type t = {
  ?x: string option;
}
#+end_src

Atddiff finds one problem:
#+begin_example
$ atddiff example.v1.atd example.v2.atd
[221ed3ce] Forward incompatibility:
File "example.v1.atd", line 2, characters 2-11
File "example.v2.atd", line 2, characters 2-19:
Formerly required field 'x' is now optional.
The following types are affected:
  t
#+end_example

Incompatibilities can be backward (= can't read older data), forward (= can't read newer data), or both. Depending
on the use case for a type, the user may care about just one direction. The
[documentation](https://atd.readthedocs.io/en/latest/atd-language.html#how-to-change-a-json-interface-safely)
expands a bit on this and provides a command to use atddiff with git.

The recommended version of atddiff is the latest, >= 2.15.0. It is installed as part of the ~atd~ opam package:
#+begin_example
opam update
opam install atd.2.15.0
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml implementation of webbench</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-implementation-of-webbench/13348/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>bigconvience announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
*** Overview
[webbench_ml](https://github.com/bigconvience/webbench_ml) is the OCaml implementation of
[webbench](http://home.tiscali.cz/~cz210552/webbench.html)

*** Web Bench
Web Bench is very simple tool for benchmarking WWW or proxy servers. Uses fork() for simulating multiple clients and
can use HTTP/0.9-HTTP/1.1 requests. This benchmark is not very realistic, but it can test if your HTTPD can realy
handle that many clients at once (try to run some CGIs) without taking your machine down. Displays pages/min and
bytes/sec. Can be used in more aggressive mode with -f switch.

*** Build
#+begin_example
$ git clone https://github.com/bigconvience/webbench_ml.git
$ cd webbench_ml
$ eval `opam env`
$ dune build
$ dune exec -- webbench -t 10 -c 20 http://127.0.0.1:8000/
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Using Docusaurus to document an OCaml project</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/using-docusaurus-to-document-an-ocaml-project/13359/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Mathieu Barbin announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi!

I wanted to share some positive feedback on using [Docusaurus](https://docusaurus.io/) to document an OCaml Project:
[Bopkit](https://mbarbin.github.io/bopkit/).

Among the reasons I choose to experiment with it was its compatibility with ~ocaml-mdx~ and the ~dune-runtest~ &amp;
~dune-promote~ workflow. That is, a lot of the dynamic contents that shows in the doc stays in sync when the code is
updated during development, including file parts, expect tests traces and mermaid diagrams.

I also liked the fact that the contents is mostly based on ~*.md~ files that are present in the tree, and those that
can be browsed directly from GitHub as well (such as all the README.md found at the leaf of the project's directory
structure, which are rendered similarly by GitHub).

This integrates well with GitHub and GitHub Actions in that the doc can be hosted directly in the GitHub pages of
the project.

I've also experimented with their support for a global search box via
[algoalia](https://docusaurus.io/docs/search#using-algolia-docsearch) which was overall straight forward to setup.

As a side note, I just went through their [v3 migration guide](https://docusaurus.io/docs/migration/v3), and I liked
the experience.

Putting it out there in case you're interested in trying it out, or simply want to browse an example of a Docusaurus
setup involving an OCaml project using ~ocaml-mdx~ and ~dune~.

Thanks!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Release of ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml:0.16.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-release-of-ocaml-sf-learn-ocaml-0-16-0/13361/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Erik Martin-Dorel announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Dear all,

We are pleased to announce the latest stable release of [Learn-OCaml](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml),
version ~0.16.0~.

Many thanks to all users who contributed bugs reports, fixes, and enhancements!

A comprehensive list of the fixes and enhancements offered by this release is available in [the Release
Notes](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml/releases/tag/v0.16.0) which also gathers static binaries for Linux
and macOS, the corresponding [opam-repository pull request](https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/24739) is
pending, and the Docker images of [learn-ocaml](https://hub.docker.com/r/ocamlsf/learn-ocaml/tags) and
[learn-ocaml-client](https://hub.docker.com/r/ocamlsf/learn-ocaml-client/tags) are immediately available on Docker
Hub.

If you happen to maintain a ~learn-ocaml~ server, we strongly recommend that you update your version to ~0.16.0~ to
benefit from important fixes, as well as newest features.

*** Highlights

1. From a student point-of-view, a feature developed by M. Hernouf, D. Pinto, and L. Gesbert from OCamlPro significantly improves the UI/UX for the *exercises list*, adding three sub-tabs ~By category~, ~By skill~ (see the screenshot below), and ~By difficulty~, with collapsible blocks:

   https://global.discourse-cdn.com/business7/uploads/ocaml/original/2X/6/616d3600c476e1c58a9446961aac8a60fb6a847f.png

2. From a teacher point-of-view, the handling of *Open/Closed status for assigned exercises* has been significantly improved (cf. issues [#534](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml/issues/534) and [#558](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml/issues/558)). When exercises are assigned, learn-ocaml's teacher tab now shows the global-status of the exercises, especially for unassigned students (see the screenshot below). The underlying soundness invariant has been made explicit, and is now verified using a dedicated **ppx_expect** test suite.

   https://global.discourse-cdn.com/business7/uploads/ocaml/original/2X/5/5f7794020fdfb596233087987e94ce1c81e5b0a8.png

If need be, feel free to open issues in the [Learn-OCaml bug
tracker](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml/issues/new/choose) or the [learn-ocaml.el bug
tracker](https://github.com/pfitaxel/learn-ocaml.el/issues), or post in this thread to share comments.

Happy OCaml learning and teaching, and stay tuned for the next release!

Erik Martin-Dorel for the Learn-OCaml team 🐫
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Erik Martin-Dorel later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
For those who don't know the learn-ocaml platform yet:

- the [learn-ocaml](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml) artifact (distributed under the MIT license) is a full-stack web server written in OCaml, fully customizable to serve Markdown-based lectures and interactive exercises endowed with auto-grading tests, written in OCaml as well;
- an [emacs frontend](https://github.com/pfitaxel/learn-ocaml.el) for learn-ocaml is also available on [MELPA](https://melpa.org/#/learn-ocaml);
- the [learn-ocaml-corpus](https://github.com/ocaml-sf/learn-ocaml-corpus) is a large collection of exercises that originated in the [OCaml MOOC](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o0CK_7ruImE&amp;list=PLTBEN441uEY36t5CCrJkdTSv588d3nWN5) and has been further extended by several authors since then;
- a static instance of learn-ocaml, combining the latest release of learn-ocaml and learn-ocaml-corpus' exercises, is available at: [https://ocaml-sf.org/learn-ocaml-public/](https://ocaml-sf.org/learn-ocaml-public/#activity=exercises)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Discord.ml: Eio-based Discord library with voice support</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/discord-ml-eio-based-discord-library-with-voice-support/13370/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>anqou announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi. I'm writing a Discord library, Discord.ml, in OCaml for my personal project. As of now, it supports voice
functionality as well as text one, and you can write, for example, a music bot with this library.

https://github.com/ushitora-anqou/discordml

I used Eio to write this library and wrote a simple Erlang-like actor model implementation
([actaa](https://github.com/ushitora-anqou/actaa)). Also, I used Cohttp-eio (beta1) with ocaml-websocket to
communicate with the Discord's server (gateway).

I hope someone may be interested in this library. Any feedback would be appreciated!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Release of Fmlib 0.5.7</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-release-of-fmlib-0-5-7/13373/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Helmut announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi all,

I am happy to annouce the release 0.5.7 of ~Fmlib~.

This release makes some minor improvements for combinator parsing with separate lexer and parser. The position
information contains now character and byte offsets and offers position range information on syntax errors.

For more information on combinator parsing with separate lexer and parser please read
https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_parse/parse_lex.html.

- General information about fmlib: https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/index.html
- Combinator parsing with fmlib: https://hbr.github.io/fmlib/odoc/fmlib_parse/index.html
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Survey on the new "Getting Started" Documentation on OCaml.org</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/survey-on-the-new-getting-started-documentation-on-ocaml-org/13380/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sabine Schmaltz announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello everyone,

we've prepared a survey to capture some anonymous feedback on the new documentation in the ["Getting Started"
section on OCaml.org](https://ocaml.org/docs/get-started).

I'd be stoked if you could help us by reviewing the new pages and completing the survey, no matter if you're a
newcomer to OCaml or not.

We're conducting this survey to understand if and what we need to change going forward, so that, in the end, we have
documentation that works for newcomers with varying backgrounds on OCaml.org. We're doing this in a non-public
survey, so that everyone can speak their mind freely without being judged. A summary of points brought up will be
posted at latest by Nov 30 as a response to this post.

If you're interested in contributing to the documentation, or having a call with us, there's a question at the very
end of the survey where you can leave your Email so we can reach out to you.

Thanks for participating! Let's make the OCaml documentation awesome! :fire:

https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeP8JUaHEoJYnFBV25ziYBSDezeXzbFrkUmi1cCvkimv3bUAw/viewform?usp=sf_link
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[https://ocaml.org/blog/][the ocaml.org blog]].

- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-11-01-webassembly-support-for-ocaml-introducing-wasm-of-ocaml][WebAssembly Support for OCaml: Introducing Wasm_of_Ocaml]]
- [[https://frama-c.com/fc-versions/nickel.html][Beta release of Frama-C 28.0~beta (Nickel)]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-10-25-tutorial-building-a-browser-extension-with-irmin][Tutorial: Building a Browser Extension With Irmin]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-10-18-off-to-the-races-using-threadsanitizer-in-ocaml][Off to the Races: Using ThreadSanitizer in OCaml]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-10-10-prioritising-mental-health-at-tarides][Prioritising Mental Health at Tarides]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-10-04-porting-obuilder-to-freebsd][Porting OBuilder to FreeBSD]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-09-27-tutorial-how-to-port-lwt-applications-to-eio][Tutorial: How to Port Lwt Applications to Eio]]
- [[http://gallium.inria.fr/blog/florian-cw-2023-09-26][Florian compiler weekly, 26 September 2023]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-09-20-a-year-of-spaceos-showing-the-world-the-benefits-of-ocaml][A Year of SpaceOS: Showing the World the Benefits of OCaml]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-09-15-our-experience-at-tarides-projects-from-our-internships-in-2023][Our Experience at Tarides: Projects From Our Internships in 2023]]
- [[https://tech.ahrefs.com/beyond-typescript-differences-between-typed-languages-f3e14253?source=rss----303662d88bae--ocaml][Beyond TypeScript: Differences Between Typed Languages]]
- [[https://blog.janestreet.com/what-the-interns-have-wrought-2023/][What the interns have wrought, 2023 edition]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-09-08-the-state-of-the-art-in-functional-programming-tarides-at-icfp-2023][The State of the Art in Functional Programming: Tarides at ICFP 2023]]
- [[https://frama-c.com/fc-plugins/frama-clang.html][Release of Frama-Clang 0.0.14]]
- [[https://blog.janestreet.com/oxidizing-ocaml-parallelism/][Oxidizing OCaml: Data Race Freedom]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
