<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2023.07.25</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2023.07.18</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2023.08.01</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>July 18 to 25, 2023</cwn_date_text>
    <cwn_extra_head></cwn_extra_head>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ppxlib dev meetings</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ppxlib-dev-meetings/12441/5</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Sonja Heinze announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are the meeting notes of the July meeting: https://github.com/ocaml-ppx/ppxlib/wiki/Dev-meeting-18-07-2023

As a heads-up: There won't be a meeting in August, so the next one will be in September. Have a nice
summer/winter/other season everyone! :)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocamls spotted in the wild</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocamls-spotted-in-the-wild/12641/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Thorsten Ohl announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here's a paper on algorithms for theoretical particle physics referring to ocaml published today:

[Functional directed acyclical graphs for scattering amplitudes in perturbation
theory](https://link.springer.com/article/10.1140/epjc/s10052-023-11787-2)
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>gasche then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It looks like this paper builds on previous work implementing a tool called Omega in OCaml, which has been around
since 2001:

  O'Mega: An Optimizing Matrix Element Generator\\
  Mauro Moretti, Thorsten Ohl, Jürgen Reuter, 2001\\
  https://arxiv.org/abs/hep-ph/0102195
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>DkML 2.0.0 Preview Release</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-dkml-2-0-0-preview-release/12642/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>jbeckford announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
There are several major changes in version 2.0.0 of DkML, a OCaml distribution that uses Visual Studio on Windows.
Full DkML 2.0.0 Release Notes are available, and the installer is
https://gitlab.com/diskuv-ocaml/distributions/dkml/-/releases/2.0.0/downloads/setup64u.exe.

Consider 2.0.0 a preview release. If you are risk-averse you may want to wait for 2.0.1.

DkML 2.0.0 Release Notes: https://gitlab.com/diskuv-ocaml/distributions/dkml/-/releases#2.0.0

*Breaking change*: The global environment (where you can run ~dune~, ~utop~, ~ocamlopt~ and a few other critical
OCaml executables without having to install your own opam switch) has changed significantly. [DkML 2.0.0 Release
Notes] describes those changes in detail.

Why do this breaking change?

1. 2.0.0+ installations are faster because the global executables do not have   to be compiled.
2. It gets the DkML distribution very close to having a lite "bytecode only"   installer that does not need to install (heavy!) Visual Studio, MSYS2 and   Git. /This upcoming lite installer could be a good fit for educational settings, so feedback from educators is appreciated./

Major non-breaking changes:

- The deprecated ~fdopen~ repository is no longer used. Previously DkML  installed a smaller and smaller portion of the ~fdopen~ repository with each  subsequent version. Now DkML 2.x.x relies only on the central opam repository and the DkML opam repository.
- Dune upgraded to 3.8.3. Among other things, the installer no longer installs  a C# file watcher proxy for ~dune build -w~; instead Dune uses its own  native Windows file watcher.
- The set of pinned packages during a ~dkml init~ local switch has gone down  from approximately 4000 to 200. Rather than pinning each package in the  opam universe to a heuristically-determined version, we pin only packages that we successfully build on Windows.
- The following packages are accessible by just typing ~utop~ without installing a switch:
  * [~refl~](https://github.com/thierry-martinez/refl#readme) reflection package
  * [~graphics~](https://github.com/ocaml/graphics#readme) package
  * [~base~](https://github.com/janestreet/base#readme) package

Bug fixes:

- The installer can now restart after a failed installation, without having  to use the uninstaller.
- Allow setup to succeed on Windows filesystems that do not support the setting  of file attributes
- FlexDLL object files ~flexdll_initer_msvc64.obj~ and ~flexdll_msvc64.obj~ (or  32-bit variant on 32-bit installs) are installed alongside ~flexlink.exe~ so  flexlink can be used by itself without setting ~FLEXDIR~ environment variable.

Changed packages:

- Many packages are upgraded. Here is a sampling of those upgrades:
  | Package             | From                     | To                               |
  |---------------------|--------------------------| ---------------------------------|
  | dune                | 3.6.2                    | 3.8.3                            |
  | utop                | 2.10.0                   | 2.13.1                           |
  | ptime               | 0.8.6-msvcsupport        | 1.1.0                            |
  | flexdll             | 0.42                     | 0.43                             |
  | base                | v0.15.1                  | v0.16.1                          |
  | yojson              | 2.0.2                    | 2.1.0                            |
  | stdcompat           |                          | 19+optautoconf                   |
  | metapp              |                          | 0.4.4+win                        |
  | ocamlformat         | 0.24.1                   | 0.25.1                           |
  | lsp                 | 1.12.2                   | 1.16.2                           |
  | cmdliner            | 1.1.1                    | 1.2.0                            |
  | alcotest            | 1.6.0                    | 1.7.0                            |
  | ocamlfind           | 1.9.1                    | 1.9.5                            |
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>later on, jbeckford added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
*** DkML 2.0.1

Version 2.0.1 is available with an installer and release notes at

https://gitlab.com/diskuv-ocaml/distributions/dkml/-/releases/2.0.1

Its main new feature is that the OCaml package ~sqlite3~ is available from the global environment. Examples of
~sqlite3~ are in the [Quick Start](https://gitlab.com/diskuv-ocaml/distributions/dkml#quick-start).

If you installed 2.0.0 you should upgrade to 2.0.1 for the bug fixes.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Next priority for OCaml?</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/next-priority-for-ocaml/12561/62</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Deep in this thread, gasche said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I would be hard pressed to mention /one/ priority for OCaml, because I think that many things are important -- and
important in different ways for different people. I thought that I could give some information on what support I
have been involved in, either as a compiler maintainer or as a member of the [OCaml Software
Foundation](https://ocaml-sf.org/), on some of the topics that have been mentioned here.

- Modular implicits: we've been trying to find people we could fund to make progress on this, but it is difficult -- it requires a lot of type-system expertise, and time. We are funding internships with @yallop in Cambridge to experiment with the system, and I am thinking of getting my hands dirty during the next school year with some module-side implementation work -- possibly diving into the PRs of Matthew Ryan.
- Type system for effects: I have decided to setup an informal working group for people interested in working on this (mostly academics, also Jane Street) to exchange information, and in particular to decide a common set of evaluation criteria -- with compatibility with existing non-effect-using OCaml code as a top priority. I hope to announce something more structured next September, with the aim of getting a clearer idea of potential design proposals by the end of the academic years.
- Debuggers: the OCaml Foundation funded ocamlearlybird's author in 2020-2021, hackwaly, before they stopped to work full-time for a startup. (https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocamlearlybird-now-an-ocaml-software-foundation-supported-project/6834 , https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocamlearlybird-1-0-0-beta1/7180 , etc. ) I learned a week ago that @sim642 is interested in continuing maintenance of the project, and we are looking at funding his work.
  (ocamlearlybird is a bytecode debugger, similar to the venerable ~ocamldebug~ -- it is a client for the same debugger protocol. Separately we would ideally have good debugging support with the native compiler. That aspect of the debugging story has been worked on by Mark Shinwell in the past, but there is a disagreement among compiler maintainers about what is the right technical approach to support DWARF information in the compiler -- it is a complex format that is not necessarily a good match for OCaml, and adding it to the compiler backend is fairly invasive.)
- A priority that people don't know about, but in my mind comes before "typed effects", is to refactor and cleanup the implementation of the OCaml type checker, which has historically been a place of technical debt in the compiler. There has been a fair amount of work on this in the last year, driven by Jacques Garrigue as his group at Nagoya ( in particular Takafumi Saikawa ), with Florian Angeletti and myself on the reviewer side, and in the last few months some very welcome help from the Jane Street group working on language features (in particular Richard Eisenberg, Chris Casinghino, Nick Roberts) who have been lending a hand on refactoring and refactoring-reviewing work.
  More generally, I have been worried this year about maintenance workforce for the OCaml compiler codebase (https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/maintenance-bottlenecks-in-the-compiler-distribution/11045 ). I think that solving this issue is also a priority, at the level of the compiler distribution. We have made some progress, with notably maintenance contributions from OCamlPro and Jane Street, but I think that the situation still requires careful monitoring.
- Relocatability: I agree with @smorimoto that this is important. I would want all OCaml packages to be relocatable, notably as the right first step to enable caching or even binary distribution of OCaml package build artifacts. There has been work in this direction from David Allsopp in the last few years, which I understand gets closer every year to being in a state that could be submitted as upstream PRs. My strategy so far is to wait for this to make progress.
- Tooling, things that directly come to mind are:
  + development-environment tools whose recommended workflow is to have separate/isolated development environment(s) for each project. The ~opam~ client allows this with local switches, but I think the UI could be streamlined a bit to make this the easy default. (For example, not everyone knows how to build a local switch with only the dependencies of the project installed, to start hacking on it.) Ideally we would have caching of package builds across those development environments, and maybe even some distributed caching of build artifacts (assuming relocatability).
  + a "code upgrade" tool to which I can specify program transformations (for example: "rewrite ~SomeLib.somefun $bar $baz~ into ~SomeLib.somefun $bar (Somelib.convert $baz)~", and it applies it to my source code in a diff-friendly way.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Explorations on Package Management in Dune</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/explorations-on-package-management-in-dune/12101/25</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Deep in this thread, Thomas Gazagnaire said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
My view on this. When people talk about Opam, this covers different aspects.

- the opam files and files repositories. The main repository is (for us OCamlers) ~ocaml/opam-repository~, but the [Coq community also has one](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/wiki/Dev-Meeting-2020.11.06-(opam-and-coq-repos)), and many companies use their private repository. We do not want to break this workflow. The Dune package management proposals aim to stay fully compatible with this workflow and work with any opam packages (using ~dune~ or not). There's also exciting ongoing work for [package signing](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/wiki/Dev-Meeting-2021.06.11-(Conex)) that we do want to see land at one point. We have also built and are operating an extensive CI infrastructure around these repositories -- for instance, [ocaml-repo-ci](https://github.com/ocurrent/opam-repo-ci) is building 100,000 jobs daily on all the Tier1 supported platforms for OCaml. We do not want to rebuild this once more time!
- the opam client(s). The main one is the ~opam~ CLI, but many more tools use the opam files metadata. There are a [few tentatives](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/wiki/Dev-Meeting-2020.10.23-(opam2nix)) of generating ~nix~ derivations for those files. There's also [esy](https://github.com/ocaml/opam/wiki/Dev-Meeting-2020.12.04-(esy-drom)) and the package managers that try to close the gap between the OCaml and JavaScript ecosystems. The client is built around a library (~opam-lib~), but this has never been designed properly. When I wrote opam initially, it was only focused on the CLI. Later with @AltGr, we tried to split it a bit more cleanly, but the API is still painful to use (for instance, every function that needs to load the filesystem needs a value that holds that state that would take dozens of arguments - then, as these functions perform file-system or network effects, you somehow need to keep these values synchronised with the new filesystem state -- that's painful and error prone). This API can somehow be split into various parts:
  1. Reading the opam repository state: parsing opam files, building a dependency graph (that's the part you mention @gasche)
  2. Resolving constraints: opam has a pluggable interface for constraint solving, and by default, it will use what solver is installed on your system (or some internal heuristics which used to be very naive but seems much better nowadays). Opam needs to serialise and parse solver requests, including solver errors that need to be somehow pretty printed to the user.
  3. If the solver can devise a building plan, parse it and prepare it by downloading (and caching) the build/package sources.
  4. run the build commands for all the packages and install them locally.

Nowadays, most package managers also have the option to snapshot the state of the build plan between 2. and 3.
That's for instance, what tools like ~opam-monorepo lock~ or ~opam lock~ are doing.
But when you do ~opam install --locked~, ~opam~ still calls the solver (to check that your lock file is consistent
and complete), so doing  3-2-3-4. And ~opam-monorepo pull~ does 3. and delegate 4. to ~dune build~ (so all your
dependencies need to use ~dune~ and be co-installable in a ~dune~ workspace).

So to come back to your question @gasche: The Dune package management experiment will be using ~opam-lib~ to do 1,
2 and 3 (whether it's the current ~opam-lib~ or an improved version that relies a bit less on filesystem state is
still in discussions - whatever the result is it will be upstreamed). And it will be using the ~dune~ scheduler to
do 4 (but still using the opam build instructions).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCamlFormat 0.26.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocamlformat-0-26-0/12649/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jules announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are happy to announce the release of OCamlFormat 0.26.0, the auto-formatter for OCaml code.

This release contains changes that might affect your code and overall projects. It could include impact to module
arguments, ~fun~ passed as a labelled argument, and indentation within parentheses.

The complete [list of changes is here](https://github.com/ocaml-ppx/ocamlformat/releases/tag/0.26.0). Items marked
with a ~*~ are likely to change your code.

The OCamlFormat dev team
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Tarides Office Hours: Benchmark Tooling</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-tarides-office-hours-benchmark-tooling/12655/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Shakthi Kannan announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The [current-bench](https://github.com/ocurrent/current-bench) infrastructure and pipeline are used for
benchmarking the OCaml compiler and ecosystem projects. It uses the
[OCurrent](https://github.com/ocurrent/ocurrent) pipeline to run predictable, I/O-bound benchmarks for the
respective OCaml projects.

We have successfully added benchmarks for Dune, Lockfree, odoc, Merlin, Eio, opam, etc., projects at
[https://autumn.ocamllabs.io](https://autumn.ocamllabs.io). We would now like to make our infrastructure available
to the larger community to increase adoption and continue our work on performance analysis, tooling, and
benchmarking.

You can follow the instructions in the current-bench
[README](https://github.com/ocurrent/current-bench/blob/main/README.md#enroll-your-repository) to create a
benchmark for your project and install the GitHub application to onboard your OCaml project to current-bench.

The Tarides Benchmark Tooling team is also making open office hours available for you to engage, ask questions, and
work with us on benchmarking OCaml projects. We will be available online, every Monday, between 1030 and 1130 CET
on Google Meet as mentioned below:

Tarides Office Hours: OCaml Benchmarking
Starting Monday, July 24, 2023 (1030 - 1130 CET) (1400 – 1500 IST)

Google Meet joining info:
Video call link: https://meet.google.com/rcu-wjpk-jyh
Or dial: ‪(US) +1 440-549-4808‬ PIN: ‪584 331 902‬#

More phone numbers: https://tel.meet/rcu-wjpk-jyh?pin=4479584706118

Please feel free to join our weekly Monday sessions, and we will be happy to interact with the community and
enhance our benchmarking efforts for OCaml!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>You Can Attend the New OCaml.org Community Meetings</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/you-can-attend-the-new-ocaml-org-community-meetings/12656/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sabine Schmaltz announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
the OCaml.org maintainers are now holding community meetings, on Mondays every two weeks on Zoom.

Here are some dates for the upcoming meetings [(scheduled on Google
Calendar)](https://calendar.google.com/calendar/u/0?cid=Y18wMmU0MWIyYWQwMDE2NWI0MDQ3ODlmYWQ3YzVkZjdlYTNhNGFlNjI3NDRjMTMzMDdlZTdmYjNmZDczODJmMWRkQGdyb3VwLmNhbGVuZGFyLmdvb2dsZS5jb20):

- 24 Jul 2023, Mon 18:00 – 19:00 CEST
- 7 Aug 2023, Mon 18:00 – 19:00 CEST
- 21 Aug 2023, Mon 18:00 – 19:00 CEST
- 4 Sept 2023, Mon 18:00 – 19:00 CEST

Topics may include:

- Proposals you want to champion
- Q&amp;A sessions about the project
- Guidance on contributing

But we're not limiting topics to just these. Many more topics relevant to OCaml.org and how to best make use of it
for the benefit of the OCaml community can also be discussed. If you'd like to add a topic/issue to the discussion
for a specific meeting, please contact Sabine on [OCaml Discuss](https://discuss.ocaml.org/u/sabine) or the
[OCaml.org Discord channel](https://discord.com/channels/436568060288172042/1126433906976112700), or [open an issue
on the ocaml/ocaml.org GitHub Repository](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/issues)

P.S.:
https://ocaml.org/news/invitation-to-contribute
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>euler, an arithmetic library for native integers</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-euler-an-arithmetic-library-for-native-integers/12482/10</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, glen announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks to @mseri, ~euler~ is now on opam! And in the meantime it has gained more functions, the most striking of
which being [~Primes.prime_seq : int -> int Seq.t~](https://gmevel.github.io/euler-lib/index.html/euler/Euler/Primes/index.html#val-prime_seq) (thank @cuihtlauac for pointing me to the
algorithm!) and [~Arith.smallest_root : int -> int * int~](https://gmevel.github.io/euler-lib/index.html/euler/Euler/Arith/index.html#val-smallest_root) (the latter in the next release, 3.0,
not on opam yet).

Also, since I still cannot edit the first post, this is a reminder that the project has moved to GitHub: *[repo](https://github.com/gmevel/euler-lib)*, *[doc](https://gmevel.github.io/euler-lib/index.html/euler/Euler/)*. The links in my first message won’t be updated.

#+begin_quote
I wonder if this is a useful addition to [Owl ](https://github.com/owlbarn/owl), the ocaml “fat” math library.
#+end_quote

Perhaps? I am not very familiar with Owl (ask Owl’s Benevolent Dictators For Life? ;-) ). Euler is an integer
arithmetic library whereas, as I understand it, Owl is mainly a floating-point math library for scientific
computing (linear algebra, differentiation, statistics and and such). I would guess that prime numbers and friends
are rather remote concerns for Owl users, but perhaps Owl is interested in expanding its domains? I did spot [a
small number of integer arithmetic functions in Owl](https://github.com/owlbarn/owl/blob/48434ea/src/owl/maths/owl_maths.mli#L587-L607), most of which are also found in Euler.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>DkML Install API 0.4.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-dkml-install-api-0-4-0/12665/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>jbeckford announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce that DkML Install API 0.4.0 is available on opam. This library is what I've been using to
create the DkML Windows distribution installer.

TLDR: To create your own installer for your own software, you define "components" which have dependencies on other
components. A component is an OCaml module you create with four essential functions: ~admin_install~ and
~admin_uninstall~ for escalated privileges, and ~user_install~ and ~user_uninstall~ for normal user privileges.
Each component almost always needs to access assets which can be defined in the ~install:[]~ section of an ~.opam~
file. The net effect is you can use opam and OCaml to define your own reproducible installer.

There is a walk-through at
[https://diskuv.github.io/dkml-install-api/doc/packages/Console.html](https://diskuv.github.io/dkml-install-api/doc/packages/Console.html)
and more general documentation at
[https://github.com/diskuv/dkml-install-api#readme](https://github.com/diskuv/dkml-install-api#readme)

The library works well for the DkML Windows distribution, although it is too complicated to recommend for casual
use today. Regardless, if someone has a burning desire to create their own installer, and that installer has
reasonably complex logic that needs to run on the end-user machine, then take a look at DkML Install API! /Expect
to see a steady but slow series of changes to the API until it hits 1.0.0./

Limitations: Today it can make an end-to-end installer for Windows. I haven't needed yet to create macOS and Linux
installers, although 95% of the pieces are present. If you are interested in creating the final packaging step for
those OS-es (ex. a ~.deb~ apt packager for Debian), feel free to contribute a PR!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Liquidsoap 2.2.0 is out! 🎉</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-liquidsoap-2-2-0-is-out/12667/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Romain Beauxis announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are delighted to announce the release of **Liquidsoap 2.2.0**! It is now available on [our release
page](https://github.com/savonet/liquidsoap/releases/tag/v2.2.0)
and should be available [via opam](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/liquidsoap) shortly!

Liquidsoap is a statically typed scripting general-purpose language with dedicated operators and backend for all
thing media, streaming, file generation, automation, HTTP backend and more.

This release comes almost 4 months after the last stable release from the ~2.1.x~ release cycle and 14 months (!)
after forking the ~2.2.x~ release branch! It includes some exciting changes in track muxing/demuxing, HLS, sound
processing and more.  See below for a detailed list!

*** ✨ New features

Here are the highlights:

**** 🎛️ Multitrack

This is by far the biggest change in this relase! This brings the ability to demux and remux tracks inside sources,
making it possible to:
- Encode video with multiple audio tracks
- Create audio-only and audio/video streams from the same content, for instance a regular audio stream and one with the studio's video.
- Drop or specify which metadata or track marks track should be used.
- Apply specific audio effect or encoding to different tracks

And much more! The full documentation is [here](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/multitrack.html). We plan on
expanding this support in the future in particular to allow track selection based on language, encoded content etc.

**** 🏷️ HLS metadata

At last! We now support metadata in HLS streams using a timed ID3 stream for ~mpegts~ container and plain ID3v2
tags for  ~adts~, ~mp3~, ~ac3~ and ~eac3~ formats. There is currently no support for metadata with ~mp4~
containers.

This feature is *enabled by default* so you might want to check if it impacts your listeners before pushing it
to production. It can be turned off by setting ~id3~ to false on your HLS streams.

Full documentation is [here](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/hls_output.html#metadata).

**** 🎨 Colored logs

Small change but not the least important! Logs are now colored by default when printed on the console. This finally
makes it possible to read logs with high level of details!

We are aware of the need for more developer tooling and quality of life improvements! In the next release cycle, we
hope to work on code formatting, highlighting and more!

**** 🕸️ New HTTP API

Interacting with your scripts is essential and, for this, web interfaces and APIs are really useful. In order to
make our HTTP server easier to use, we wrote a new web API that is very close to node express' API and should be
fairly easy to use! The documentation is
[here](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/harbor_http.html#nodeexpress-api)

These changes also included a revamping of our SSL support which is now modular and with a new TLS optional
support!

**** 🎚️ Native stereotool support

While commited to open-source through and through, we also do want to meet our users where they are. To this end,
it seems that a lof of them want to use the proprietary stereotool audio processing. Up until this version, the
only option was via the external command line encoder and this was not satisfactory.

With this release, it is now possible to use the shared library distributed by the author, which provides support
for  an new ~stereotool~ internal operator that is much easier to integrate. See the documentation
[here](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/stereotool.html).

**** 📟 Records enhancements

As part of the language changes requred for multitrack, we now support the following operations on records:

Record spread:
#+begin_example
let {foo, bar, ...rest} = someRecord

let otherRecord = { bla = "blo", ...someRecord }
#+end_example

Additionally, we now support optional record methods, for instance:

#+begin_example
def f(x) =
  if x?.foo == null() then
    print("x does not have method foo")
  else
    print("x has method foo")
  end
end
#+end_example

**** 🪢 Support for YAML parsing/rendering

Following the recent [JSON parsing](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/json.html) feature, we now support [YAML
parsing](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/yaml.html) in a very similar way as json.

**** 🔮 Memory optimization

While we are aware that memory consumption with this release may have increased a bit due to on-going changes, we
have done our best to introduce more ways to control it and understand its usage.

In particular, we now support the alternative [jemalloc]() memory allocator, enabled in all our release assets and
configurable via the internal settings.

We also introduced two new audio content formats, ~pcm_s16~ and ~pcm_f32~ that can be used to store audio
internally as, resp., 16-bit signed integers or 32-bit floating point numbers. Our default internal format being
OCaml's native 64-bit floating point numbers.

We also added a new ~track.audio.defer~ operator that can be used to buffer large amount of audio data without
impacting performances.

You can read more about memory utilization in liquidsoap [here](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/memory.html).

**** 🐪 Switch to ~dune~ and javascript runtime

While perhaps more exciting to developers, the project has now fully moved to the OCaml ~dune~ builder. This
provides an extra level of flexibility, In particular, we were able to extract the code that is specific to the
liquidsoap language, that is everything that pertains to parsing/evaluating/type checking without the streaming and
system specific operators and export it as an [online playground](https://www.liquidsoap.info/try/). We're not sure
yet what we'll do with it. It might be possible, for instance, to write a javascript backend to use liquidsoap
scripts  with the [Web media APIs](https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Media)!

*** 🕵️ Versioning and release assets

For a little over a year now, we have switched to _rolling release cycles_ with maintenance and bugfixes applying
only to the current release cycle. Regular releases are tagged ~vX.Y.Z~ (for instance ~v2.2.0~) on github and
docker while on-going releases are tagged ~rolling-release-vX.Y.Z~.

When an initial release, for instance ~2.2.0~, is being worked on, bugfixes and user issues were being addressed
for users using the ~2.1.x~ releases. While we would like to extend support, this is the best that we can do with
our limited resources!

At any given time, the ~rolling-release-vX.Y.Z~ denotes the released being worked on. For stable releases branches,
this would be for instance, ~rolling-release-v2.2.1~ after release ~v2.2.0~. For a yet-to-be released initial
version, this would be for instance ~rolling-release-v2.3.x~. We try our best to make those releases as bug-free as
possible. Using one of them to test your production script also guarantees the fastest response to bugs and issues!

For release assets, we try to maintain two packages for debian and ubuntu distributions, one with the latest LTS or
stable and one with a recent release. The new ~minimal~ assets are, as the name suggests, _minimal_ builds. They
contain a limited set of features and standard library operators. Minimal builds are intended for most production
run and should limit the risk for issues such as segfault and etc. If your script can run with it, we recommend it
over the fully featured builds.

For each release asset, you can consult the associated ~.config~ file to see which features are enabled.

Docker release images are located at: ~savonet/liquidsoap:v2.2.0~. The release tag may be updated if needed. You
can use git sha-based images to pick a fixed build, e.g. ~savonet/liquidsoap:&lt;sha&gt;~

Lastly, we may update the list of release assets on the github release page. If you are looking for permanent
release asset links make sure to checkout
[savonet/liquidsoap-release-assets](https://github.com/savonet/liquidsoap-release-assets).

*** 🧮 Migration guide

We listed most of the migration issues you might run into on [this
page](https://www.liquidsoap.info/doc-2.2.0/migrating.html). The detailed changelog below may also help.

As a reminder, we strongly recommend to test your script in a stagging environment, even between minor releases, to
make sure that everything is working correctly before pushing a new liquidsoap version to production!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>kcas and kcas_data 0.6.1: STM and compositional lock-dree data structures</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-kcas-and-kcas-data-0-6-1-stm-and-compositional-lock-dree-data-structures/12674/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Vesa Karvonen announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm happy to announce that version 0.6.1 of ~kcas~ and ~kcas_data~ has been released on opam.

See the [Kcas](https://github.com/ocaml-multicore/kcas/#readme) project for more details, but briefly
[*kcas*](https://ocaml-multicore.github.io/kcas/doc/kcas/Kcas/index.html) provides a software transactional
memory (STM) implementation and
[*kcas_data*](https://ocaml-multicore.github.io/kcas/doc/kcas_data/Kcas_data/index.html) provides compositional
lock-free data structures implemented using Kcas.  Together these libraries allow one to implement safe concurrent
abstractions compositionally.

Aside from internal improvements, notable features added since the [previously announced
0.3.0](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-kcas-and-kcas-data-0-3-0-software-transactional-memory/12085)
version include:

- Doubly linked list [~Dllist~](https://ocaml-multicore.github.io/kcas/doc/kcas_data/Kcas_data/Dllist/index.html), see [example](https://github.com/ocaml-multicore/kcas#a-transactional-lru-cache).
- Synchronizing variable [~MVar~](https://ocaml-multicore.github.io/kcas/doc/kcas_data/Kcas_data/Mvar/index.html), see [example](https://github.com/ocaml-multicore/kcas#the-dining-philosophers-problem).
- [Nested conditional transactions](https://ocaml-multicore.github.io/kcas/doc/kcas/Kcas/Xt/index.html#nested-transactions), see [example](https://github.com/ocaml-multicore/kcas#log-updates-optimistically).
- Timeouts, see [example](https://github.com/ocaml-multicore/kcas#timeouts).
- Support for OCaml 4.14, allowing Kcas to be used to implement systhread and parallelism safe code and help projects requiring OCaml 4 support on their way to OCaml 5.

Stay tuned for more news on Kcas!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ctypes 0.21.1, now with dune support</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ctypes-0-21-1-now-with-dune-support/12675/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>yallop announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I’m happy to announce a new release of [ctypes](https://github.com/yallop/ocaml-ctypes/), 0.21.1, available for
installation via OPAM.

ctypes is a library for binding to C libraries using pure OCaml, with the primary aim of make writing C extensions
as straightforward as possible.

The core of ctypes is a set of combinators for describing the structure of C types -- numeric types, arrays,
pointers, structs, unions and functions. You can use these combinators to describe the types of the functions that
you want to call, then bind directly to those functions -- all without writing any C!

The major change in this release is a switch to the dune build system, contributed by Anil Madhavapeddy (@avsm) and
Etienne Millon (@emillon).  The benefits of this change for users of ctypes are described in [the pull request
implementing the change](https://github.com/yallop/ocaml-ctypes/pull/588); in summary:

#+begin_quote
With a port to ~dune~, the ctypes library can be embedded in larger dune projects simply by including it in the
directory tree of the bigger project.
#+end_quote

The [release notes](https://github.com/yallop/ocaml-ctypes/blob/0.21.1/CHANGES.md) have further details of the
changes in this release and recent point releases.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Announcing the ocaml-wasm organisation</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/announcing-the-ocaml-wasm-organisation/12676/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>KC Sivaramakrishnan announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We are happy to announce the creation of the [ocaml-wasm](https://github.com/ocaml-wasm) Github organisation which
will work towards [WebAssembly](https://webassembly.org/) (Wasm) support for OCaml. The goal of the organisation is
to enable users to build high-performance and secure applications for the Wasm platform using the OCaml programming
language and the platform tools.

Wasm is a binary instruction format, designed as a portable compilation target for programming languages, enabling
deployment on the Web for client and server applications. It provides a sandboxed execution environment, which also
makes it attractive for both blockchains and Cloud deployment. For example, Fastly's [Compute@Edge
platform](https://docs.fastly.com/products/compute-at-edge) is based on WebAssembly.

*** Compilers

The ocaml-wasm organisation brings together the ongoing efforts at compiling OCaml to Wasm.

**** wasocaml

[OCamlPro](https://ocamlpro.com/) has been developing [wasocaml](https://github.com/ocaml-wasm/wasocaml), [an
experimental compiler backend](https://ocamlpro.com/blog/2022_12_14_wasm_and_ocaml/) for OCaml that targets Wasm
starting from the flambda intermediate representation of the OCaml compiler. OCamlPro engineers have also been
contributing to the Wasm GC working group to ensure that the GC and other extensions in Wasm are amenable to
targeting OCaml.

**** wasm_of_ocaml

Alongside this effort, [Tarides](https://tarides.com/) has been working on implementing
[wasm_of_ocaml](https://github.com/ocaml-wasm/wasm_of_ocaml), a toolchain to compile OCaml to WebAssembly based on
the battle-tested [js_of_ocaml](https://github.com/ocsigen/js_of_ocaml) compiler. Both js_of_ocaml and
wasm_of_ocaml use OCaml bytecode as the input and emit JavaScript and Wasm respectively.

It is notable that these efforts started off jointly a few years ago with [an
exploration](https://github.com/sabine/ocaml-to-wasm-overview/tree/master) aimed at adding a Wasm backend to OCaml.
At that time, it was clear that Wasm did not have enough features to support OCaml efficiently. With the
implementation of several key Wasm extensions in browser engines, the time is right for this effort.

There exist other approaches to running OCaml programs using Wasm runtimes, where the speed of generated code is
less of a concern. For example, a relatively straightforward approach is to compile the OCaml bytecode interpreter
to Wasm and interpret the bytecode programs. [ocamlrun-wasm](https://github.com/sebmarkbage/ocamlrun-wasm) and
[wasicaml](https://github.com/remixlabs/wasicaml) are ports of the OCaml bytecode interpreter to Wasm. Wasicaml
furthermore has a compiler mode somewhat similar to wasm_of_ocaml (but simpler) that parses a bytecode executable
and translates it into Wasm.

**** Evolving Wasm

Wasm is an evolving standard. Wasm 1.0 focuses on low-level support for compiling low-level languages such as C and
C++. There are several extensions under development which aim to provide support for targeting high-level languages
including [garbage collection](https://github.com/WebAssembly/gc), [tail
calls](https://v8.dev/blog/wasm-tail-call), [stack switching](https://github.com/WebAssembly/stack-switching) and
[threads](https://github.com/WebAssembly/threads). In particular, the Wasm development process is completely open
and anyone can participate in the evolution of Wasm.

The OCamlPro engineers [contributed](https://ocamlpro.com/blog/2022_12_14_wasm_and_ocaml/) to the Wasm GC extension
with the help of their experimental flambda to Wasm compiler. Both OCamlPro and Tarides engineers are actively
involved with the Wasm development process on multiple fronts. Having more than one approach to compile OCaml to
Wasm allows us to build comprehensive evidence and make informed arguments to influence the design of Wasm
extensions. In addition, a major implementation effort is the runtime system support for Wasm-compiled OCaml code,
which will be shared between the different OCaml to Wasm compilers.

*** OCaml-Wasm monthly update

We will post a summary of the work done in the [ocaml-wasm](https://github.com/ocaml-wasm) org on [OCaml
discuss](https://discuss.ocaml.org/).

/Happy hacking!/
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Feedback Needed: New "Arrays" Tutorial on OCaml.org</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/feedback-needed-new-arrays-tutorial-on-ocaml-org/12683/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sabine Schmaltz announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hey everyone,

there's a new tutorial on "Arrays" at

https://staging.ocaml.org/docs/arrays

Looking for constructive feedback.

Is there any information missing or questions that you would need answered in order for this tutorial to be useful?
Anything you would change?
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
