<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2023.12.12</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2023.12.05</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2023.12.19</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>December 05 to 12, 2023</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ecosystem Wishlist Survey</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ecosystem-wishlist-survey/13578/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Sabine Schmaltz announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hey OCaml folks,

I am running a little OCaml Ecosystem Wishlist survey where you can put in really specific wishes for

- new packages,
- package improvements,
- compiler / tooling / language changes

I'm really curious what you all need and I think this will be helpful to better understand the current state of the
ecosystem.

The survey will stay open at least into January, probably much longer.

Put those wishes in! 🎄🐫🔥🔥

https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdVGjO3g9qS31rXy3SE-PxcG6Aki652jiqxzfM2lb7kVh5UHg/viewform?usp=sf_link
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OUPS meetup december 2023</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/oups-meetup-december-2023/13580/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>zapashcanon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
The next OUPS meetup will take place on *Thursday, 14th of December* 2023. It will start at *7pm* at the *4
place Jussieu* in Paris.

:warning: :trumpet: It will be in the in the *Esclangon building* (amphi TBA). :trumpet: :warning:

Please, *[register on meetup ](https://www.meetup.com/fr-FR/ocaml-paris/events/297791037)* as soon as possible to
let us know how many pizza we should order.

For more details, you may check the [OUPS’ website ](https://oups.frama.io).

This month will feature the following talks :

*Miou, un simple scheduler pour OCaml 5 -- Romain Calascibetta (@dinosaure)*

Miou est un scheduler pour OCaml 5 utilisant les effets nouvellement introduit. Il se concentre sur la
disponibilité d'une application au travers d'une politique de gestion des tâches bien décrite. Cette présentation
introduira les effets avec OCaml 5 ainsi qu'une rétrospective de son API. Il s'agira ensuite de présenter les
spécifités de Miou par rapport aux autres schedulers. Enfin, il y aura la présentation d'un client/serveur HTTP
développé selon le design de Miou. La présentation permettra de faire un état des lieux du scheduling en OCaml, des
raisons de la multiplicité des solutions ainsi que des objectifs concrets de Miou (implémentation de services,
disponibilités des applications, unikernels).

*Towards a solution to the expression problem for compilers: strongly typed nano-passes -- Boris Yakobowski*

We present a new solution to the problem of (strongly) typing compiler passes when the source and destination
language share multiple constructors. We are interested in approaches that limit the amount of boilerplate that
needs to be (re)written for each language, while still maintaining a very strict typing discipline. Our solution
uses well-known tools, but combine them in a novel way:

- the idea of nanopasses, in which each pass encodes a very limited transformation
- the use of ppx syntax extensions to express only the differences between a language and the next
- the traversal of the AST using top-down and bottom-up recursion schemes
- OCaml polymorphic variants, which are instrumental to precisely type our (non-recursive) transformation functions.

We present our implementation of this approach in the context of the Ada frontend for the Infer analyzer, which as
of today contains 28 passes. We will also discuss the various pitfalls we have encountered along the way, as well
as possible improvements (in particular deforesting the combination of multiple passes).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Js_of_ocaml 5.2</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-js-of-ocaml-5-2/13581/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hhugo announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I’m pleased to announce the release of js_of_ocaml 5.2. It should soon be able available in opam.

Js_of_ocaml is a compiler from OCaml bytecode to JavaScript. It makes it
possible to run pure OCaml programs in JavaScript environment like browsers and
Node.js.

Most significant changes:
- Improve support for modern javascript
- New global dead code elimination pass. Jsoo can now drop unused code inside functors. See the [pull request](https://github.com/ocsigen/js_of_ocaml/pull/1503) for more details
- Change strategy used for control flow compilation. It was adapted from wasm_of_ocaml and based on the following paper https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3547621.

See the [Changelog ](https://github.com/ocsigen/js_of_ocaml/blob/master/CHANGES.md) for other changes.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>containers 3.13</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-containers-3-13/13582/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Simon Cruanes announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello, I just released [containers 3.13](https://github.com/c-cube/ocaml-containers/releases/tag/v3.13) on opam.

This release is somewhat more breaking than usual:
- OCaml 4.08 is now the minimum OCaml version.
- ~CCShims_~ (which was used to provide a shim for ~Stdlib~ pre-4.08) is removed
- ~containers-thread~, which was deprecated, is no more. The recommended alternative is [Moonpool](https://github.com/c-cube/moonpool/).

On OCaml 5.1 and above, tail-rec-mod-cons is used to simplify and accelerate some functions in ~CCList~.

Happy hacking!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Melange 2.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-melange-2-0/13073/3</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Antonio Nuno Monteiro announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Melange 2.2 is now out with support for OCaml 5.1.1.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml 5.1.1 released</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-5-1-1-released/13592/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>octachron announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
In the last three months after the release of OCaml 5.1.0, three significant regressions have been discovered in
OCaml 5.1.0. Those regressions concern the packaging of executables, the typechecking of OCaml programs, and the
performance of numerical codes.

Since those regressions affect many users and could have lasting effects, we have published a patch release, OCaml
5.1.1, fixing those issues.

As a major exception to our policy for patch releases, OCaml 5.1.1 will contain one breaking change in the standard
library: the ~Compression~ flag has been removed from the ~Marshal~ module.
This drastic measure has been taken because supporting zstd compression in the standard library made zstd a
dependency of all OCaml executables. Since the compiler should not propagate its dependencies on end-users, the
support for compressed marshalling has been moved to a compiler internal library in 5.1.1.

Accounting for the still experimental nature of the multicore runtime, this patch release 5.1.1 also contains safe
fixes for subtle concurrency bugs in the OCaml runtime.

In brief, if you were using OCaml 5.1.0, I strongly recommend that you switch to 5.1.1 .

The full list of changes is available below for more details.

*** Installation Instructions

The base compiler can be installed as an opam switch with the following commands:

#+begin_example
opam update
opam switch create 5.1.1
#+end_example

The source code for the release is also directly available on:

- [GitHub](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/archive/5.1.1.tar.gz)
- [Inria archive](https://caml.inria.fr/pub/distrib/ocaml-5.1/ocaml-5.1.1.tar.gz)

*** Changes in OCaml 5.1.1 (8 December 2023)

**** Standard Library

- (*breaking change*) [#12562](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12562), [#12734](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12734), [#12783](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12783): Remove the ~Marshal.Compression~ flag to the ~Marshal.to_*~ functions introduced in 5.1 by [#12006](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12006), as it cannot be implemented without risking to link -lzstd with all ocamlopt-generated executables.  The compilers are still able to use ZSTD compression for compilation artefacts. (Xavier Leroy and David Allsopp, report by Kate Deplaix, review by Nicolás Ojeda Bär, Kate Deplaix, and Damien Doligez).

**** Bug Fixes
  - [#12623](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12623), fix the computation of variance composition
    (Florian Angeletti, report by Vesa Karvonen, review by Gabriel Scherer)
  - [#12581](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12581), [#12609](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12609): Fix error on uses of packed modules outside their pack
    to correctly handle nested packs
    (Vincent Laviron, report by Javier Chávarri, review by Pierre Chambart)
  - [#12645](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12645), [#12649](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12649) fix error messages for cyclic type definitions in presence of
    the ~-short-paths~ flag.
    (Florian Angeletti, report by Vesa Karvonen, review by Gabriel Scherer)
  - [#12757](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12757): Fix ocamlnat (native toplevel) by registering frametables correctly
    (Stephen Dolan, Nick Barnes and Mark Shinwell,
     review by Vincent Laviron and Sébastien Hinderer)
  - [#12791](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12791): ~extern~ is applied to definitions of ~caml_builtin_cprim~
    and ~caml_names_of_builtin_cprim~ when linking bytecode '-custom'
    executables with a C++ linker.
    (Shayne Fletcher, review by Antonin Décimo and Xavier Leroy)

**** GC Performance Regression Fixes
  - [#12318](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12318): GC: simplify the meaning of custom_minor_max_size: blocks with
    out-of-heap memory above this limit are now allocated directly in
    the major heap.
    (Damien Doligez, report by Stephen Dolan, review by Gabriel Scherer)
  - [#12439](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12439): Finalize and collect dead custom blocks during minor collection
    (Damien Doligez, review by Xavier Leroy, Gabriel Scherer and KC
    Sivaramakrishnan)
  - [#12590](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12590), [#12595](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12595): Move ~caml_collect_gc_stats_sample~ in
    ~caml_empty_minor_heap_promote~ before barrier arrival.
    (B. Szilvasy, review by Gabriel Scherer)
  - [#12491](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12491), [#12493](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12493), [#12500](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12500), [#12754](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12754): Do not change GC pace when creating sub-arrays of bigarrays (Xavier Leroy, report by Ido Yariv, analysis by Gabriel Scherer, review by Gabriel Scherer and Fabrice Buoro)

**** Runtime Bug Fixes
  - [#11800](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/11800), [#12707](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12707): fix an assertion race condition in ~install_backup_thread~
    (Jan Midtgaard, review by Gabriel Scherer)
  - [#12486](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12486), [#12535](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12535): Fix delivery of unhandled effect exceptions on amd64 with
    --enable-frame-pointers
    (Miod Vallat, report by Jan Midtgaard, review by Gabriel Scherer)
  - [#12712](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12712), [#12742](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12742): fix an assertion boundary case in ~caml_reset_young_limit~
    (Jan Midtgaard, review by Guillaume Munch-Maccagnoni)
  - [#12713](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12713), [#12715](https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/issues/12715): disable common subexpression elimination for atomic loads
    (Gabriel Scherer and Vincent Laviron,
     review by Vincent Laviron, KC Sivaramakrishnan and Xavier Leroy,
     report by Vesa Karvonen and Carine Morel)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>DkML 2.1.0 - Major changes</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-dkml-2-1-0-major-changes/13593/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>jbeckford announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce a major overhaul of DkML in version 2.1.0.

Some of the major changes include:
- ~winget install dkml~ is the recommended way to install.
- Installation is now in stages. The first stage (~winget install dkml~) takes 5 minutes and lets the end-user do ~utop~, ~ocamlc~ and ~ocamlrun~ (sufficient for learning). However, any command that need Visual Studio (ex. ~opam~, ~dkml~) will first:
  - guide you if you need Git and/or Visual Studio (~winget~ does not support auto-installing dependencies like other /sane/ package managers), and then
  - install the OCaml system compiler, the opam root and a playground global switch automatically on first run
- Alpha support for macOS/Silicon and most modern distros of GNU/Linux
- Has an accompanying video describing how to install and use DkML on Windows targeted to both learners and professionals. Includes Visual Studio Code and LSP:
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Call for Participation: BOB 2024 (Berlin, March 15)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/call-for-participation-bob-2024-berlin-march-15/13609/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Michael Sperber announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
More info at https://bobkonf.de/2024/!

#+begin_example
=========================================================================
			       BOB 2024
			      Conference
	     “What happens if we simply use what’s best?”
		       March 15, 2024, Berlin
		       https://bobkonf.de/2024/

	    Program: https://bobkonf.de/2024/program.html
	  Registration: https://bobkonf.de/2024/registration.html
=========================================================================

BOB conference is a place for developers, architects, and decision-makers
to explore technologies beyond the mainstream in software development
and to find the best tools available to software developers today. Our
goal is for all participants of BOB to return home with new insights
that enable them to improve their own software development
experience.

The program features 14 talks and 8 tutorials on current topics:

https://bobkonf.de/2024/program.html

Talk subjects includes functional programming, property-based testing,
service API design, programming for spacecraft, accessibility,
hypermedia, business processes, software analytics, event-based
communication and zero-knowledge proofs.

BOB will feature tutorials on F#, Haskell, Lean, SwiftUI, Copilot, the
K Framework, functional domain modelling, and Liberating Structures.

Andreas Rossberg will give the keynote talk.

Registration is open - online tickets are all under 200€, and many
discount options are available, as are grants for members of groups
underrepresented in tech:

https://bobkonf.de/2024/registration.html
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ocaml-protoc 3.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocaml-protoc-3-0/13611/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Simon Cruanes announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Dear camlidae,

I'm happy to announce the release of [ocaml-protoc
3.0](https://github.com/mransan/ocaml-protoc/releases/tag/v3.0.0) (alongside the multiple runtime libraries:
~pbrt~, ~pbrt_yojson~, and the new ~pbrt_services~). This is a majorly breaking release, I'm sorry for that (I do,
however, believe it necessary) and recommend every user of ocaml-protoc add an upper bound ~&lt; 3.0~ to their current
project and migrate when they have time.

First, a summary. ~ocaml-protoc~ is a self-contained compiler that turns [protobuf](https://protobuf.dev/) IDL
files (~.proto~ files) into OCaml types, pretty-printers, and (de)serialization functions. The runtime library
~pbrt~ ("protobuf runtime") contains support code for printers and binary (de)serialization; ~pbrt_yojson~ contains
support code for JSON (de)serialization by way of ~yojson~.

So what changed with ocaml-protoc 3.0? Many things.

For a start, from one ~.proto~ file we now generate one pair of ~.ml~ and ~.mli~ files instead of several pairs.
This reduces the boilerplate in build systems and simplifies user code overall (one module per ~.proto~ file). A
large internal refactor of ~ocaml-protoc~ was done prior to the integration of… _services_.

The major new feature of ~ocaml-protoc~ 3.0 is the support for service declarations. These are essentially [a
way](https://protobuf.dev/programming-guides/proto3/#services) to describe RPC endpoints, next to the types used to
interact with the endpoint
([example](https://github.com/mransan/ocaml-protoc/blob/master/src/examples/file_server.proto); [full generated
code](https://gist.github.com/c-cube/c76fecafeedf426c353e487c2e471354)). This is typically what it used in systems
such as [gRPC](https://grpc.io). Now ~ocaml-protoc~ generates server and client stubs for each endpoint, that pack
together the type definitions and the relevant (de)serializers; that code doesn't presume anything about a concrete
RPC system. I have in the works a simple [Twirp](https://github.com/twitchtv/twirp) [OCaml
library](https://github.com/c-cube/ocaml-twirp) that relies on this generated code to provide services over HTTP
1.1; It is also possible to write RPC systems over ZMQ, websockets, etc. without changes to the generated code[^1].

[^1]: note that twirp doesn't support stream RPC over HTTP 1.1. Other RPC systems can support these, e.g. gRPC
does.

Another big-ish change is how the generated code looks like, at least when it comes to binary (de)serialization.
~ocaml-protoc~ 3.0
 comes with significant speedups for encoding (up to twice the throughput; order of magnitude reduction in
allocations in some cases [^2]) and some less impressive speedups for decoding. This is a combination of multiple
changes:
- use of a few C stubs to accelerate varint decoding/encoding;
- encoding is done back-to-front, which allows the encoder to use a single slice internally[^3]. This is what required changes in the generated code in the first place;
- encoding code now requires a lot fewer closures (passing arguments explicitly instead) which reduces allocations to almost nothing.

I haven't recently benchmarked against other protobuf implementations in OCaml, but I'm reasonably confident that
this is now the fastest one by a healthy margin.

There are also other improvements and bugfixes. I want to thank in particular
[@Konstantin_Olkhovski](https://github.com/lupus) for some of these contributions and for very helpful discussions,
and also @VPhantom for more discussions on the topic of performance.

[^2]: if the encoder type is reused, there's almost no minor allocations, and no major allocations, to encode an
existing value into the encoder's buffer.

[^3]: because sub-messages use varint as their sizes, encoding front-to-back cannot be efficiently done in a single
buffer, because it's not clear how many bytes to reserve in front of a sub-message. With back-to-front that's not
an issue.

The [changelog](https://github.com/mransan/ocaml-protoc/releases/tag/v3.0.0) contains many more details.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
- [[https://gallium.inria.fr/blog/florian-cw-2023-12-11][Florian compiler weekly, 11 December 2023]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2023-12-05-international-disability-day-2023-why-it-matters][International Disability Day 2023: Why It Matters]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
