<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2024.01.16</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2024.01.09</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2024.01.23</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>January 09 to 16, 2024</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Verifying an Effect-Based Cooperative Concurrency Scheduler in Iris, by Adrian Dapprich</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/video-verifying-an-effect-based-cooperative-concurrency-scheduler-in-iris-by-adrian-dapprich/13825/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Vincent Balat announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Adrian Dapprich gave a talk at Tarides a few weeks ago, about Verifying an Effect-Based Cooperative Concurrency
Scheduler in Iris. Here is a link to the video.

Abstract:

#+begin_quote
Lightweight asynchronous programming (using futures, goroutines or green threads) has been widely adopted to
organize programs with many concurrent tasks, more than are traditionally feasible with thread-per-task models of
concurrency. With the release of OCaml 5 and its support for effect handlers, the new concurrency library Eio was
proposed which aims to replace previous monadic concurrency libraries for OCaml. In this work we verify the core
fiber and promise abstractions of Eio and show their safety and effect safety using the Hazel program logic.
Hazel is built on the Iris framework and allows reasoning about programs with effect handlers. We also adapt the
existing proof of the verified CQS datastructure since Eio uses a customized version of CQS for its
implementation of promises. We do not treat some features of Eio like cancellation, because it does not yield a
verifiable specification, and resource control using switches, since it is a liveness property.
#+end_quote

https://watch.ocaml.org/w/iQNqZzA8gVmd4RQaycAwx4
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml Software Foundation: January 2024 update</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-software-foundation-january-2024-update/13828/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>gasche announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Happy new year!

This is an update update on recent works of the [OCaml Software Foundation](http://ocaml-sf.org/), covering our
2023 actions -- the previous update was in [January
2023](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-software-foundation-january-2023-update/11217).

The OCaml Software Foundation is a non-profit foundation ([earlier
thread](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-the-ocaml-software-foundation/4476)) that receives funding from [our
industrial sponsors](http://ocaml-sf.org/#sponsors) each year, and tries its best to spend it to support and
strengthen the OCaml ecosystem and community.

The funding volume we receive each year is around 200K€. (For comparison: this is the yearly cost of one
experienced full-time software engineer in many parts of the world.) We do not fund people full-time for long
periods. Most actions receive from 3K€ to 20K€.
The work to prepare and execute actions is mostly done by the (unpaid) [Executive
Committee](http://ocaml-sf.org/about-us/). It is currently formed by Nicolás Ojeda Bär, Damien Doligez, Xavier
Leroy, Kim Nguyễn, Virgile Prevosto and myself, with administrative personnel provided by
[INRIA](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Institute_for_Research_in_Computer_Science_and_Automation) and general
assistance by Alan Schmitt.

Our current sponsors (thanks!) are [ahrefs](https://ahrefs.com/), [Jane Street](https://janestreet.com/),
[Tezos](https://tezos.com/), [Bloomberg](https://bloomberg.com/), [Lexifi](https://lexifi.com/),
[SimCorp](https://simcorp.com/), [MERCE](https://www.mitsubishielectric-rce.eu/) and
[Tarides](https://tarides.com/). (If your company would like to join as a sponsor, please [get in
touch](http://ocaml-sf.org/becoming-a-sponsor/). Unfortunately, we still cannot efficiently process small
donations, so we are not calling for individual donations.)

Feel free to use this thread for questions/suggestions :-)

*Recent actions*

*** Teaching

We are funding an update and English translation (still in progress) of the French book [Apprendre à Programmer
avec OCaml](http://programmer-avec-ocaml.lri.fr/), by Sylvain Conchon and Jean-Christophe Filliâtre, under the
understanding that it will be released as open access content -- online, at no cost. This is a good book that is
suitable for use in classroom of first- or second-year university students of various level. (In comparison, [OCaml
from the Very Beginning](https://johnwhitington.net/ocamlfromtheverybeginning/index.html) and [Real World
OCaml](https://dev.realworldocaml.org/) are more aimed as self-study than use in classroom, and the [Cornell CS3110
textbook](https://cs3110.github.io/textbook/cover.html) is aimed at more advanced students with a strong
background.)

For the second year in a row, we funded a Spanish [summer school](https://webdiis.unizar.es/evpf/index.html) on
functional programming in OCaml, organized in Saragossa by Ricardo Rodriguez and Roberto Blanco. This is an
occasion for students to discover OCaml and functional programming, and the organizers also run a one-day
mini-workshop for the students and anyone interested (including online), the [Day of the
Caml](https://webdiis.unizar.es/evpf/event.html).

*** Outreach

We are funding the recurring [OCaml Meetup in Paris](https://discuss.ocaml.org/tag/oups); this year we are also
funding a new meetup in Toulouse, a city in the south-west region of France known for duck cuisine, white beans,
and strong aerospace industry. If you are interested in organizing an OCaml meetup in your city, and some light
funding would help, please get in touch!

We got in touch with the organizers of the ICFP 2023 conference to ensure that colocated workshops (which include
the OCaml Workshop) can be attended online at low or no cost. The ICFP organizers accepted to (semi-officially)
make virtual attendance free, so we tried to [encourage broad
participation](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-workshop-2023-saturday-september-9th-seattle-timezone-online-attendance-is-free/12226)
to the OCaml Workshop. We also supported the OCaml Workshop by funding the expenses of some of the program
committee members to attend, when they do not have an employer in academia or industry that can easily reimburse
their trip.

We are supporting the work of Alan Schmitt on the [Caml Weekly Newsletter
(CWN)](https://alan.petitepomme.net/cwn/).

Kim Nguyễn ran the [OCaml User Survey 2023](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocaml-user-survey-2023/13469) for the
OCaml Foundation -- we have not posted the survey results yet.

We invited Sudha Parimala to propose more actions oriented towards diversity and inclusion. A first step is the
inclusion of demographic questions in the 2023 survey, to get a better picture of the current composition of the
OCaml community.

*** Ecosystem

**** Infrastructure

As in previous years, we are funding Kate Deplaix to work on "release readiness" of the OCaml ecosystem: when a new
OCaml release is being prepared, Kate checks the compatibility of all opam packages with the upcoming release and
gets in touch with maintainers to contribute or request support for the new version. The OCaml 5 transition has
been a lot of work for Kate on this front -- mostly not due to the Multicore runtime changes, but the removal of
various long-deprecated functions of our C and OCaml APIs.

For almost as long as we can remember, Kate Deplaix has also been the most active maintainer of the opam-repository
-- the person who provides feedback when there is a packaging issue in a new PR to the opam-repository, to
interpret CI failures, recommend best packaging practices, etc. (Kate's work on this topic was funded by OCamllabs
then Tarides, not the OCaml Foundation.) Kate decided recently to move on to other things -- notably, contributions
to ~opam~. (There was a [call for
volunteers](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/call-for-new-opam-repository-maintainers/12041/8) on Discuss around that
time.) This was a bit of a scare for us as the good health of the public opam-repository is central to the
functioning of the current OCaml free software ecosystem. We were already providing financial support (in the form
of research funding) to Marcello Seri, the second most-active contributor, and renewed our support. We also got in
touch with other opam-repository contributors, and started funding the work of Haochen Xie.

**** Tools

We got in touch with frequent Dune contributors to offer financial support for their contributions. [Ali
Caglayan](https://github.com/Alizter) was supported in this way in 2023.

We are supporting some of the work of Jonah Beckford on Windows support of OCaml, as well as his work on mentoring
OCaml students in the Seattle area. If you want to learn about Jonah's work, consider watching [his April 2023
talk](https://hfpug.org/2023/04/21/jonah-beckford-what-distributing-ocaml-on-windows-gave-me-and-you/) at the
Houston Functional Programmers meetup.

Simmo Saan spontaneously [took up maintenance of
ocamlearlybird](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-earlybird-1-2-0-revival-of-a-debugger/12741), the bytecode debugger
frontend that integrates with visual studio code -- we had previously funded ocamlearlybird maintenance, but its
Wen moved to a demanding startup and was not available to work on ocamlearlybird anymore. We are funding the time
of Simmo Saan, who accomplished a lot in a short amount of time, notably the integration of the ocamlearlybird
plugin in the main OCaml plugin for vscode.

We will be funding one year of post-doc by [Takafumi Saikawa](https://github.com/t6s) at Nagoya University, to
continue his work with Jacques Garrigue on the refactoring of the OCaml type-checker. The type-checker codebase
suffers from technical debt, and the effort led by Jacques in the last few year has been precious in making it
easier to understand, improve and extend for other developers.

**** Libraries

We funded work by Alan Hu to improve the OCaml LLVM bindings, to support newer LLVM releases and make them
compatible with OCaml 5. Alan [announced this work](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-llvm-15-is-out/13019) on
Discuss.

We support the contributions of Daniel Bünzli to the OCaml ecosystem. Daniel used this support to fund the
development of

- [cmarkit](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-cmarkit-0-1-0-commonmark-parser-and-renderer-for-ocaml/11900), a new Markdown parser and renderer for OCaml, and [ocamlmark](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/poc-ocamlmark-an-ocamldoc-to-commonmark-bi-directional-translation/11901/2) a tool to use Markdown to write OCaml documentation comments,
- [WebGPU support in brr](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/poc-ocamlmark-an-ocamldoc-to-commonmark-bi-directional-translation/11901/2), his browser interaction toolkit
- support for Unicode 15.0 and 15.1 in his Unicode libraries
- [zipc](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-zipc-0-1-0/13388), a pure-OCaml ZIP archiver.

We continued providing partial support for the work of Antonio Monteiro on [Melange](https://melange.re/v2.2.0/).
In 2023, Antonio [announced Melange
1.0](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-melange-1-0-compile-ocaml-reasonml-to-javascript/12305).

We are supporting the work of Petter Urkedal on the [Caqti](https://github.com/paurkedal/ocaml-caqti/) library, the
main database connection library in the OCaml community. [Caqti
2](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-caqti-2-0-1/12885) was released in 2023.

We will be supporting the time of Nathan Rebours to [contribute to the
maintenance](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/welcoming-a-new-ppxlib-maintainer/13620) of
[ppxlib](https://github.com/ocaml-ppx/ppxlib).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Miou, a simple scheduler for OCaml 5</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-miou-a-simple-scheduler-for-ocaml-5/12963/13</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Calascibetta Romain announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm delighted to announce the [~beta2~](https://github.com/robur-coop/miou/releases/tag/v0.0.1_beta2) release of
Miou. This summarises the feedback we've received and specifies the API that this library should offer in terms of
scheduling.

As a reminder, Miou is intended to be simple and designed for developing services and integrating into a unikernel.
We were talking about implementing a library such as [happy-eyeballs](https://github.com/robur-coop/happy-eyeballs)
with Miou, but we have now made available a library that implements [an HTTP client and/or
server](https://github.com/robur-coop/httpcats) (~http/1.1~, ~h2~ as well as ~alpn~ support via
[ocaml-tls](https://github.com/mirleft/ocaml-tls/)).

This has enabled us to find bugs typical of a transition between OCaml 4 and OCaml 5, in particular illegal
parallel access to data on [mirage-crypto](https://github.com/mirage/mirage-crypto/pull/186) (although we would
like to observe the implications in terms of performance of our fix).

We will of course continue to listen and experiment with Miou in order to develop this library in a way that suits
us and our users. The documentation has been updated accordingly and is now available
[here](https://docs.osau.re/).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Grace 💅, fancy diagnostic library for compilers</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-grace-fancy-diagnostic-library-for-compilers/13834/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Alistair O'Brien announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It is my pleasure to announce the initial release of [Grace](https://github.com/johnyob/grace), a cutting-edge
OCaml library 🐪 that includes a series of interfaces for building, reporting, and rendering beautiful compiler
diagnostics.

To get started, simply run:
#+begin_src shell
opam update
opam install grace
#+end_src

*Key features*
- 📐 Inline and multi-line error messages with associated priorities
- 📂 Multi-file errors
- ⚙️ Configurable rendering (styling and character set)
- 🌈 Coloured messages for ANSI terminals
- 💪 100% OCaml

The project is still in its early phase with many additional features planned:
- 📚 Unicode support
- ⚡️ LSP integration with ~linol~
- 👀 Accessibility features such improved colour options and narratable renderers

I invite the community to play with Grace, exploring its capabilities and limitations. Your insights will play a
crucial role in shaping the future of this library :)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Js_of_ocaml 5.5.2</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-js-of-ocaml-5-5-2/13581/2</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Hhugo announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Js_of_ocaml 5.6 was released recently with many fixes related to its javascript parser/printer/minifier
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>First release of oma</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-first-release-of-oma/13845/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>François Pottier announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello,

It is my pleasure to announce the first release of Oma. This library offers an implementation of the
order maintenance data structure described in [this
paper](https://erikdemaine.org/papers/DietzSleator_ESA2002/paper.pdf).

#+begin_src shell
  opam update
  opam install oma
#+end_src

Here is its [documentation](http://cambium.inria.fr/~fpottier/oma/doc/oma/Oma/index.html).

Happy hacking!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Ocamlearlybird just got ability to inspect opaque/abstract values</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocamlearlybird-just-got-ability-to-inspect-opaque-abstract-values/13852/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>文宇祥 announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I'm pleased to announce the release of ocamlearlybird.1.3.0. It should soon be able available in opam.

A big feature just landed. You can inspect opaque/abstract values since version 1.3.0.

see https://github.com/hackwaly/ocamlearlybird/pull/53
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Validate - A New Library for Data Validation</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-validate-a-new-library-for-data-validation/13861/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Mateusz Ledwoń announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello!

I'm excited to announce the preview release of a new library called ~validate~! This library aims to make the
process of validating records, lists, or individual values more streamlined and efficient.

~validate~ operates through a PPX deriver that automatically generates validators using annotations. It comes with
an array of helper validation functions for different data types, making it versatile and easy to integrate into
your projects.

*Example Usage*:

Imagine you have a record type with various fields that need validation. With ~validate~, you can easily annotate
these fields and the library will handle the rest. For example:

#+begin_src ocaml
type my_record = {
  min : string; [@min_length 2]
  email : string; [@email]
  uuid : string; [@uuid]
  url : string; [@url] [@max_length 200]
  numeric_list : int list; [@list_min_length 2] [@less_than 10]
  other_record: other; [@dive]
} [@@deriving validate]
#+end_src

This will automatically create a ~validate_my_record~ function, applying the specified validations to each field.

*Installation*:
You can install ~validate~ using OPAM:

Copy code

#+begin_example
opam install validate
#+end_example
I encourage you to try it out, and your feedback and contributions are invaluable at this stage.

For more details, please visit GitHub [repository](https://github.com/Axot017/validate ) and check out the
[documentation](https://axot017.github.io/validate/).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>dune.3.12.1</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-dune-3-12-1/13536/2</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Etienne Millon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
We just released version 3.12.2 with 2 bugfixes:

- Fix version check in ~runtest_alias~ for ~cram~ stanza (#9454, @emillon)
- Fix stack overflow when a ~(run)~ action can not be parsed. (#9530, fixes #9529, @gridbugs)
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[https://ocaml.org/blog/][the ocaml.org blog]].

- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2024-01-10-meet-odoc-ocaml-s-documentation-generator][Meet odoc, OCaml's Documentation Generator]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
