<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2025.02.25</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2025.02.18</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2025.03.04</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>February 18 to 25, 2025</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Early work experimenting with zig as a cross-compiler for OCaml</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/early-work-experimenting-with-zig-as-a-cross-compiler-for-ocaml/16151/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Chris Armstrong announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
This is some early work [using zig as a cross-compiler](https://ruoyusun.com/2022/02/27/zig-cc.html) for building OCaml cross-compilation systems:

[opam-cross-lambda](https://github.com/chris-armstrong/opam-cross-lambda)

*Status*: It is currently severely untested but the aim is to be able to cross-compile to Linux from Windows/Mac/Linux for aarch64 and x86_64 CPU architectures simply by adding an opam repository, and without the need for nix.

*Why:* The novel aspect is zig, which allows you to cross-compile C code without needing to install or set up a cross-compilation sysroot i.e. glibc, gcc, binutils, kernel headers etc. as zig packages much of the needed headers and symbol information internally.

*Next steps:* start importing packages (including those with native binaries) into the opam repository overlay, validate them in CI/CD

This approach has led me down some rabbit-holes with a bunch of learning - some interesting points:

- zig uses clang internally, so its effectively testing clang compatibility with OCaml's autoconf + Makefile assumptions about the C compiler
- targeting windows isn't possible with this setup at this time, because flexdll hardcodes mingw binary names (e.g. x86_64-w64-mingw32-gcc) in its Makefile and the flexlink binary (it assumes these exist because targeting mingw32 is always a cross-compilation, even on Windows). It also depends on binutils' windres, which zig does not provide a wrapper for.
- targeting macos x is untested
- as you can see in the CI/CD scripts, setting the ZIG cache directory environment variables is crucial for MacOS because of opam's sandboxing (zig builds its cache in the user's home directory, which is outside the default sandbox)
- although ocamlfind and dune have some cross-compilation support with "toolchains", there are gaps and undocumented assumption
- opam doesn't really support cross-compilation environments well - packages often don't require much change, but you do need to create a ~&lt;package&gt;-cross-&lt;cross-name&gt;~ version of every single package - this could be a lot more straightforward and less work with a more cohesive platform strategy for cross-compilation

*Alternatives*: I'm aware of alternatives in the ecosystem (and indeed have benefitted from):

- [ocaml nix overlays](https://github.com/nix-ocaml/nix-overlays) - these offer a far better tested and reproducible cross-compilation environment, mostly for systems that can run nix
- [opam-cross-windows](https://github.com/ocaml-cross/opam-cross-windows/tree/main/packages) - lots of little nuggets of build-time information found in here
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Dune dev meeting</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-dune-dev-meeting/14994/24</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, art-w announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Thanks everyone for joining! The meetings notes are here: https://github.com/ocaml/dune/wiki/dev-meeting-2025-02-19
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Outreachy June 2025</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/outreachy-june-2025/16154/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Patrick Ferris announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi everyone!

Once again, the OCaml community has signed up to Outreachy (see [past](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/outreachy-summer-2023/11159) [posts](https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/outreachy-december-2024-round/15223))!

** What is Outreachy?

Outreachy is a paid, remote internship program. Outreachy promotes diversity in open source and open science. Our internships are for people who face under-representation, and discrimination or systemic bias in the technology industry of their country.

The current round is still ongoing with an intern making great progress on [ocaml-api-watch](https://github.com/ocaml-semver/ocaml-api-watch) with @NathanReb and @panglesd. 

*** Important Dates 

For this next round, the important dates are as follows (these are always subject to some change):

- Feb 26 - Community sign up deadline :white_check_mark: 
- Mar 7 - [Mentor project description deadline](https://www.outreachy.org/communities/cfp/ocaml/)
- Mar 10 to Apr 8 - Contribution period
- Jun 2 to Aug 29 - Internship period

Our next deadline is for mentors to sign up to the OCaml community with a project idea. Please do consider being an Outreachy mentor. If you have any questions or ideas you can always reach out to me directly. If you need a refresher of past projects, there's a dedicated page on the OCaml website: https://ocaml.org/outreachy. 

The OCaml community is currently able to financially support Outreachy internships thanks to the generous support of [Tarides](https://tarides.com) and [Janestreet](https://www.janestreet.com).

Thanks! :camel:
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Js_of_ocaml 6.0.1 / Wasm_of_ocaml</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-js-of-ocaml-6-0-1-wasm-of-ocaml/16160/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jérôme Vouillon announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
I’m pleased to announce the joint release of js_of_ocaml 6.0.1 and wasm_of_ocaml.

Js_of_ocaml is a compiler from OCaml bytecode to JavaScript. It makes it possible to run pure OCaml programs in JavaScript environment like browsers and Node.js.

[Wasm_of_ocaml](https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/wasm_of_ocaml-compiler/) is a compiler from OCaml bytecode to WebAssembly. It is highly compatible with Js_of_ocaml, so you can compile your programs with wasm_of_ocaml instead of js_of_ocaml and experience overall better performance. It is [supported by Dune 3.17](https://dune.readthedocs.io/en/stable/wasmoo.html), making the switch very easy.

Most significant changes in js_of_ocaml:
- The conversion between Javascript numbers and OCaml floats is now explicit, using functions ~Js.float~ and ~Js.to_float~ (this is necessary for wasm_of_ocaml which does not use the same representation for JS numbers and OCaml floats)
- ~Dom_html~ has been modernized, removing some no longer relevant ~Js.optdef~ type annotations
- Effects:
  * add an optional feature of "dynamic switching" between CPS and direct style, resulting in better performance when no effect handler is installed
  * make resuming a continuation more efficient

See the [Changelog](https://github.com/ocsigen/js_of_ocaml/blob/master/CHANGES.md) for other changes.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Olivier Nicole then added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Regarding wasm_of_ocaml, Tarides also just posted [a blog
post](https://tarides.com/blog/2025-02-19-the-first-wasm-of-ocaml-release-is-out/) with some more details about its recent
developments, and what kind of performance gains have been observed with it.

I want to insist that building your project to Wasm can be as simple as enabling the ~wasm~ mode in dune. To quote the documentation
page cited by Jérôme:

#+begin_example
(executable (name foo) (modes wasm))
#+end_example

And then request the .wasm.js target:

#+begin_example
$ dune build ./foo.bc.wasm.js
$ node _build/default/foo.bc.wasm.js
hello from wasm
#+end_example
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Bytecode debugging in OCaml 5.3</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/bytecode-debugging-in-ocaml-5-3/16177/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>gasche announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Today I conducted a small experiment of using a debugger on a small OCaml program (built using ~dune~). The program is not written by me, does non-trivial things, and is written in such a way that my usual approaches to understand what is going on would require more work than I want to pour in it.

I took notes on this experience, in the hope that it could be of interest to others -- maybe I'm doing things wrong and people will let me know, maybe this can help identify potential tooling improvements.

Disclaimer: I am a complete beginner as far as running OCaml debuggers goes. (I have used ~ocamldebug~ and ~gdb~ irregularly in the past, never heaily, and long forgotten how to use them.)

*** TL;DR:

Bytecode debugging with OCaml 5.3 and dune:

- works fine in Emacs/Tuareg, as it did in the past
- works okay in vscode using ocamlearlybird
- could be improved with a bit more targeted work,
  some of it probably easy (and some of it hard)

If I understand correctly, no one is specifically working on this right now.
Let me take this occasion to thank the people who contributed to all these tools (Tuareg, ocamldebug, ocamlearlybird, vscode+ocaml integration, dune, etc.).

*** Why a debugger?

I am looking at an OCaml program that I did not write, and does interesting and complex things. I would like to build my understanding of how it works by observing the flow of values in some parts of the program, on concrete examples of interest.

I am unfamiliar with debuggers and tried other things first:

1. I considered modifying the code to print the values it encouters at runtime. But the program does not define pretty-printers for its values, and writing them is cumbersome. (I could probably use ~deriving~ to produce debuggers more easily.)

2. My next move is usually ~dune utop~: instead of running the program, I can call its library functions via the toplevel on small examples. But this particular program is only a binary, it was not split as a library and a binary, and splitting it would be non-trivial.

When "printf debugging" and "play in the toplevel" are not immediately within reach, it may be time to try a debugger. They should let us stop at a given point in the program, print values, and move around in the execution trace to better understand what is going on.

*** Running a debugger in general

To run a debugger on OCaml programs, one has to choose between a bytecode debugger, ~ocamldebug~, and native debuggers such as ~gdb~ and ~lldb~.

Native debuggers are not OCaml-specific and likely to be better documented, have more integrated tooling etc., but they are more low-level and don't know as much about OCaml programs; in particular they're not so good at printing values.

On the other hand ~ocamldebug~ can print OCaml values, and it is a time-travel debugger that supports going backward in time; but it relies on running the bytecode executable that is probably 10x slower than the native executable. It is also probably worse when debugging cross-language programs, for example using the FFI.

I would not try ~ocamldebug~ to debug performance-sensitive programs, programs in production, and in particular to debug anything resembling a segmentation fault. But it should offer a nice experience for pure-OCaml programs during their development.

The Coq/Rocq maintainers have long been using ~ocamldebug~ to understand their software, a large OCaml program with tricky bugs and non-trivial performance requirements. They rely on specific tooling to make it nicer -- autoloaded scripts, customized pretty-printers. So there is evidence that ~ocamldebug~ can work well when integrated inside a project development workflow. (Here the program I want to debug has /not/ had any such written, so it will be more barebones.)

*** Getting a bytecode executable from Dune

Before going any further, you need to ask ~dune~ to generate bytecode executables, by adding

#+begin_example
 (modes byte exe)
#+end_example

to the ~executable~ stanza. Then you run ~dune build~, and when invoking the debugger you will need to manually pass the path to the bytecode program, for example ~_build/default/bin/main.bc~.

*** IDE integration

Running ~ocamldebug~ directly is doable but not great. Just like it's
nice when IDEs let you jump to the location of a compilation error,
you really want the debugger to show you "where" it is in the program
execution by showing you a program point in your programming
editor. (~ocamldebug~ will print the source line where it is at, so
it's not too bad, but still noticeably less pleasant, and typing
movement commands one by one gets old fast.)

I considered two approaches to running a bytecode debugger for OCaml programs:
- run ~ocamldebug~ from Emacs/Tuareg
- run ~ocamlearlybird~ from VsCode

**** ocamlearlybird in vscode

I first decided to use ocamlearlybird from vscode.

I opened vscode (which is not my usual editor) and tried to use ~Run > start debugging~ directly... and it didn't work well. You need to configure things manually, and the vscode interface did not tell me that, it would show nothing and appear not to work as expected but without much help.

The better way to configure vscode+earlybird is to... read the documentation first. I recommend:

1. Read the [vscode-ocaml-platform README.md](https://github.com/ocamllabs/vscode-ocaml-platform#debugging-ocaml-programs-experimental) about how to setup things.
2. then read the [ocamlearlybird README](https://github.com/hackwaly/ocamlearlybird?tab=readme-ov-file) (which also links to the README above), in particular watch the short demo, to know what to expect when the interface works. The README documents the field of the ~launch.json~ file that you have to write to describe how to invoke the debugger, and this is helpful.

After reading this, I knew how to tweak the ~launch.json~ file so that the debugger would pass command-line arguments to the program, and it started working correctly.

Unfortunately ~ocamlearlybird~ does not current support time-travel ([issue](https://github.com/hackwaly/ocamlearlybird/issues/78)), so it is only possible to stop at breakpoints and move forward in time, while I was expecting to run until a failure and then go backward in time, as I usually do with ~ocamldebug~. At this point I decided to go back to my familiar Emacs.

***** Points to improve

When trying to "run the debugger" without having configured a specific bytecode program, the vscode UI appears to work but does nothing. For example it is possible to add breakpoints, etc., and then clicking "run" does nothing that I can see.

I wish there was clearer feedback when things are not setup and there is no chance that it will work. This would also be a good time to point me to the online documentation -- from within the IDE -- so that the process is more discoverable.

**** ocamldebug in Emacs

At this point I had already set things up to build a bytecode executable in Dune, so things were easy: ~M-x ocamldebug~ and there you go. There is [documentation in the user manual](https://ocaml.org/manual/5.3/debugger.html), which was probably written more than a decade ago, and it mostly reads just fine today.

(Note: some of the documented keybindings do not work: ~C-c C-k~ is documented as stepping back in the manual, but it is not supported by Tuareg ([issue](https://github.com/ocaml/tuareg/pull/227)).)

Moving around program execution is fun, printing values works okay -- the next step for convenience would be to install custom printers to get nice output.

***** Points to improve

1. Emacs jumps to source code to follow the program execution in the debugger; but on every movement in the execution trace it asks me again whether I want ~src/foo.ml~ instead of ~_build/default/src/foo.ml~, and this is annoying. (Sometimes I did not observe this behavior, not sure why.)

2. Dune includes various wrapping/mangling of module names that show up in the ~ocamldebug~ printing, and can be annoying at time. For example some module names show up as ~Dune__exe.Foo~, and I would prefer to see just ~Foo~. I think it should be possible to hard-code some more de-Dune-mangling logic in the debugger's pretty-printer, and ideally we could even make them user-configurable or dune-configurable a bit.

3. If I print an AST from an execution point that does not have ~open Ast~ in its typing environment, the AST is printed like ~Dune__exe.Ast.Let (Dune__exe.Ast.Var "x", ...)~. It would be nice to omit the ~Dunne__exe~ part, but ideally I should also be able to tell the debugger: "let's open ~Ast~ locally from now on when you print values", so that it prints in a more readable way by default.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Vincent Laviron replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Nice post, thanks !
        
A few things I would like to add:
- Time travelling is possible for the native debuggers with ~rr~. At some point it was Linux-only, it might still be the case, but it's /very/ nice to use. I have on some occasions debugged bytecode programs by using ~rr~ on it, and with the appropriate gdb/lldb macros to print OCaml values it can be useful (but mostly for debugging the C parts; for problems purely on the OCaml side ~ocamldebug~ is still better suited). I use it regularly for native debugging and it's very convenient (it can even help with debugging eisenbugs in parallel programs ! Just run ~rr record ./my_program~ several times until the bug triggers, and then ~rr replay~ will always replay the same run, including thread interleavings, consistently reproducing the bug).
- I have tried time travelling with ~ocamldebug~ in the past and I have hit some serious issues: limited history means that you cannot go very far in the past, and the way it works (by setting checkpoints and replaying from the checkpoint to the required instruction) means that you can often see weird artifacts due to C calls being replayed each time you step back, sometimes breaking the program completely. I'm curious to know if this is just bad luck (or me doing weird things), or if you had similar issues too.
- The ~Dune__exe~ stuff is, I believe, ~dune~'s misguided attempt to shield users from potential conflicts between files linked in the executable and modules with the same name present in non-wrapped libraries required as dependencies. I suspect that ~(wrapped false)~ or something like that in the section of the dune file corresponding to the executable will get rid of it.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Tim McGilchrist also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
It is possible to use ~ocamlearlybird~ with ~dap-mode~ in Emacs [link](https://lambdafoo.com/posts/2024-03-25-ocaml-debugging-with-emacs.html). The setup uses the same json config file as VSCode. I'm putting my effort into DAP support since that gets cross editor support and I can switch between LLDB/ocamlearlybird. 

For Emacs the two main options for DAP support are:
 * dap-mode, which ties into lsp-mode and follows that style of things. Uses JSON configuration based off VSCode configuration. The UI elements depend on lsp-mode, so it's a heavier setup and might not play as well with eglot.
 * dape, standalone DAP mode with a more minimal approach. I didn't get it working satisfactorily but it seems closer to eglot in philosophy https://github.com/svaante/dape

For both I see the challenges are:
 1. Setting up DAP itself reliably and with less fuss. It could be smoother and better documented.
 2. Setting up dune builds to generate the right artifacts. Having a direct LSP code action to run a debugger against a particular executable like Rust does would be ideal.
 3. Bugs in ocamlearlybird and lack of maintainer time.

It's interesting to hear about users of bytecode debugging, I thought there wouldn't be many people using that.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Nicolas Ojeda Bar also replied</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
#+begin_quote
For example some module names show up as ~Dune__exe.Foo~, and I would prefer to see just ~Foo~.
#+end_quote

This is controlled by ~(wrapped_executables &lt;bool&gt;)~ in ~dune-project~: https://dune.readthedocs.io/en/latest/reference/dune-project/wrapped_executables.html
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>New F* release on opam (2025.02.17)</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-new-f-release-on-opam-2025-02-17/16179/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Chandradeep Dey announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello! It is my pleasure to announce that F* is once again available on opam for direct installation after a long time. This probably does not mean much to regular users, as there were regular releases on GitHub for some time now. However, the opam release offers a convenient alternative by eliminating the need to separately set up OCaml to compile extracted OCaml code.

From the [website](https://fstar-lang.org/) -
F* is a general-purpose proof-oriented programming language, supporting both purely functional and effectful programming. It combines the expressive power of dependent types with proof automation based on SMT solving and tactic-based interactive theorem proving.

The biggest new thing worth mentioning is perhaps the Pulse DSL for programming with concurrent separation logic. A tutorial is available in the F* book, Proof-oriented Programming in F*. A comprehensive overview of various projects that have utilized F* over the years can also be found on the website.

Feel free to join the [Zulip forum](https://fstar.zulipchat.com/) for discussions with the developers, researchers, and casual users. Happy writing provably correct programs!
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[https://ocaml.org/blog/][the ocaml.org blog]].

- [[https://choum.net/panglesd/undo-monad/#step2torevisit][How I fixed Slipshow's worst flaw using OCaml and a monad]]
- [[https://tarides.com/blog/2025-02-19-the-first-wasm-of-ocaml-release-is-out][The First Wasm_of_ocaml Release is Out!]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
