<cwn>
  <cwn_head>
    <cwn_date>2026.01.06</cwn_date>
    <cwn_prev>2025.12.30</cwn_prev>
    <cwn_next>2026.01.13</cwn_next>
    <cwn_date_text>December 30, 2025 to January 06, 2026</cwn_date_text>
  </cwn_head>
  <cwn_body>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Announcing the first release of Alice, a radical OCaml build system</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/announcing-the-first-release-of-alice-a-radical-ocaml-build-system/17472/20</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Steve Sherratt announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[Alice v0.3.0](https://www.alicecaml.org/blog/alice-v0-3-0/) is out! This introduces a breaking change which is that Alice now follows the [XDG Base Directory Spec](https://specifications.freedesktop.org/basedir/latest/) in lieu of creating a ~~/.alice~ directory.

To migrate from an older version:
- Delete ~~/.alice~.
- If you have a block in your shell config starting with ~# BEGIN configuration from Alice installer~, remove that block.
- If you installed Alice with the installation script then run the script again (instructions [here](https://www.alicecaml.org/install)).
- If you used Alice to install OCaml tools, you'll need to reinstall those tools (run ~alice tools install~).
- If you've configured a custom sandbox template with Visual Studio Code for any Alice projects, change the template based on the new LSP instructions for Visual Studio Code [here](https://www.alicecaml.org/lsp/#visual-studio-code).

To enable bash/zsh completions for Alice, source the appropriate file from ~~/.local/share/alice/env~.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Steve Sherratt later added</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
[Alice v0.4.0](https://www.alicecaml.org/blog/alice-v0-4-0/) is out. The main change is that package manifests now use [KDL](https://kdl.dev/) instead of TOML. See [this post](https://www.alicecaml.org/blog/switching-manifests-to-kdl/) for the motivation for this change. There's a migration guide [here](https://www.alicecaml.org/blog/alice-v0-4-0/#migrating-from-earlier-versions).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>OCaml/opam package manager support for Dependabot - I need your help</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-opam-package-manager-support-for-dependabot-i-need-your-help/17656/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Jakub Polak announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hello OCaml community! 😊

Let's kick off the new year with something exciting! I just created a Pull Request to dependabot-core that adds support for Opam in OCaml. This could be super useful for all of us using this ecosystem in our projects!

https://github.com/dependabot/dependabot-core/pull/13877

But the Dependabot maintainers emphasized that maintaining new ecosystems requires community support (check their comment here: [https://github.com/dependabot/dependabot-core/pull/13711#issuecomment-3659899321](https://github.com/dependabot/dependabot-core/pull/13711?referrer=grok.com#issuecomment-3659899321)). They already have 3 community-maintained ecosystems and want more, but only if the community helps with long-term updater support.

They will be looking for volunteers to help maintain this – in testing, fixes, or ongoing maintenance. We can push this together if you really want it.

What do you think?
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>shakuhachi 0.1.0 - A music collection manager</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-shakuhachi-0-1-0-a-music-collection-manager/17659/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>EruEri announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Dear all,

I humbly announce shakuhachi `0.1.0`.

Shakuhachi is a music collection manager. It aims to be a rather simple collection manager extensible by plugins. It organizes musics into an artist/album directory structure, can handle multiple collections and provides a mechanism similar to ~GitHub - beetbox/beet~ for querying a collection.  Shakuhachi also exposes some of its internals which allows to hook it inside other applications.

You can visit the source code at [codeberg - erueri/shakuhachi](https://codeberg.org/EruEri/shakuhachi).

You can also see an example of integrating shakuhachi inside a C++ music player [codeberg - erueri/audacious-skhc-plugin](https://codeberg.org/EruEri/audacious-skhc-plugin).

Sincerely yours.
      </cwn_what>
      <cwn_who>Christian Lindig later said</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
- https://github.com/rossberg/camp

This is an MP3 player that claims to have good library management - maybe worth a comparison.
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>.mlx syntax dialect</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-mlx-syntax-dialect/15035/22</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Continuing this thread, Andrey Popp announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Some updates from .mlx team (@davesnx and me): 

- mlx 0.11 is released, OCaml 5.4 support + some lexer improvements
- ocamlformat-mlx 0.28.1 is released, OCaml 5.4 support + formatting improvements
- ocaml-lsp-server and vscode’s OCaml Platform extension now have first class support for .mlx
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>ocaml-posix release 4.0.0</cwn_title>
      <cwn_url>https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ann-ocaml-posix-release-4-0-0/17670/1</cwn_url>
      <cwn_who>Romain Beauxis announced</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Hi there!

I’m happy to report the release of ~ocaml-posix~ version ~4.0.0~: https://github.com/savonet/ocaml-posix

This collection of modules was started some time ago with the goal of centralizing and normalizing the patterns for binding constants, types (including C ~stuct~ ) and functions from the POSIX standard using ~ctypes~.

The goal is to offer:

- A common set of tools and practices for structuring and binding using ~ctypes~.
- APIs and modules suitable for low-level ~ctypes~ use.
- High level APIs and modules suitable for direct OCaml use.
- Multi platform compatibility: ~*BSD~, ~linux~, ~macos~ and ~windows~when available.
- Cross-platform compilation using ~dune~'s awesome cross-compilation support when applicable (currently only ~posix-errno~and ~posix-socket~)

With this release, 4 new modules have been added:

- ~posix-errno~ to deal with unix error numbers. Although there are some alternatives already existing, this one is a more straight-forward and modern implementation using ~dune~ for building with cross-compilation and multi-platform support.
- ~posix-stat~, ~posix-resource~ and the extensive ~posix-unistd~.

Hopefully these modules can be useful to more developers and provide a common platform for interfacing OCaml programs with system calls in a portable and extensible way!

*** FAQ:

- Why is this not using ~dune~'s direct support for ~ctypes~?

Cross-compilation support requires running binary compiled for the target (e.g. ~windows~) on the host (e.g. ~linux~) in order to extract specific data points such as C constants values and C struct entries offset. Currently, this is not supported using ~dune~' builtin ~ctypes~ support. However, support for this is [being worked on](https://github.com/ocaml/dune/pull/13112).
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
    <cwn_entry>
      <cwn_title>Other OCaml News</cwn_title>
      <cwn_who>From the ocaml.org blog</cwn_who>
      <cwn_what>
Here are links from many OCaml blogs aggregated at [[https://ocaml.org/blog/][the ocaml.org blog]].

- [[https://soap.coffee/~lthms/posts/i-cannot-ssh-into-my-server-anymore.html][I Cannot SSH Into My Server Anymore (And That’s Fine)]]
- [[https://www.tunbury.org/2025/12/31/ocaml-pico/][Multi Domain OCaml on Raspberry Pi Pico 2 Microcontroller]]
      </cwn_what>
    </cwn_entry>
  </cwn_body>
</cwn>
